^ (Prov. 7:1-11:31) My son, keep my sayings, And treasure up my commandments.  2 Keep my commandments and live; Guard my instruction* like the pupil of your eye.  3 Tie them around your fingers; Write them on the tablet of your heart.  4 Say to wisdom, “You are my sister,” And call understanding “my relative,”  5 To guard you against the wayward* woman, Against the immoral* woman and her smooth* words.  6 From the window of my house, Through my lattice, I looked down,  7 And as I observed the naive* ones, I discerned among the youths a young man lacking good sense.*  8 He passed along the street near her corner, And he marched in the direction of her house  9 In the twilight, in the evening, At the approach of night and darkness. 10 Then I saw a woman meet him, Dressed like* a prostitute, with a cunning heart. 11 She is loud and defiant. She never stays* at home. 12 One moment she is outside, next she is in the public squares, She lurks near every corner. 13 She grabs hold of him and gives him a kiss; With a bold face, she says to him: 14 “I had to offer communion sacrifices. Today I paid my vows. 15 That is why I came out to meet you, To look for you, and I found you! 16 I have spread fine covers upon my bed, Colorful linen from Egypt. 17 I have sprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon. 18 Come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning; Let us enjoy passionate love together, 19 For my husband is not at home; He has gone on a distant journey. 20 He took a bag of money with him, And he will not return until the day of the full moon.” 21 She misleads him with great persuasiveness. She seduces him with smooth speech. 22 Suddenly he goes after her, like a bull to the slaughter, Like a fool to be punished in the stocks,* 23 Until an arrow pierces his liver; Like a bird rushing into a trap, he does not know that it will cost him his life.* 24 And now, my sons, listen to me; Pay attention to the words I speak. 25 Do not let your heart turn aside to her ways. Do not stray onto her paths, 26 For she has caused many to fall down slain, And those she has killed are numerous. 27 Her house leads to the Grave;* It goes down to the inner chambers of death.

8 Is not wisdom calling out? Is not discernment raising its voice?  2 On the heights along the road, It takes its position at the crossroads.  3 Next to the gates leading into the city, At the entrances of the doorways, It keeps crying out loudly:  4 “To you, O people, I am calling; I raise my voice to everyone.*  5 You inexperienced ones, learn shrewdness; You stupid ones, acquire an understanding heart.*  6 Listen, for what I say is important, My lips speak what is right;  7 For my mouth softly utters truth, And my lips detest what is wicked.  8 All the sayings of my mouth are righteous. None of them are twisted or crooked.  9 They are all straightforward to the discerning And right to those who have found knowledge. 10 Take my discipline instead of silver, And knowledge rather than the finest gold, 11 For wisdom is better than corals;* All other desirable things cannot compare to it. 12 I, wisdom, dwell together with shrewdness; I have found knowledge and thinking ability. 13 The fear of Jehovah means the hating of bad. I hate self-exaltation and pride and the evil way and perverse speech. 14 I possess good advice and practical wisdom; Understanding and power are mine. 15 By me kings keep reigning, And high officials decree righteousness. 16 By me princes keep ruling, And nobles judge in righteousness. 17 I love those loving me, And those seeking me will find me. 18 Riches and glory are with me, Lasting wealth* and righteousness. 19 My fruitage is better than gold, even refined gold, And what I produce is better than the finest silver. 20 I walk in the path of righteousness, In the middle of the pathways of justice; 21 I give a rich inheritance to those who love me, And I fill up their storehouses. 22 Jehovah produced me as the beginning of his way, The earliest of his achievements of long ago. 23 From ancient times* I was installed, From the start, from times earlier than the earth. 24 When there were no deep waters, I was brought forth,* When there were no springs overflowing with water. 25 Before the mountains were set in place, Before the hills, I was brought forth, 26 When he had not yet made the earth and its fields Or the first clods of earth’s soil. 27 When he prepared the heavens, I was there; When he marked out the horizon* on the surface of the waters, 28 When he established* the clouds above, When he founded the fountains of the deep, 29 When he set a decree for the sea That its waters should not pass beyond his order, When he established* the foundations of the earth, 30 Then I was beside him as a master worker. I was the one he was especially fond of day by day; I rejoiced before him all the time; 31 I rejoiced over his habitable earth, And I was especially fond of the sons of men.* 32 And now, my sons, listen to me; Yes, happy are those who keep my ways. 33 Listen to discipline and become wise, And never neglect it. 34 Happy is the man who listens to me By coming early to* my doors day by day, By waiting next to my doorposts; 35 For the one finding me will find life, And he receives approval from Jehovah. 36 But the one who ignores me harms himself,* And those who hate me love death.”

9 True wisdom has built its house; It has carved* out its seven pillars.  2 It has fully prepared its meat;* It has mixed its wine; It has also arranged its table.  3 It has sent out its female servants To call out from the heights above the city:  4 “Whoever is inexperienced, let him come in here.” She says to the one lacking good sense:*  5 “Come, eat my bread And share in drinking the wine that I have mixed.  6 Leave behind your inexperience* and live; Walk forward in the way of understanding.”  7 The one who corrects a ridiculer invites dishonor, And whoever reproves someone wicked will get hurt.  8 Do not reprove a ridiculer, or he will hate you. Reprove a wise person, and he will love you.  9 Share with a wise person, and he will become wiser. Teach someone righteous, and he will add to his learning. 10 The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom, And knowledge of the Most Holy One is understanding. 11 For by me your days will be many, And years will be added to your life. 12 If you become wise, you are wise to your own advantage, But if you are a ridiculer, you alone will bear it. 13 A stupid woman is loud. She is ignorant and knows absolutely nothing. 14 She sits at the entrance of her house On a seat in the high places of the city, 15 Calling out to those passing by, To those walking straight ahead on their way: 16 “Whoever is inexperienced, let him come in here.” She says to those lacking good sense:* 17 “Stolen waters are sweet, And food eaten in secret is pleasant.” 18 But he does not know that those powerless in death are there, That her guests are in the depths of the Grave.*

10 Proverbs of Solʹo·mon. A wise son makes his father rejoice, But a foolish son is the grief of his mother.  2 The treasures gained by wickedness will be of no benefit, But righteousness is what rescues from death.  3 Jehovah will not cause the righteous one* to go hungry, But he will deny the wicked what they crave.  4 Idle hands will cause poverty, But diligent hands bring riches.  5 The son acting with insight gathers the crop in summer, But the son acting shamefully is fast asleep during the harvest.  6 Blessings are on the head of the righteous one, But the mouth of the wicked conceals violence.  7 The memory* of the righteous one is due for a blessing, But the name of the wicked will rot.  8 The wisehearted person will accept instructions,* But the one speaking foolishly will be trodden down.  9 The one walking in integrity will walk in security, But the one making his ways crooked will be found out. 10 The one who slyly winks his eye causes grief, And the one who speaks foolishly will be trodden down. 11 The mouth of the righteous one is a source of life, But the mouth of the wicked conceals violence. 12 Hatred is what stirs up contentions, But love covers over all transgressions. 13 Wisdom is found on the lips of the discerning person, But the rod is for the back of one lacking good sense.* 14 Those who are wise treasure up knowledge, But the mouth of the fool invites ruin. 15 The wealth* of a rich man is his fortified city. The ruin of the poor is their poverty. 16 The activity of the righteous one leads to life; But the produce of the wicked one leads to sin. 17 The one who heeds discipline is a path to life,* But the one who ignores reproof leads others astray. 18 The one who conceals his hatred speaks lies, And the one spreading malicious reports* is stupid. 19 When words are many, transgression cannot be avoided, But whoever controls his lips acts discreetly. 20 The tongue of the righteous one is like the finest silver, But the heart of the wicked one is worth little. 21 The lips of the righteous one nourish* many, But the foolish die for lack of sense. 22 It is the blessing of Jehovah that makes one rich, And He adds no pain* with it. 23 Engaging in shameful conduct is like a game to the stupid one, But wisdom is for the man of discernment. 24 What the wicked one fears will come upon him; But the desire of the righteous will be granted. 25 When the storm passes by, the wicked one will be no more, But the righteous one is a foundation forever. 26 Like vinegar to the teeth and smoke to the eyes, So the lazy person is to the one who sends him.* 27 The fear of Jehovah prolongs life, But the years of the wicked will be cut short. 28 The expectation* of the righteous brings joy, But the hope of the wicked will perish. 29 The way of Jehovah is a stronghold for the blameless one, But it means ruin for evildoers. 30 The righteous one will never be made to fall, But the wicked will no longer inhabit the earth. 31 The mouth of the righteous one produces* wisdom, But the perverse tongue will be cut off. 32 The lips of the righteous one know what is pleasing, But the mouth of the wicked is perverse.

11 Dishonest* scales are detestable to Jehovah, But an accurate weight* brings pleasure to him.  2 When presumptuousness comes, dishonor will follow, But wisdom is with the modest ones.  3 The integrity of the upright is what guides them, But the deviousness of the treacherous will destroy them.  4 Wealth* will be of no benefit on the day of fury, But righteousness is what will rescue from death.  5 The righteousness of the blameless one makes his path straight, But the wicked one will fall because of his own wickedness.  6 The righteousness of the upright will rescue them, But the treacherous will be caught by their own desires.  7 When a wicked man dies, his hope perishes; And expectations based on his power also perish.  8 The righteous one is rescued from distress, And the wicked one takes his place.  9 By his mouth the apostate* brings his neighbor to ruin, But by knowledge the righteous are rescued. 10 The goodness of the righteous makes a city rejoice, And when the wicked perish, there is a joyful cry. 11 Because of the blessing of the upright a city is exalted, But the mouth of the wicked tears it down. 12 Whoever is lacking good sense* shows contempt for* his neighbor, But the man of true discernment remains silent. 13 A slanderer goes about revealing confidential talk, But the trustworthy person* keeps a confidence.* 14 When there is no skillful direction,* the people fall, But there is success* through many advisers.* 15 Whoever guarantees a loan* for a stranger is sure to fare badly, But whoever avoids* shaking hands in a pledge will be secure. 16 A gracious* woman acquires glory, But ruthless men seize riches. 17 A kind man* benefits himself,* But the cruel person brings trouble* on himself. 18 The wicked one earns deceptive wages, But the one who sows righteousness receives a true reward. 19 The one standing firmly for righteousness is in line for life, But the one chasing after evil is in line for death. 20 Those crooked at heart are detestable to Jehovah, But those whose way is blameless bring pleasure to him. 21 Be assured of this:* An evil person will not go unpunished, But the children of the righteous will escape. 22 Like a gold ring in the snout of a pig Is a beautiful woman who rejects good sense. 23 The desire of the righteous leads to good, But what the wicked hope for leads to fury. 24 One gives generously* and ends up with more; Another withholds what should be given, but he comes to poverty. 25 The generous person* will prosper,* And whoever refreshes* others will himself be refreshed. 26 The people will curse the one who withholds grain, But they will bless the one who sells it. 27 The one who diligently seeks to do good seeks favor, But the one searching for bad—that is what will surely come upon him. 28 The one trusting in his riches will fall, But the righteous will flourish like the foliage. 29 Anyone who brings trouble* on his household will inherit the wind, And the fool will be a servant to the wisehearted one. 30 The fruitage of the righteous one is a tree of life, And the one who wins souls* is wise. 31 If, indeed, the righteous one on earth is rewarded, How much more the wicked one and the sinner!

Or “law.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “seductive.”

Or “inexperienced.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “with the garment of.”

Lit., “Her feet never stay.”

Or “fetters.”

Or “soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Lit., “to the sons of men.”

Lit., “understand heart.”

See Glossary.

Or “Hereditary values.”

Or “From time immemorial.”

Or “brought forth as with labor pains.”

Lit., “a circle.”

Lit., “made strong.”

Or “decreed.”

Or “mankind.”

Or “By keeping awake at.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “hewed.”

Lit., “She has slaughtered her slaughtering.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “the inexperienced ones.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “the soul of the righteous one.”

Or “reputation.”

Lit., “commandments.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “valuable thing.”

Or possibly, “is on the path to life.”

Or “rumors.”

Or “guide.”

Or “sorrow; hardship.”

Or “to his employer.”

Or “hope.”

Or “bears the fruit of.”

Or “Cheating.”

Or “a complete stone weight.”

Or “Valuable things.”

Or “godless man.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “despises.”

Lit., “the one faithful in spirit.”

Lit., “covers over a matter.”

Or “wise guidance.”

Or “salvation.”

Or “counselors.”

Or “puts up security.”

Lit., “hates.”

Or “charming.”

Or “A man of loyal love.”

Or “does good to his soul.”

Or “disgrace.”

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

Lit., “scatters.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “will be made fat.”

Lit., “freely waters.”

Or “disgrace.”

See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 7:1-27) My son, keep my sayings, And treasure up my commandments.  2 Keep my commandments and live; Guard my instruction* like the pupil of your eye.  3 Tie them around your fingers; Write them on the tablet of your heart.  4 Say to wisdom, “You are my sister,” And call understanding “my relative,”  5 To guard you against the wayward* woman, Against the immoral* woman and her smooth* words.  6 From the window of my house, Through my lattice, I looked down,  7 And as I observed the naive* ones, I discerned among the youths a young man lacking good sense.*  8 He passed along the street near her corner, And he marched in the direction of her house  9 In the twilight, in the evening, At the approach of night and darkness. 10 Then I saw a woman meet him, Dressed like* a prostitute, with a cunning heart. 11 She is loud and defiant. She never stays* at home. 12 One moment she is outside, next she is in the public squares, She lurks near every corner. 13 She grabs hold of him and gives him a kiss; With a bold face, she says to him: 14 “I had to offer communion sacrifices. Today I paid my vows. 15 That is why I came out to meet you, To look for you, and I found you! 16 I have spread fine covers upon my bed, Colorful linen from Egypt. 17 I have sprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon. 18 Come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning; Let us enjoy passionate love together, 19 For my husband is not at home; He has gone on a distant journey. 20 He took a bag of money with him, And he will not return until the day of the full moon.” 21 She misleads him with great persuasiveness. She seduces him with smooth speech. 22 Suddenly he goes after her, like a bull to the slaughter, Like a fool to be punished in the stocks,* 23 Until an arrow pierces his liver; Like a bird rushing into a trap, he does not know that it will cost him his life.* 24 And now, my sons, listen to me; Pay attention to the words I speak. 25 Do not let your heart turn aside to her ways. Do not stray onto her paths, 26 For she has caused many to fall down slain, And those she has killed are numerous. 27 Her house leads to the Grave;* It goes down to the inner chambers of death.

Or “law.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “seductive.”

Or “inexperienced.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “with the garment of.”

Lit., “Her feet never stay.”

Or “fetters.”

Or “soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 12:1-16:33) The one who loves discipline loves knowledge, But the one who hates reproof is unreasoning.*  2 The good person obtains Jehovah’s approval, But He condemns the man of wicked schemes.  3 No man is made secure by wickedness, But the righteous will never be uprooted.  4 A capable wife is a crown to her husband, But the wife who acts shamefully is like rottenness in his bones.  5 The thoughts of the righteous are just, But the guidance of the wicked is deceptive.  6 The words of the wicked are a deadly ambush,* But the mouth of the upright saves them.  7 When the wicked are overthrown, they are no more, But the house of the righteous will keep standing.  8 A man is praised for the discretion of his mouth, But one with a twisted heart will be treated with contempt.  9 Better to be lightly esteemed and have a servant Than to glorify oneself and have no food.* 10 The righteous one takes care of his domestic animals,* But even the mercy of the wicked is cruel. 11 The one who cultivates his land will be satisfied with food, But the one pursuing worthless things is lacking good sense.* 12 The wicked man envies what other evil men have caught, But the root of the righteous bears fruit. 13 The evil man is ensnared by his own sinful speech, But the righteous one escapes from distress. 14 From the fruitage of his speech* a man is satisfied with good, And the work of his hands will reward him. 15 The way of the fool is right in his own eyes, But the wise one accepts advice.* 16 A fool immediately* shows his annoyance, But the shrewd man overlooks* an insult. 17 The one who testifies faithfully will tell the truth,* But a false witness speaks deceit. 18 Thoughtless speech is like the stabs of a sword, But the tongue of the wise is a healing. 19 Truthful lips will endure forever, But a lying tongue will last for only a moment. 20 Deceit is in the heart of those who plot mischief, But those who promote* peace have joy. 21 No harm will befall the righteous one, But the wicked will have their fill of calamity. 22 Lying lips are detestable to Jehovah, But those acting faithfully bring pleasure to him. 23 A shrewd man conceals what he knows, But the heart of the fool blurts out his foolishness. 24 The hand of the diligent ones will rule, But idle hands will be put to forced labor. 25 Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down,* But a good word cheers it up. 26 The righteous one searches out his pastures, But the course of the wicked leads them astray. 27 The lazy do not chase after the prey, But diligence is a man’s precious treasure. 28 The path of righteousness leads to life; Along its pathway there is no death.

13 A wise son accepts his father’s discipline, But the scoffer does not listen to a rebuke.*  2 From the fruitage of his speech* a man will eat what is good, But the very desire* of the treacherous is for violence.  3 The one guarding his mouth* protects his life,* But the one opening his lips wide will come to ruin.  4 The lazy person has his cravings, yet he* has nothing, But the diligent one* will be fully satisfied.*  5 The righteous one hates lies, But the actions of the wicked bring shame and disgrace.  6 Righteousness protects the one whose way is innocent, But wickedness brings down the sinner.  7 There is one who pretends to be rich, yet has nothing; There is another who pretends to be poor, yet has great wealth.  8 Riches are the ransom for a man’s life,* But the poor are not even threatened.*  9 The light of the righteous shines brightly,* But the lamp of the wicked will be extinguished. 10 Presumptuousness leads only to strife, But wisdom belongs to those who seek advice.* 11 Wealth quickly gained* will dwindle, But the wealth of the one who gathers it little by little* will increase. 12 Expectation* postponed makes the heart sick, But a desire realized is a tree of life. 13 Whoever despises instruction* will pay the penalty, But the one who respects the commandment will be rewarded. 14 The teaching* of the wise one is a source of life To turn one away from the snares of death. 15 Keen insight wins favor, But the way of the treacherous is harsh. 16 The shrewd person acts with knowledge, But the fool exposes his own foolishness. 17 A wicked messenger falls into trouble, But a faithful envoy brings healing. 18 Whoever neglects discipline comes to poverty and disgrace, But the one accepting correction* will be glorified. 19 Desire when realized is sweet to a person,* But the stupid hate to turn away from bad. 20 The one walking with the wise will become wise, But the one who has dealings with the stupid will fare badly. 21 Calamity pursues sinners, But prosperity rewards the righteous. 22 The good person leaves an inheritance to his grandchildren, But the sinner’s wealth will be stored up for the righteous one. 23 The plowed field of the poor yields much food, But it* may be swept away by injustice. 24 Whoever holds back his rod* hates his son, But the one who loves him disciplines him diligently.* 25 The righteous one eats and satisfies his appetite,* But the stomach of the wicked is empty.

14 The truly wise woman builds up her house, But the foolish one tears it down with her own hands.  2 The one walking in his uprightness fears Jehovah, But the one whose ways are devious* despises Him.  3 The rod of haughtiness is in the mouth of the fool, But the lips of the wise will protect them.  4 Where there are no cattle the manger is clean, But the power of a bull yields an abundant harvest.  5 A faithful witness will not lie, But a false witness lies with every breath.  6 The scoffer seeks wisdom and finds none, But knowledge comes easily to the person with understanding.  7 Stay away from the foolish man, For you will not find knowledge on his lips.  8 By wisdom the shrewd man understands the way he is going, But the stupid are deceived* by their foolishness.  9 Fools make fun of guilt,* But among the upright, there is a willingness to reconcile.* 10 The heart knows its own bitterness,* And no outsider can share in its joy. 11 The house of the wicked will be destroyed, But the tent of the upright will flourish. 12 There is a way that seems right to a man, But in the end it leads to death. 13 Even in laughter the heart may feel pain, And rejoicing may end in grief. 14 The one wayward at heart will reap the results of his ways, But the good man reaps the reward of his dealings. 15 The naive* person believes every word, But the shrewd one ponders each step. 16 The wise one is cautious and turns away from evil, But the stupid one is reckless* and overconfident. 17 The one who is quick to anger acts foolishly, But the man who thinks things out* is hated. 18 The naive* will inherit foolishness, But the shrewd are crowned with knowledge. 19 Bad people will have to bow down before the good, And the wicked will bow at the gates of the righteous. 20 The poor man is hated even by his neighbors, But many are the friends of the rich person. 21 The one who despises his neighbor sins, But whoever shows compassion to the lowly is happy. 22 Will not those who plot mischief go astray? But those intent on doing good will receive loyal love and faithfulness. 23 There is benefit in every kind of hard work, But mere talk leads to want. 24 The crown of the wise is their wealth; But the foolishness of the stupid is only foolishness. 25 A true witness saves lives,* But a deceitful one lies with every breath. 26 There is strong confidence in the fear of Jehovah, And it will be a refuge for his children. 27 The fear of Jehovah is a fountain of life, To turn one away from the snares of death. 28 A multitude of people are a king’s majesty, But a ruler without subjects is ruined. 29 The one who is slow to anger has great discernment, But the impatient one displays his foolishness. 30 A calm heart gives life* to the body, But jealousy is rottenness to the bones. 31 The one who defrauds the lowly one insults his Maker, But whoever shows compassion to the poor glorifies Him. 32 The wicked one will be brought down by his own evil, But the righteous one will find refuge in his integrity. 33 Wisdom rests quietly in the heart of an understanding person, But among the stupid it must make itself known. 34 Righteousness exalts a nation, But sin is disgraceful to a people. 35 The king finds pleasure in a servant who acts with insight, But his fury is against the one who acts shamefully.

15 A mild* answer turns away rage, But a harsh* word stirs up anger.  2 The tongue of the wise makes good use of knowledge, But the mouth of the stupid blurts out foolishness.  3 The eyes of Jehovah are everywhere, Watching both the bad and the good.  4 A calm tongue* is a tree of life, But twisted speech causes despair.*  5 A fool disrespects his father’s discipline, But a shrewd person accepts correction.*  6 In the house of the righteous one there is abundant treasure, But the produce* of the wicked one brings him trouble.  7 The lips of the wise spread knowledge, But not so the heart of the stupid one.  8 The sacrifice of the wicked is detestable to Jehovah, But the prayer of the upright is a pleasure to Him.  9 Jehovah detests the way of the wicked one, But he loves the one who pursues righteousness. 10 Discipline seems bad* to one forsaking the way, But whoever hates reproof will die. 11 The Grave* and the place of destruction* are in full view of Jehovah. How much more so the hearts of men! 12 The scoffer does not love the one correcting* him. He will not consult the wise. 13 A joyful heart makes for a cheerful countenance, But heartache crushes the spirit. 14 The understanding heart seeks knowledge, But the mouth of the stupid feeds on* foolishness. 15 All the days of the afflicted one are bad, But the one with a cheerful* heart has a continual feast. 16 Better is a little in the fear of Jehovah Than great wealth along with anxiety.* 17 Better is a dish of vegetables where there is love Than a fattened* bull where there is hatred. 18 A hot-tempered man stirs up strife, But one who is slow to anger calms a quarrel. 19 The way of the lazy one is like a hedge of thorns, But the path of the upright is like a level highway. 20 A wise son makes his father rejoice, But a stupid man despises his mother. 21 Foolishness is a joy to one lacking good sense,* But the man of discernment walks straight ahead. 22 Plans fail when there is no consultation,* But there is accomplishment through many advisers.* 23 A man rejoices in giving the right answer,* And a word spoken at the right time—how good it is! 24 The path of life leads upward to one with insight, To turn him away from the Grave* below. 25 Jehovah will tear down the house of the haughty, But he will preserve the boundary of the widow. 26 Jehovah detests the schemes of the wicked one, But pleasant sayings are pure to Him. 27 The one making dishonest profit brings trouble* on his own household, But the one hating bribes will keep living. 28 The heart of the righteous one meditates before answering,* But the mouth of the wicked blurts out bad things. 29 Jehovah is far away from the wicked, But he hears the prayer of the righteous. 30 Bright eyes make* the heart rejoice; A good report invigorates the bones.* 31 The one who listens to life-giving reproof Is at home among the wise. 32 Anyone refusing discipline despises his life,* But whoever listens to reproof acquires understanding.* 33 The fear of Jehovah is a training in wisdom, And before glory there is humility.

16 A man prepares the thoughts of his heart,* But the answer he gives* is from Jehovah.  2 All of a man’s ways seem right* to him, But Jehovah examines the motives.*  3 Commit to Jehovah whatever you do,* And your plans will succeed.  4 Jehovah has made everything work for his purpose, Even the wicked for the day of disaster.  5 Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah. Be assured* that he will not go unpunished.  6 By loyal love and faithfulness, error is atoned for, And by fearing Jehovah one turns away from bad.  7 When Jehovah is pleased with a man’s ways, He causes even his enemies to be at peace with him.  8 Better is a little with righteousness Than a large income without justice.  9 A man may plot out his course in his heart, But it is Jehovah who directs his steps. 10 Inspired* decision should be on the lips of a king; He must never betray justice. 11 Honest balances and scales are from Jehovah; All the weights in the bag are his doing. 12 Wicked practices are detestable to kings, For the throne is firmly established by righteousness. 13 Righteous speech is a pleasure to kings. They love someone who speaks honestly. 14 The king’s rage is like a messenger of death, But the wise man appeases* it. 15 In the light of the king’s face there is life; His favor is like a cloud of rain in spring. 16 How much better to acquire wisdom than gold! To gain understanding is to be chosen over silver. 17 The highway of the upright avoids what is bad. Whoever safeguards his way preserves his life.* 18 Pride is before a crash, And a haughty spirit before stumbling. 19 Better to be humble* among the meek Than to share the spoil of the haughty. 20 The one who shows insight in a matter will find success,* And happy is the one trusting in Jehovah. 21 The wise in heart will be called understanding, And the one kind in speech* adds persuasiveness. 22 Insight is a fountain of life to those possessing it, But fools are disciplined by their own foolishness. 23 The heart of the wise one gives his mouth insight And adds persuasiveness to his speech. 24 Pleasant sayings are a honeycomb, Sweet to the soul* and a healing to the bones. 25 There is a way that seems right to a man, But in the end it leads to death. 26 The appetite* of a laborer makes him work hard For his hunger* urges him on. 27 A worthless man digs up what is bad; His speech is like a scorching fire. 28 A troublemaker* causes dissension, And a slanderer separates close friends. 29 A violent man entices his neighbor And leads him in the wrong way. 30 He winks his eye as he schemes harm. He pinches his lips together as he carries out mischief. 31 Gray hair is a crown of beauty* When it is found in the way of righteousness. 32 The one slow to anger is better than a mighty man, And the one controlling his temper* than one conquering a city. 33 The lot is cast into the lap, But every decision by it is from Jehovah.

Or “has no sense.”

Lit., “lie in wait for blood.”

Lit., “bread.”

Or “the soul of his domestic animal.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “counsel.”

Or “in the same day.”

Lit., “covers over.”

Lit., “what is righteous.”

Lit., “those who are counselors of.”

Or “depresses him.”

Or “correction.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “soul.”

Or “what he says.”

Or “soul.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “will be made fat.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “hear no rebuke.”

Lit., “rejoices.”

Or “those consulting together.”

Or “Wealth from vanity.”

Lit., “gathers by hand.”

Or “Hope.”

Or “the word.”

Or “law.”

Or “reproof.”

Or “soul.”

Or “he.”

Or “discipline; punishment.”

Or possibly, “promptly.”

Or “soul.”

Or “crooked.”

Or possibly, “the stupid deceive others.”

Or “of making amends.”

Or “there is goodwill.”

Or “the bitterness of its soul.”

Or “inexperienced.”

Or “furious.”

Or “the man of thinking abilities.”

Or “inexperienced.”

Or “souls.”

Or “health.”

Or “gentle.”

Or “painful.”

Or “A tongue of healing.”

Lit., “the crushing of the spirit.”

Or “reproof.”

Or “income.”

Or “severe.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “and Abaddon.”

Or “reproving.”

Or “pursues.”

Or “good.”

Or “confusion.”

Lit., “manger-fed.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “confidential talk.”

Or “counselors.”

Lit., “in the answer of his mouth.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “disgrace.”

Or “carefully considers how to answer; thinks before speaking.”

Or “A cheerful glance makes.”

Lit., “makes the bones fat.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “heart.”

Lit., “The arrangings of the heart belong to a man.”

Or “the right answer.” Lit., “the answer of the tongue.”

Lit., “pure.”

Lit., “spirits.”

Lit., “Roll to Jehovah your works.”

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

Or “Divine.”

Or “avoids.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “lowly of spirit.”

Lit., “good.”

Or “And appealing speech.” Lit., “And sweetness of lips.”

Or “taste.” See Glossary.

Or “soul.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “A schemer.”

Or “glory.”

Lit., “ruling over his spirit.”

^ (Prov. 15:18-16:6) A hot-tempered man stirs up strife, But one who is slow to anger calms a quarrel. 19 The way of the lazy one is like a hedge of thorns, But the path of the upright is like a level highway. 20 A wise son makes his father rejoice, But a stupid man despises his mother. 21 Foolishness is a joy to one lacking good sense,* But the man of discernment walks straight ahead. 22 Plans fail when there is no consultation,* But there is accomplishment through many advisers.* 23 A man rejoices in giving the right answer,* And a word spoken at the right time—how good it is! 24 The path of life leads upward to one with insight, To turn him away from the Grave* below. 25 Jehovah will tear down the house of the haughty, But he will preserve the boundary of the widow. 26 Jehovah detests the schemes of the wicked one, But pleasant sayings are pure to Him. 27 The one making dishonest profit brings trouble* on his own household, But the one hating bribes will keep living. 28 The heart of the righteous one meditates before answering,* But the mouth of the wicked blurts out bad things. 29 Jehovah is far away from the wicked, But he hears the prayer of the righteous. 30 Bright eyes make* the heart rejoice; A good report invigorates the bones.* 31 The one who listens to life-giving reproof Is at home among the wise. 32 Anyone refusing discipline despises his life,* But whoever listens to reproof acquires understanding.* 33 The fear of Jehovah is a training in wisdom, And before glory there is humility.

16 A man prepares the thoughts of his heart,* But the answer he gives* is from Jehovah.  2 All of a man’s ways seem right* to him, But Jehovah examines the motives.*  3 Commit to Jehovah whatever you do,* And your plans will succeed.  4 Jehovah has made everything work for his purpose, Even the wicked for the day of disaster.  5 Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah. Be assured* that he will not go unpunished.  6 By loyal love and faithfulness, error is atoned for, And by fearing Jehovah one turns away from bad.

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “confidential talk.”

Or “counselors.”

Lit., “in the answer of his mouth.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “disgrace.”

Or “carefully considers how to answer; thinks before speaking.”

Or “A cheerful glance makes.”

Lit., “makes the bones fat.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “heart.”

Lit., “The arrangings of the heart belong to a man.”

Or “the right answer.” Lit., “the answer of the tongue.”

Lit., “pure.”

Lit., “spirits.”

Lit., “Roll to Jehovah your works.”

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

^ ***sn song 69 Make Me Know Your Ways***

Song 69

Make Me Know Your Ways

([Psalm 25:4])

1. We’re gathered together Jehovah, our God,

Accepting your warm invitation.

Your Word is a lamp that lights up our roadway,

The source of divine education.

(CHORUS)

Teach me your ways, and make me understand;

Incline my ear to hear your wise command.

Cause me to walk in ways of truth and right,

And make your law my principal delight.

2. Unreachably high is your wisdom, O God;

Your judgments we find reassuring.

Your Word is a source of unending wonder;

Your sayings of truth are enduring.

(CHORUS)

Teach me your ways, and make me understand;

Incline my ear to hear your wise command.

Cause me to walk in ways of truth and right,

And make your law my principal delight.

(See also [Ex. 33:13;][Ps. 1:2;][119:27,][35,][73,][105].)

^ (Ps. 25:4) Make me know your ways, O Jehovah; Teach me your paths.

^ (Ex. 33:13) Please, if I have found favor in your eyes, make me know your ways, so that I may know you and continue to find favor in your eyes. Consider, too, that this nation is your people.”

^ (Ps. 1:2) But his delight is in the law of Jehovah, And he reads His law in an undertone* day and night.

Or “he meditates on His law.”

^ (Ps. 119:27) Make me understand the meaning* of your orders, So that I may ponder over* your wonderful works.

Lit., “way.”

Or “study.”

^ (Ps. 119:35) Guide me* in the pathway of your commandments, For in it I take delight.

Or “Make me walk.”

^ (Ps. 119:73) Your hands made me and formed me. Give me understanding, So that I may learn your commandments.

^ (Ps. 119:105) Your word is a lamp to my foot, And a light for my path.

^ ***w07 7/15 p. 8 “Wisdom Is for a Protection”***

“Wisdom Is for a Protection”

“THE getting of wisdom is O how much better than gold! And the getting of understanding is to be chosen more than silver,” states Proverbs 16:16. Why is wisdom so valuable? Because “wisdom is for a protection the same as money is for a protection; but the advantage of knowledge is that wisdom itself preserves alive its owners.” (Ecclesiastes 7:12) How, though, does wisdom preserve alive its owners?

Acquiring godly wisdom, that is, gaining accurate knowledge of God’s Word, the Bible, and acting in harmony with it, helps us to walk in the way Jehovah approves. (Proverbs 2:10-12) King Solomon of ancient Israel says: “The highway of the upright ones is to turn away from bad. One who is safeguarding his way is keeping his soul.” (Proverbs 16:17) Yes, wisdom delivers its owners from bad ways and preserves them alive! The concise, wise sayings at Proverbs 16:16-33 show the positive effect that godly wisdom can have on our disposition, speech, and actions.*

“Be Lowly in Spirit”

Wisdom personified is portrayed as saying: “Self-exaltation and pride . . . I have hated.” (Proverbs 8:13) Pride and wisdom are poles apart. We need to act with wisdom and be careful not to develop a haughty, or arrogant, disposition. Especially should we be on guard if we have enjoyed success in some areas of life or are entrusted with a position of responsibility in the Christian congregation.

“Pride is before a crash,” warns Proverbs 16:18, “and a haughty spirit before stumbling.” Consider the greatest crash in the universe—the fall of a perfect spirit son of God who made himself Satan the Devil. (Genesis 3:1-5; Revelation 12:9) Did he not manifest a haughty spirit prior to his crash? The Bible points to this when it says that a newly converted man should not be appointed to an office of oversight in the Christian congregation

^ (Prov. 16:16) How much better to acquire wisdom than gold! To gain understanding is to be chosen over silver.

^ (Eccl. 7:12) For wisdom is a protection just as money is a protection, but the advantage of knowledge is this: Wisdom preserves the life of its owner.

^ (Prov. 2:10-12) When wisdom enters your heart And knowledge becomes pleasant to your soul,* 11 Thinking ability will keep watch over you, And discernment will safeguard you, 12 To save you from the bad course, From the man speaking perverse things,

See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 16:17) The highway of the upright avoids what is bad. Whoever safeguards his way preserves his life.*

Or “soul.”

^ (Prov. 16:16-33) How much better to acquire wisdom than gold! To gain understanding is to be chosen over silver. 17 The highway of the upright avoids what is bad. Whoever safeguards his way preserves his life.* 18 Pride is before a crash, And a haughty spirit before stumbling. 19 Better to be humble* among the meek Than to share the spoil of the haughty. 20 The one who shows insight in a matter will find success,* And happy is the one trusting in Jehovah. 21 The wise in heart will be called understanding, And the one kind in speech* adds persuasiveness. 22 Insight is a fountain of life to those possessing it, But fools are disciplined by their own foolishness. 23 The heart of the wise one gives his mouth insight And adds persuasiveness to his speech. 24 Pleasant sayings are a honeycomb, Sweet to the soul* and a healing to the bones. 25 There is a way that seems right to a man, But in the end it leads to death. 26 The appetite* of a laborer makes him work hard For his hunger* urges him on. 27 A worthless man digs up what is bad; His speech is like a scorching fire. 28 A troublemaker* causes dissension, And a slanderer separates close friends. 29 A violent man entices his neighbor And leads him in the wrong way. 30 He winks his eye as he schemes harm. He pinches his lips together as he carries out mischief. 31 Gray hair is a crown of beauty* When it is found in the way of righteousness. 32 The one slow to anger is better than a mighty man, And the one controlling his temper* than one conquering a city. 33 The lot is cast into the lap, But every decision by it is from Jehovah.

Or “soul.”

Lit., “lowly of spirit.”

Lit., “good.”

Or “And appealing speech.” Lit., “And sweetness of lips.”

Or “taste.” See Glossary.

Or “soul.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “A schemer.”

Or “glory.”

Lit., “ruling over his spirit.”

^ (Prov. 8:13) The fear of Jehovah means the hating of bad. I hate self-exaltation and pride and the evil way and perverse speech.

^ (Prov. 16:18) Pride is before a crash, And a haughty spirit before stumbling.

^ (Gen. 3:1-5) Now the serpent was the most cautious* of all the wild animals of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it said to the woman: “Did God really say that you must not eat from every tree of the garden?” 2 At this the woman said to the serpent: “We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden. 3 But God has said about the fruit of the tree that is in the middle of the garden: ‘You must not eat from it, no, you must not touch it; otherwise you will die.’” 4 At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die. 5 For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.”

Or “shrewdest; craftiest.”

^ (Rev. 12:9) So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.

^ par. 3 For a discussion of Proverbs 16:1-15, see pages 17-20 of the May 15, 2007, issue of The Watchtower.

^ (Prov. 16:1-15) A man prepares the thoughts of his heart,* But the answer he gives* is from Jehovah.  2 All of a man’s ways seem right* to him, But Jehovah examines the motives.*  3 Commit to Jehovah whatever you do,* And your plans will succeed.  4 Jehovah has made everything work for his purpose, Even the wicked for the day of disaster.  5 Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah. Be assured* that he will not go unpunished.  6 By loyal love and faithfulness, error is atoned for, And by fearing Jehovah one turns away from bad.  7 When Jehovah is pleased with a man’s ways, He causes even his enemies to be at peace with him.  8 Better is a little with righteousness Than a large income without justice.  9 A man may plot out his course in his heart, But it is Jehovah who directs his steps. 10 Inspired* decision should be on the lips of a king; He must never betray justice. 11 Honest balances and scales are from Jehovah; All the weights in the bag are his doing. 12 Wicked practices are detestable to kings, For the throne is firmly established by righteousness. 13 Righteous speech is a pleasure to kings. They love someone who speaks honestly. 14 The king’s rage is like a messenger of death, But the wise man appeases* it. 15 In the light of the king’s face there is life; His favor is like a cloud of rain in spring.

Lit., “The arrangings of the heart belong to a man.”

Or “the right answer.” Lit., “the answer of the tongue.”

Lit., “pure.”

Lit., “spirits.”

Lit., “Roll to Jehovah your works.”

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

Or “Divine.”

Or “avoids.”

^ ***w07 7/15 pp. 8-9 “Wisdom Is for a Protection”***

“Wisdom Is for a Protection”

“THE getting of wisdom is O how much better than gold! And the getting of understanding is to be chosen more than silver,” states Proverbs 16:16. Why is wisdom so valuable? Because “wisdom is for a protection the same as money is for a protection; but the advantage of knowledge is that wisdom itself preserves alive its owners.” (Ecclesiastes 7:12) How, though, does wisdom preserve alive its owners?

Acquiring godly wisdom, that is, gaining accurate knowledge of God’s Word, the Bible, and acting in harmony with it, helps us to walk in the way Jehovah approves. (Proverbs 2:10-12) King Solomon of ancient Israel says: “The highway of the upright ones is to turn away from bad. One who is safeguarding his way is keeping his soul.” (Proverbs 16:17) Yes, wisdom delivers its owners from bad ways and preserves them alive! The concise, wise sayings at Proverbs 16:16-33 show the positive effect that godly wisdom can have on our disposition, speech, and actions.*

“Be Lowly in Spirit”

Wisdom personified is portrayed as saying: “Self-exaltation and pride . . . I have hated.” (Proverbs 8:13) Pride and wisdom are poles apart. We need to act with wisdom and be careful not to develop a haughty, or arrogant, disposition. Especially should we be on guard if we have enjoyed success in some areas of life or are entrusted with a position of responsibility in the Christian congregation.

“Pride is before a crash,” warns Proverbs 16:18, “and a haughty spirit before stumbling.” Consider the greatest crash in the universe—the fall of a perfect spirit son of God who made himself Satan the Devil. (Genesis 3:1-5; Revelation 12:9) Did he not manifest a haughty spirit prior to his crash? The Bible points to this when it says that a newly converted man should not be appointed to an office of oversight in the Christian congregation “for fear that he might get puffed up with pride and fall into the judgment passed upon the Devil.” (1 Timothy 3:1, 2,[6]) How important it is to guard against feeding the pride of others as well as allowing it to develop in us!

“Better is it to be lowly in spirit with the meek ones than to divide spoil with the self-exalted ones,” states Proverbs 16:19. That this is good admonition is shown in the case of King Nebuchadnezzar of ancient Babylon. He proudly set up an immense image—perhaps representing himself—on the plain of Dura. The statue may have been mounted on a very high pedestal so that it reached a height of 90 feet [27 m]. ([Daniel 3:1]) This towering monument was meant to be an impressive symbol of Nebuchadnezzar’s empire. While high and lofty things—such as that statue as well as obelisks, steeples, and skyscrapers—may impress humans, this is not the case with God. The psalmist sang: “Jehovah is high, and yet the humble one he sees; but the lofty one he knows only from a distance.” ([Psalm 138:6]) In fact, “what is lofty among men is a disgusting thing in God’s sight.” ([Luke 16:15]) Better it is for us to “be led along with the lowly things” than for us to “be minding lofty things.”—[Romans 12:16].

Speak With “Insight” and “Persuasiveness”

How does acquiring wisdom affect our speech? The wise king tells us: “He that is showing insight in a matter will find good, and happy is he that is trusting in Jehovah. The one that is wise in heart will be called understanding, and he that is sweet in his lips adds persuasiveness. To its owners insight is a well of life; and the discipline of the foolish ones is foolishness. The heart of the wise one causes his mouth to show insight, and to his lips it adds persuasiveness.”—Proverbs 16:20-23.

Wisdom helps us speak with insight and persuasiveness. Why? Because a person who is wise at heart tries to “find good” in a matter and ‘trusts in Jehovah.’ When we endeavor to find good in others, we are more likely to speak well of them. Rather than being harsh or confrontational, our words are sweet and persuasive. Insight into the circumstances of others helps us to understand the extent of hardship they may be experiencing and how they are coping with it.

Speech influenced by wisdom is also vital when it comes to our Kingdom-preaching and disciple-making work. When we teach God’s Word to others, our objective is not merely to convey Scriptural information. Our goal is to reach the heart of individuals. This calls for adding persuasiveness to our lips. The apostle Paul urged his associate Timothy to continue in the things he had been “persuaded to believe.”—2 Timothy 3:14, 15.

^ (Prov. 16:16) How much better to acquire wisdom than gold! To gain understanding is to be chosen over silver.

^ (Eccl. 7:12) For wisdom is a protection just as money is a protection, but the advantage of knowledge is this: Wisdom preserves the life of its owner.

^ (Prov. 2:10-12) When wisdom enters your heart And knowledge becomes pleasant to your soul,* 11 Thinking ability will keep watch over you, And discernment will safeguard you, 12 To save you from the bad course, From the man speaking perverse things,

See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 16:17) The highway of the upright avoids what is bad. Whoever safeguards his way preserves his life.*

Or “soul.”

^ (Prov. 16:16-33) How much better to acquire wisdom than gold! To gain understanding is to be chosen over silver. 17 The highway of the upright avoids what is bad. Whoever safeguards his way preserves his life.* 18 Pride is before a crash, And a haughty spirit before stumbling. 19 Better to be humble* among the meek Than to share the spoil of the haughty. 20 The one who shows insight in a matter will find success,* And happy is the one trusting in Jehovah. 21 The wise in heart will be called understanding, And the one kind in speech* adds persuasiveness. 22 Insight is a fountain of life to those possessing it, But fools are disciplined by their own foolishness. 23 The heart of the wise one gives his mouth insight And adds persuasiveness to his speech. 24 Pleasant sayings are a honeycomb, Sweet to the soul* and a healing to the bones. 25 There is a way that seems right to a man, But in the end it leads to death. 26 The appetite* of a laborer makes him work hard For his hunger* urges him on. 27 A worthless man digs up what is bad; His speech is like a scorching fire. 28 A troublemaker* causes dissension, And a slanderer separates close friends. 29 A violent man entices his neighbor And leads him in the wrong way. 30 He winks his eye as he schemes harm. He pinches his lips together as he carries out mischief. 31 Gray hair is a crown of beauty* When it is found in the way of righteousness. 32 The one slow to anger is better than a mighty man, And the one controlling his temper* than one conquering a city. 33 The lot is cast into the lap, But every decision by it is from Jehovah.

Or “soul.”

Lit., “lowly of spirit.”

Lit., “good.”

Or “And appealing speech.” Lit., “And sweetness of lips.”

Or “taste.” See Glossary.

Or “soul.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “A schemer.”

Or “glory.”

Lit., “ruling over his spirit.”

^ (Prov. 8:13) The fear of Jehovah means the hating of bad. I hate self-exaltation and pride and the evil way and perverse speech.

^ (Prov. 16:18) Pride is before a crash, And a haughty spirit before stumbling.

^ (Gen. 3:1-5) Now the serpent was the most cautious* of all the wild animals of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it said to the woman: “Did God really say that you must not eat from every tree of the garden?” 2 At this the woman said to the serpent: “We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden. 3 But God has said about the fruit of the tree that is in the middle of the garden: ‘You must not eat from it, no, you must not touch it; otherwise you will die.’” 4 At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die. 5 For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.”

Or “shrewdest; craftiest.”

^ (Rev. 12:9) So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.

^ (1 Tim. 3:1, 2) This statement is trustworthy: If a man is reaching out to be an overseer, he is desirous of a fine work. 2 The overseer should therefore be irreprehensible, a husband of one wife, moderate in habits, sound in mind,* orderly, hospitable, qualified to teach,

Or “have good judgment; be sensible.”

^ (1 Tim. 3:6) not a newly converted man, for fear that he might get puffed up with pride and fall into the judgment passed on the Devil.

^ (Prov. 16:19) Better to be humble* among the meek Than to share the spoil of the haughty.

Lit., “lowly of spirit.”

^ (Dan. 3:1) Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar the king made an image* of gold that was 60 cubits* high and 6 cubits* wide. He set it up on the plain of Duʹra in the province* of Babylon.

Or “statue.”

About 27 m (88 ft). See App. B14.

About 2.7 m (8.8 ft). See App. B14.

Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ (Ps. 138:6) Though Jehovah is high, he takes note of the humble, But the haughty he knows only from a distance.

^ (Luke 16:15) So he said to them: “You are those who declare yourselves righteous before men, but God knows your hearts. For what is considered exalted by men is a disgusting thing in God’s sight.

^ (Rom. 12:16) Have the same attitude toward others as toward yourselves; do not set your mind on lofty things,* but be led along with the lowly things. Do not become wise in your own eyes.

Or “cultivate lofty ideas.”

^ (Prov. 16:20-23) The one who shows insight in a matter will find success,* And happy is the one trusting in Jehovah. 21 The wise in heart will be called understanding, And the one kind in speech* adds persuasiveness. 22 Insight is a fountain of life to those possessing it, But fools are disciplined by their own foolishness. 23 The heart of the wise one gives his mouth insight And adds persuasiveness to his speech.

Lit., “good.”

Or “And appealing speech.” Lit., “And sweetness of lips.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:14, 15) You, however, continue in the things that you learned and were persuaded to believe, knowing from whom you learned them 15 and that from infancy you have known the holy writings, which are able to make you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.

^ par. 3 For a discussion of Proverbs 16:1-15, see pages 17-20 of the May 15, 2007, issue of The Watchtower.

^ (Prov. 16:1-15) A man prepares the thoughts of his heart,* But the answer he gives* is from Jehovah.  2 All of a man’s ways seem right* to him, But Jehovah examines the motives.*  3 Commit to Jehovah whatever you do,* And your plans will succeed.  4 Jehovah has made everything work for his purpose, Even the wicked for the day of disaster.  5 Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah. Be assured* that he will not go unpunished.  6 By loyal love and faithfulness, error is atoned for, And by fearing Jehovah one turns away from bad.  7 When Jehovah is pleased with a man’s ways, He causes even his enemies to be at peace with him.  8 Better is a little with righteousness Than a large income without justice.  9 A man may plot out his course in his heart, But it is Jehovah who directs his steps. 10 Inspired* decision should be on the lips of a king; He must never betray justice. 11 Honest balances and scales are from Jehovah; All the weights in the bag are his doing. 12 Wicked practices are detestable to kings, For the throne is firmly established by righteousness. 13 Righteous speech is a pleasure to kings. They love someone who speaks honestly. 14 The king’s rage is like a messenger of death, But the wise man appeases* it. 15 In the light of the king’s face there is life; His favor is like a cloud of rain in spring.

Lit., “The arrangings of the heart belong to a man.”

Or “the right answer.” Lit., “the answer of the tongue.”

Lit., “pure.”

Lit., “spirits.”

Lit., “Roll to Jehovah your works.”

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

Or “Divine.”

Or “avoids.”

^ ***w07 7/15 pp. 9-10 “Wisdom Is for a Protection”***

“for fear that he might get puffed up with pride and fall into the judgment passed upon the Devil.” (1 Timothy 3:1, 2,[6]) How important it is to guard against feeding the pride of others as well as allowing it to develop in us!

“Better is it to be lowly in spirit with the meek ones than to divide spoil with the self-exalted ones,” states Proverbs 16:19. That this is good admonition is shown in the case of King Nebuchadnezzar of ancient Babylon. He proudly set up an immense image—perhaps representing himself—on the plain of Dura. The statue may have been mounted on a very high pedestal so that it reached a height of 90 feet [27 m]. ([Daniel 3:1]) This towering monument was meant to be an impressive symbol of Nebuchadnezzar’s empire. While high and lofty things—such as that statue as well as obelisks, steeples, and skyscrapers—may impress humans, this is not the case with God. The psalmist sang: “Jehovah is high, and yet the humble one he sees; but the lofty one he knows only from a distance.” ([Psalm 138:6]) In fact, “what is lofty among men is a disgusting thing in God’s sight.” ([Luke 16:15]) Better it is for us to “be led along with the lowly things” than for us to “be minding lofty things.”—[Romans 12:16].

Speak With “Insight” and “Persuasiveness”

How does acquiring wisdom affect our speech? The wise king tells us: “He that is showing insight in a matter will find good, and happy is he that is trusting in Jehovah. The one that is wise in heart will be called understanding, and he that is sweet in his lips adds persuasiveness. To its owners insight is a well of life; and the discipline of the foolish ones is foolishness. The heart of the wise one causes his mouth to show insight, and to his lips it adds persuasiveness.”—Proverbs 16:20-23.

Wisdom helps us speak with insight and persuasiveness. Why? Because a person who is wise at heart tries to “find good” in a matter and ‘trusts in Jehovah.’ When we endeavor to find good in others, we are more likely to speak well of them. Rather than being harsh or confrontational, our words are sweet and persuasive. Insight into the circumstances of others helps us to understand the extent of hardship they may be experiencing and how they are coping with it.

Speech influenced by wisdom is also vital when it comes to our Kingdom-preaching and disciple-making work. When we teach God’s Word to others, our objective is not merely to convey Scriptural information. Our goal is to reach the heart of individuals. This calls for adding persuasiveness to our lips. The apostle Paul urged his associate Timothy to continue in the things he had been “persuaded to believe.”—2 Timothy 3:14, 15.

The Greek word for “persuade” has the meaning of “bringing about a change of mind by the influence of reason or moral considerations,” says An Expository Dictionary of New Testament Words, by W. E. Vine. Coming up with convincing arguments that lead to a change of mind in our listener calls for insight into his or her thinking, interests, circumstances, and background. How can we gain such insight? The disciple James answers: “Be swift about hearing, slow about speaking.” ([James 1:19]) By drawing the listener out and carefully paying attention to what he says, we can get to know what he is at heart.

The apostle Paul was outstanding in his ability to persuade others. ([Acts 18:4]) Even one of his opposers, Demetrius, a silversmith, acknowledged: “Not only in Ephesus but in nearly all the district of Asia this Paul has persuaded a considerable crowd and turned them to another opinion.” ([Acts 19:26]) Did Paul take personal credit for his effectiveness in the preaching work? Not at all. He considered his preaching to be “a demonstration of [God’s] spirit and power.” (1 Corinthians 2:4, 5) We too have the help of Jehovah’s holy spirit. Because we trust in Jehovah, we are confident of his help as we endeavor to speak with insight and persuasiveness in our ministry.

No wonder that “the one that is wise in heart” is called “intelligent” or “discerning”! (Proverbs 16:21, An American Translation; New International Version) Yes, insight is “a well of life” to those who have it. But what about the foolish? They ‘despise wisdom and discipline.’ ([Proverbs 1:7]) What results do they reap by rejecting discipline from Jehovah? As noted above, Solomon says: “The discipline of the foolish ones is foolishness.” (Proverbs 16:22) They receive further discipline, often in the form of severe chastisement. The foolish may also bring upon themselves hardship, shame, disease, and even untimely death.

Pointing further to the wholesome effect that wisdom has on our speech, the king of Israel says: “Pleasant sayings are a honeycomb, sweet to the soul and a healing to the bones.” (Proverbs 16:24) As honey is sweet and provides quick refreshment to a hungry person, pleasant sayings are encouraging and refreshing. Honey also has health-giving and curative properties and is good for a person. So are pleasant sayings; they are healthful spiritually.—Proverbs 24:13, 14.

Beware of ‘a Way That Seems Upright’

“There exists a way that is upright before a man,” says Solomon, “but the ways of death are the end of it afterward.” (Proverbs 16:25) This is a warning against false reasoning and the pursuit of a course opposed to divine law. A certain path may seem right from a fleshly standpoint but may really be against the righteous principles of God’s Word. Moreover, Satan may promote such deception

^ (1 Tim. 3:1, 2) This statement is trustworthy: If a man is reaching out to be an overseer, he is desirous of a fine work. 2 The overseer should therefore be irreprehensible, a husband of one wife, moderate in habits, sound in mind,* orderly, hospitable, qualified to teach,

Or “have good judgment; be sensible.”

^ (1 Tim. 3:6) not a newly converted man, for fear that he might get puffed up with pride and fall into the judgment passed on the Devil.

^ (Prov. 16:19) Better to be humble* among the meek Than to share the spoil of the haughty.

Lit., “lowly of spirit.”

^ (Dan. 3:1) Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar the king made an image* of gold that was 60 cubits* high and 6 cubits* wide. He set it up on the plain of Duʹra in the province* of Babylon.

Or “statue.”

About 27 m (88 ft). See App. B14.

About 2.7 m (8.8 ft). See App. B14.

Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ (Ps. 138:6) Though Jehovah is high, he takes note of the humble, But the haughty he knows only from a distance.

^ (Luke 16:15) So he said to them: “You are those who declare yourselves righteous before men, but God knows your hearts. For what is considered exalted by men is a disgusting thing in God’s sight.

^ (Rom. 12:16) Have the same attitude toward others as toward yourselves; do not set your mind on lofty things,* but be led along with the lowly things. Do not become wise in your own eyes.

Or “cultivate lofty ideas.”

^ (Prov. 16:20-23) The one who shows insight in a matter will find success,* And happy is the one trusting in Jehovah. 21 The wise in heart will be called understanding, And the one kind in speech* adds persuasiveness. 22 Insight is a fountain of life to those possessing it, But fools are disciplined by their own foolishness. 23 The heart of the wise one gives his mouth insight And adds persuasiveness to his speech.

Lit., “good.”

Or “And appealing speech.” Lit., “And sweetness of lips.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:14, 15) You, however, continue in the things that you learned and were persuaded to believe, knowing from whom you learned them 15 and that from infancy you have known the holy writings, which are able to make you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.

^ (Jas. 1:19) Know this, my beloved brothers: Everyone must be quick to listen, slow to speak, slow to anger,

^ (Acts 18:4) He would give a talk* in the synagogue every sabbath and would persuade Jews and Greeks.

Or “He would reason with them.”

^ (Acts 19:26) Now you see and hear how, not only in Ephʹe·sus but in nearly all the province of Asia, this Paul has persuaded a considerable crowd and turned them to another opinion, saying that the gods made by hands are not really gods.

^ (1 Cor. 2:4, 5) and my speech and what I preached were not with persuasive words of wisdom but with a demonstration of spirit and power, 5 so that your faith might be, not in men’s wisdom, but in God’s power.

^ (Prov. 16:21) The wise in heart will be called understanding, And the one kind in speech* adds persuasiveness.

Or “And appealing speech.” Lit., “And sweetness of lips.”

^ (Prov. 1:7) The fear of* Jehovah is the beginning of knowledge. Only fools despise wisdom and discipline.

Or “reverence for.”

^ (Prov. 16:22) Insight is a fountain of life to those possessing it, But fools are disciplined by their own foolishness.

^ (Prov. 16:24) Pleasant sayings are a honeycomb, Sweet to the soul* and a healing to the bones.

Or “taste.” See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 24:13, 14) My son, eat honey, because it is good; Honey from the comb is sweet to the taste. 14 Likewise, know that wisdom is good for you.* If you find it, you will have a future And your hope will not be cut off.

Or “is sweet to your soul.”

^ (Prov. 16:25) There is a way that seems right to a man, But in the end it leads to death.

^ ***g 11/13 p. 16 Do You Have “a Feast Constantly”?***

Do You Have “a Feast Constantly”?

“All the days of the afflicted one are bad; but the one that is good at heart has a feast constantly.”—Proverbs 15:15.

WHAT do those words mean? They refer to one’s mental and emotional state. “The afflicted one” dwells on the negative—an outlook that makes his days “bad,” or dismal. By contrast, the one who “is good at heart” tries to focus on the positive—an attitude that fosters inner joy, giving him “a feast constantly.”

We all have problems that can rob us of a measure of happiness. Yet, we may be able to do certain things that help us to retain our joy through difficult times. Consider what the Bible says.

Do not let anxieties over tomorrow weigh you down today. Jesus Christ said: “Do not worry about tomorrow; it will have enough worries of its own. There is no need to add to the troubles each day brings.”—[Matthew 6:34], Good News Translation.

Try to focus on the good things that have happened to you. In fact, when you feel down, why not make a list of those good things and reflect on them? Also, do not dwell on past mistakes or bad deeds. Learn from them, and move on. Be like a driver who glances into his rearview mirror but does not focus on it. Keep in mind, too, that “there is the true forgiveness with [God].”—[Psalm 130:4].

When anxieties weigh you down, confide in someone who may be able to cheer you up. “Anxious care” causes our heart “to bow down, but the good word is what makes it rejoice,” says Proverbs 12:25. That “good word” may come from a family member or a trusted friend—someone who is not cynical or pessimistic but “is loving all the time.”—Proverbs 17:17.

The wise sayings found in the Bible have helped many to find more joy in life, even through trying times. May those precious sayings help you too.

^ (Prov. 15:15) All the days of the afflicted one are bad, But the one with a cheerful* heart has a continual feast.

Or “good.”

^ (Matt. 6:34) So never be anxious about the next day, for the next day will have its own anxieties. Each day has enough of its own troubles.

^ (Ps. 130:4) For with you there is true forgiveness, So that you may be held in awe.*

Lit., “be feared.”

^ (Prov. 12:25) Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down,* But a good word cheers it up.

Or “depresses him.”

^ (Prov. 17:17) A true friend shows love at all times, And is a brother who is born for times of distress.

^ ***w07 5/15 pp. 18-19 “Your Plans Will Be Firmly Established”***

Self-love may cause us to justify our errors, camouflage bad personality traits, and be blind to our own badness. Jehovah, though, cannot be deceived. He is making an estimate of spirits. A person’s spirit is his or her dominant mental inclination and is connected to the heart. To a large extent, its development depends on the activity of the figurative heart, which involves such things as our thoughts, emotions, and motives. The spirit is what “the examiner of hearts” estimates, and his judgments are free from favoritism or partiality. We are wise to guard our spirit.

“Roll Your Works Upon Jehovah”

Making plans involves the thought process—an activity of our heart. Deeds usually follow plans. Will we succeed in our endeavors? Solomon says: “Roll your works upon Jehovah himself and your plans will be firmly established.” (Proverbs 16:3) To roll our works on Jehovah means to place our trust in him, to rely on him, to be committed to him—to roll the burden off our shoulders, as it were, onto his. The psalmist sang: “Roll upon Jehovah your way, and rely upon him, and he himself will act.”—[Psalm 37:5].

For our plans to be firmly established, however, they must be in harmony with God’s Word, and they must stem from good motives. Moreover, we should pray to Jehovah for help and support and conscientiously do our best to follow the Bible’s advice. It is particularly important to ‘throw our burden upon Jehovah’ when we are faced with trials or difficulties, for ‘he will sustain us.’ Indeed, “never will he allow the righteous one to totter.”—[Psalm 55:22].

“Everything Jehovah Has Made for His Purpose”

What else will result from our rolling our works upon Jehovah? “Everything Jehovah has made for his purpose,” says the wise king. (Proverbs 16:4a) The Creator of the universe is a God of purpose. When we roll our works upon him, our life becomes filled with purposeful and meaningful activity, void of futility or vanity. And Jehovah’s purpose for the earth and man upon it is eternal. (Ephesians 3:11) He formed the earth and created it “to be inhabited.” ([Isaiah 45:18]) Moreover, what he originally purposed for mankind on earth is bound to become a reality. ([Genesis 1:28]) A life devoted to the true God will be unending and have meaning forever.

Jehovah has made “even the wicked one for the evil day.” (Proverbs 16:4b) He did not create the wicked, for “perfect is his activity.” (Deuteronomy 32:4) However, he has allowed them to come into existence and continue living until he sees fit to execute his adverse judgment. For example, Jehovah said to Pharaoh of Egypt: “For this cause I have kept you in existence, for the sake of showing you my power and in order to have my name declared in all the earth.” ([Exodus 9:16]) The Ten Plagues and the destruction of Pharaoh and his forces in the Red Sea were indeed memorable demonstrations of God’s matchless power.

Jehovah can also make circumstances work out in such a way that the wicked unknowingly serve his purpose. The psalmist said: “The very rage of man will laud you; the remainder of raging you [Jehovah] will gird upon yourself.” ([Psalm 76:10]) Jehovah may allow his enemies to express their rage toward his servants—but only to the extent necessary to discipline his people and thus train them. What is in excess of this, God takes upon himself.

While Jehovah supports his humble servants, what about the proud and arrogant? “Everyone that is proud in heart is something detestable to Jehovah,” says the king of Israel. “Hand may join to hand, yet one will not be free from punishment.” (Proverbs 16:5) Those “proud in heart” may band together in mutual support, but they will not escape punishment. We are wise, then, to cultivate the spirit of humility regardless of how knowledgeable we are or how capable we may be or whatever service privileges we may have.

“In the Fear of Jehovah”

Born in sin, we are prone to err. ([Romans 3:23;][5:12]) What will help us to avoid making plans that will lead to a bad course? Proverbs 16:6 states: “By loving-kindness and trueness error is atoned for, and in the fear of Jehovah one turns away from bad.” While by his loving-kindness and trueness Jehovah atones for our sins, it is the fear of Jehovah that serves as a deterrent to committing sins. How vital it is that along with love for God and appreciation for his loving-kindness, we cultivate fear of displeasing him!

The fear of God enters into our heart when we develop reverence and respect for God’s awesome power. Just think of his power reflected in the creation! Being reminded of the manifestation of power in God’s creative works helped the patriarch Job to readjust his thinking. ([Job 42:1-6]) Are we not likewise affected when we read and reflect on the accounts of Jehovah’s dealings with his people as recorded in the Bible? The psalmist sang: “Come, you people, and see the activities of God. His dealing with the sons of men is fear-inspiring.” ([Psalm 66:5]) Jehovah’s loving-kindness is not to be taken for granted. When the Israelites ‘rebelled and made God’s holy spirit feel hurt, Jehovah was changed into an enemy of theirs; he himself warred against them.’ ([Isaiah 63:10]) On the other hand, “when Jehovah takes pleasure in the ways of a man he causes even his enemies themselves to be at peace with him.” (Proverbs 16:7) What a protection the fear of Jehovah is!

“Better is a little with righteousness than an abundance of products without justice,” says the wise king. (Proverbs 16:8) Proverbs 15:16 states: “Better is a little in the fear of Jehovah than an abundant supply and confusion along with it.” A reverential awe of God is certainly essential for staying on a righteous course.

“The Heart of Earthling Man May Think Out His Way”

Man was created a free moral agent, able to choose between right and wrong. (Deuteronomy 30:19, 20) Our figurative heart has the ability to consider different options and fix its aim on one or more of them. Indicating that making choices is our responsibility, Solomon says: “The heart of earthling man may think out his way.” Once this is done, “Jehovah himself does the directing of his steps.” (Proverbs 16:9) Since Jehovah can

^ (Prov. 16:3) Commit to Jehovah whatever you do,* And your plans will succeed.

Lit., “Roll to Jehovah your works.”

^ (Ps. 37:5) Commit your way to* Jehovah; Rely on him, and he will act in your behalf.

Lit., “Roll your way upon.”

^ (Ps. 55:22) Throw your burden on Jehovah, And he will sustain you. Never will he allow the righteous one to fall.*

Or “stagger; totter.”

^ (Prov. 16:4) Jehovah has made everything work for his purpose, Even the wicked for the day of disaster.

^ (Eph. 3:11) This is according to the eternal purpose that he formed in connection with the Christ, Jesus our Lord,

^ (Isa. 45:18) For this is what Jehovah says, The Creator of the heavens, the true God, The One who formed the earth, its Maker who firmly established it, Who did not create it simply for nothing,* but formed it to be inhabited: “I am Jehovah, and there is no one else.

Or possibly, “to be empty.”

^ (Gen. 1:28) Further, God blessed them, and God said to them: “Be fruitful and become many, fill the earth and subdue it, and have in subjection the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and every living creature that is moving on the earth.”

^ (Prov. 16:4) Jehovah has made everything work for his purpose, Even the wicked for the day of disaster.

^ (Deut. 32:4) The Rock, perfect is his activity, For all his ways are justice. A God of faithfulness who is never unjust; Righteous and upright is he.

^ (Ex. 9:16) But for this very reason I have kept you in existence: to show you my power and to have my name declared in all the earth.

^ (Ps. 76:10) For the rage of man will serve to your praise; With the remnants of their rage you will adorn yourself.

^ (Prov. 16:5) Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah. Be assured* that he will not go unpunished.

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

^ (Rom. 3:23) For all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God,

^ (Rom. 5:12) That is why, just as through one man sin entered into the world and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because they had all sinned—.

^ (Prov. 16:6) By loyal love and faithfulness, error is atoned for, And by fearing Jehovah one turns away from bad.

^ (Job 42:1-6) Then Job said in reply to Jehovah:  2 “Now I know that you are able to do all things And that nothing you have in mind to do is impossible for you.  3 You said, ‘Who is this who is obscuring my counsel without knowledge?’ Therefore I spoke, but without understanding About things too wonderful for me, which I do not know.  4 You said, ‘Please listen, and I will speak. I will question you, and you inform me.’  5 My ears have heard about you, But now I do see you with my eyes.  6 That is why I take back what I said,* And I repent in dust and ashes.”

Or “make a retraction.”

^ (Ps. 66:5) Come and see the works of God. His deeds toward the sons of men are awe-inspiring.

^ (Isa. 63:10) But they rebelled and grieved his holy spirit. He then turned into their enemy, And he fought against them.

^ (Prov. 16:7) When Jehovah is pleased with a man’s ways, He causes even his enemies to be at peace with him.

^ (Prov. 16:8) Better is a little with righteousness Than a large income without justice.

^ (Prov. 15:16) Better is a little in the fear of Jehovah Than great wealth along with anxiety.*

Or “confusion.”

^ (Deut. 30:19, 20) I take the heavens and the earth as witnesses against you today that I have put life and death before you, the blessing and the curse; and you must choose life so that you may live, you and your descendants, 20 by loving Jehovah your God, by listening to his voice, and by sticking to him, for he is your life and by him you will endure a long time in the land that Jehovah swore to give to your forefathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.”

^ (Prov. 16:9) A man may plot out his course in his heart, But it is Jehovah who directs his steps.

^ ***bh pp. 191-192 Remain in God’s Love***

18. Why should we worship Jehovah publicly in association with true Christians?

18 Jehovah wants us to worship him publicly in association with true Christians. That is why his Word says: “Let us consider one another so as to incite to love and fine works, not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.” (Hebrews 10:24, 25) When we gather with fellow believers at Christian meetings, we have a wonderful opportunity to praise and worship our beloved God. We also build one another up and encourage one another.

19. How can we work to strengthen the bonds of love in the Christian congregation?

19 As we associate with other worshippers of Jehovah, we strengthen the bonds of love and friendship in the congregation. It is important that we look for the good in one another, as Jehovah looks for the good in us. Do not expect perfection from your fellow believers. Remember that all are at different stages of spiritual growth and that every one of us makes mistakes. (Read Colossians 3:13.) Seek to build close friendships with those who love Jehovah intensely, and you will find yourself growing spiritually. Yes, worshipping Jehovah with your spiritual brothers and sisters will help you to remain in God’s love. How does Jehovah reward those who worship him faithfully and thus remain in his love?

^ par. 18 (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ par. 19 (Col. 3:13) Continue putting up with one another and forgiving one another freely even if anyone has a cause for complaint against another. Just as Jehovah* freely forgave you, you must also do the same.

See App. A5.

^ ***sn song 117 We Must Be Taught***

Song 117

We Must Be Taught

([Isaiah 50:4;][54:13])

1. Come with rejoicing, and learn about Jehovah.

“Come drink life’s water,” the spirit has said.

Healthful instruction, God has provided.

All those who hunger for truth will be fed.

2. Never forsaking our gathering together,

We must be taught; we must learn what is right.

Here with God’s spirit, here with our brothers,

Here we are strengthened to walk in the light.

3. Lips that sing praise, how encouraging to hear them!

Tongues of the taught ones, how sweet is their sound!

Oh, may we always meet with God’s people!

Oh, may we always among them be found!

(See also Heb. 10:24, 25;[Rev. 22:17].)

^ (Isa. 50:4) The Sovereign Lord Jehovah has given me the tongue of those taught,* So that I may know how to answer* the tired one with the right word.* He awakens me morning by morning; He awakens my ear to listen like the taught ones.

Or “a well-trained tongue.”

Or possibly, “strengthen.”

Lit., “with a word.”

^ (Isa. 54:13) And all your sons* will be taught by Jehovah, And the peace of your sons* will be abundant.

Or “children.”

Or “children.”

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Rev. 22:17) And the spirit and the bride keep on saying, “Come!” and let anyone hearing say, “Come!” and let anyone thirsting come; let anyone who wishes take life’s water free.

^ ***kr pp. 19-23 The Kingdom Is Born in Heaven***

Zealous Preaching

23. How did the Watch Tower make it plain that all anointed ones must be preachers of the truth?

23 The Bible Students taught that all the anointed must be preachers of the truth. In 1885, the Watch Tower commented: “We should not forget that every member of the anointed body is anointed to preach ([Isa. 61:1]), called to the ministry.” An 1888 issue contained this exhortation: “Our commission is plain . . . If we ignore it and excuse ourselves, we are certainly slothful servants, proving our unworthiness of the high position to which we are called.”

24, 25. (a) How did Russell and his close associates do more than encourage people to preach? (b) How did one colporteur describe his work in the “preautomobile days”?

24 Brother Russell and his close associates did more than encourage people to preach. They also began to produce tracts called Bible Students’ Tracts, which were later also called Old Theology Quarterly. Readers of the Watch Tower received these to distribute to the public without charge.

We do well to ask ourselves, ‘Is the preaching work central to my life?’

25 Those who devoted themselves to the ministry full-time were called colporteurs. Charles Capen, mentioned earlier, was among them. He later recalled: “I used maps made by the United States Government Geological Survey to guide my covering the territory in Pennsylvania. These maps showed all the roads, making it possible to reach all sections of each county on foot. Sometimes after a three-day trip through the country taking orders for the books in the Studies in the Scriptures series, I would hire a horse and buggy so that I could make the deliveries. I often stopped and stayed overnight with farmers. Those were the preautomobile days.”

26. (a) Why did God’s people need to engage in the preaching work in order to be prepared for Christ’s reign? (b) What questions do we do well to ask ourselves?

26 Such early efforts at preaching certainly required courage and zeal. Would true Christians have been prepared for Christ’s reign if they had not been taught the importance of the preaching work? Assuredly not! After all, that work was to become an outstanding feature of Christ’s presence. ([Matt. 24:14]) God’s people had to be prepared to make that lifesaving work the central feature of their lives. We today do well to ask ourselves: ‘Is the preaching work central to my life? Do I make sacrifices in order to have a full share in that activity?’

God’s Kingdom Is Born!

27, 28. What did the apostle John witness in vision, and how did Satan and his demons react to the birth of the Kingdom?

27 Finally, the momentous year 1914 arrived. As we discussed at the outset of this chapter, there were no human eyewitnesses to the glorious events in heaven. However, the apostle John was given a vision that described matters in symbolic terms. Imagine this: John witnesses “a great sign” in heaven. God’s “woman”—his organization of spirit creatures in heaven—is pregnant and gives birth to a male child. This symbolic child, we are told, is soon to “shepherd all the nations with an iron rod.” Upon its birth, though, the child is “snatched away to God and to his throne.” A loud voice in heaven says: “Now have come to pass the salvation and the power and the Kingdom of our God and the authority of his Christ.”—[Rev. 12:1,][5,][10].

28 Without doubt, John saw in vision the birth of the Messianic Kingdom. That event was surely a glorious one, but it did not please everyone. Satan and his demons warred against the faithful angels, who were under the leadership of Michael, or Christ. The outcome? We read: “Down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.”—[Rev. 12:7,][9].

29, 30. Following the birth of the Messianic Kingdom, how did conditions change (a) on earth? (b) in heaven?

29 Long before 1914, the Bible Students said that a time of trouble would begin in that marked year. But even they could not have imagined how accurate that prediction would turn out to be. As John’s vision revealed, Satan would then begin to have an even greater impact on human society: “Woe for the earth and for the sea, because the Devil has come down to you, having great anger, knowing that he has a short period of time.” ([Rev. 12:12]) In 1914, the first world war broke out and the sign of Christ’s presence in kingly power began to see global fulfillment. The “last days” of this system of things had begun.—[2 Tim. 3:1].

30 However, there was joy in heaven. Satan and his demons were banished forever. John’s account reads: “On this account be glad, you heavens and you who reside in them!” ([Rev. 12:12]) With the heavens cleansed and Jesus enthroned as King, the Messianic Kingdom was now poised to act in behalf of God’s people on earth. What action would it take? As we saw at the outset of this chapter, Christ as “the messenger of the covenant” would first act as a refiner of God’s servants here on earth. What would that mean?

A Time of Testing

31. What did Malachi foretell about the period of refining, and how did that prophecy begin to see fulfillment? (See also the footnote.)

31 Malachi foretold that the refining process would not be easy. He wrote: “Who will endure the day of his coming, and who will be able to stand when he appears? For he will be like the fire of a refiner and like the lye of laundrymen.” ([Mal. 3:2]) How true those words proved to be! Beginning in 1914, God’s people on earth faced a succession of major tests and hardships. As World War I raged, many Bible Students experienced vicious persecution and imprisonment.*

32. What internal turmoil afflicted God’s people following 1916?

32 From within, the organization suffered turmoil as well. In 1916, Brother Russell died at only 64 years of age, leaving many of God’s people in shock. His death revealed that some had been placing too much emphasis on one exemplary man. Though Brother Russell wanted no such reverence, a measure of creature worship had grown up around him. Many thought that the progressive revelation of truth had ended with his death, and some bitterly resisted efforts to move forward. That attitude contributed to an outbreak of apostasy that divided the organization.

33. How did unfulfilled expectations test God’s people?

33 Unfulfilled expectations were another test. Though the Watch Tower had rightly pointed to 1914 as the year when the Gentile Times would end, the brothers did not yet understand what would take place in that year. ([Luke 21:24]) They thought that in 1914, Christ would take his anointed bride class to heaven to rule with him there. Those hopes were not realized. Late in 1917, The Watch Tower announced that a 40-year harvest period would end in the spring of 1918. But the preaching work did not end. It continued to prosper after that date passed. The magazine suggested that the harvest had indeed ended but that a period of gleaning remained. Still, many stopped serving Jehovah because of disappointment.

34. What daunting test arose in 1918, and why did Christendom think that God’s people were “dead”?

34 A daunting test arose in 1918. J. F. Rutherford, who succeeded C. T. Russell in taking the lead among God’s people, was arrested along with seven other responsible brothers. They were unjustly sentenced to long terms of imprisonment in the federal penitentiary in Atlanta, Georgia, U.S.A. For a time, the work of God’s people may have seemed paralyzed. Many among the clergy of Christendom rejoiced. They assumed that with the “leaders” imprisoned, the headquarters in Brooklyn closed up, and the preaching work under attack in America and Europe, those pestilent Bible Students were “dead”—no longer a threat. ([Rev. 11:3,][7-10]) How wrong they were!

^ par. 23 (Isa. 61:1) The spirit of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah is upon me, Because Jehovah anointed me to declare good news to the meek. He sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, To proclaim liberty to the captives And the wide opening of the eyes to the prisoners,

^ par. 26 (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ par. 27 (Rev. 12:1) Then a great sign was seen in heaven: A woman was arrayed* with the sun, and the moon was beneath her feet, and on her head was a crown of 12 stars,

Or “clothed.”

^ par. 27 (Rev. 12:5) And she gave birth to a son, a male, who is to shepherd all the nations with an iron rod. And her child was snatched* away to God and to his throne.

Or “caught.”

^ par. 27 (Rev. 12:10) I heard a loud voice in heaven say: “Now have come to pass the salvation and the power and the Kingdom of our God and the authority of his Christ, because the accuser of our brothers has been hurled down, who accuses them day and night before our God!

^ par. 28 (Rev. 12:7) And war broke out in heaven: Miʹcha·el* and his angels battled with the dragon, and the dragon and its angels battled

Meaning “Who Is Like God?”

^ par. 28 (Rev. 12:9) So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.

^ par. 29 (Rev. 12:12) On this account be glad, you heavens and you who reside in them! Woe for the earth and for the sea, because the Devil has come down to you, having great anger, knowing that he has a short period of time.”

^ par. 29 (2 Tim. 3:1) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.

^ par. 30 (Rev. 12:12) On this account be glad, you heavens and you who reside in them! Woe for the earth and for the sea, because the Devil has come down to you, having great anger, knowing that he has a short period of time.”

^ par. 31 (Mal. 3:2) “But who will endure the day of his coming, and who will be able to stand when he appears? For he will be like the fire of a refiner and like the lye* of laundrymen.

Or “soap.”

^ par. 33 (Luke 21:24) And they will fall by the edge of the sword and be led captive into all the nations; and Jerusalem will be trampled on by the nations* until the appointed times of the nations* are fulfilled.

Or “Gentiles.”

Or “Gentiles.”

^ par. 34 (Rev. 11:3) I will cause my two witnesses to prophesy for 1,260 days dressed in sackcloth.”

^ par. 34 (Rev. 11:7-10) When they have finished their witnessing, the wild beast that ascends out of the abyss will wage war with them and conquer them and kill them. 8 And their corpses will be on the main street of the great city that is in a spiritual sense called Sodʹom and Egypt, where their Lord was also executed on the stake. 9 And those of the peoples and tribes and tongues* and nations will look at their corpses for three and a half days, and they do not allow their corpses to be laid in a tomb. 10 And those dwelling on the earth rejoice over them and celebrate, and they will send gifts to one another, because these two prophets tormented those dwelling on the earth.

Or “languages.”

^ par. 31 In September 1920, The Golden Age (now Awake!) published a special issue detailing numerous instances of wartime persecution—some of it shockingly brutal—in Canada, England, Germany, and the United States. In contrast, the decades prior to the first world war saw very little persecution of that kind.

^ ***sn song 102 Join in the Kingdom Song!***

Song 102

Join in the Kingdom Song!

([Psalm 98:1])

1. This is a song, a happy song of vict’ry;

It magnifies the One who is supreme.

The words give hope and prompt all to be loyal.

Come sing with us; enjoy its Kingdom theme:

(CHORUS)

‘Come worship God Before His throne.

His Son is King; Let’s make it known!

Come learn this song, this song about the Kingdom;

Bow down to God, and praise His holy name.’

2. With this new song, we advertise the Kingdom.

Christ Jesus rules; the earth is his domain.

And as foretold, there is a newborn nation:

The Kingdom heirs, who welcome Jesus’ reign:

(CHORUS)

‘Come worship God Before His throne.

His Son is King; Let’s make it known!

Come learn this song, this song about the Kingdom;

Bow down to God, and praise His holy name.’

3. This Kingdom song, all humble ones can master.

The words are clear, their message warm and bright.

In all the earth, vast multitudes have learned it,

And they in turn still others now invite:

(CHORUS)

‘Come worship God Before His throne.

His Son is King; Let’s make it known!

Come learn this song, this song about the Kingdom;

Bow down to God, and praise His holy name.’

(See also [Ps. 95:6;] 1 Pet. 2:9, 10;[Rev. 12:10].)

^ (Ps. 98:1) Sing to Jehovah a new song, For he has done wonderful things. His right hand, his holy arm, has brought about salvation.*

Or “has won him victory.”

^ (Ps. 95:6) Come, let us worship and bow down; Let us kneel before Jehovah our Maker.

^ (1 Pet. 2:9, 10) But you are “a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for special possession, that you should declare abroad the excellencies”* of the One who called you out of darkness into his wonderful light. 10 For you were once not a people, but now you are God’s people; once you had not been shown mercy, but now you have received mercy.

Lit., “the virtues,” that is, his praiseworthy qualities and deeds.

^ (Rev. 12:10) I heard a loud voice in heaven say: “Now have come to pass the salvation and the power and the Kingdom of our God and the authority of his Christ, because the accuser of our brothers has been hurled down, who accuses them day and night before our God!

^ (Prov. 12:1-16:33) The one who loves discipline loves knowledge, But the one who hates reproof is unreasoning.*  2 The good person obtains Jehovah’s approval, But He condemns the man of wicked schemes.  3 No man is made secure by wickedness, But the righteous will never be uprooted.  4 A capable wife is a crown to her husband, But the wife who acts shamefully is like rottenness in his bones.  5 The thoughts of the righteous are just, But the guidance of the wicked is deceptive.  6 The words of the wicked are a deadly ambush,* But the mouth of the upright saves them.  7 When the wicked are overthrown, they are no more, But the house of the righteous will keep standing.  8 A man is praised for the discretion of his mouth, But one with a twisted heart will be treated with contempt.  9 Better to be lightly esteemed and have a servant Than to glorify oneself and have no food.* 10 The righteous one takes care of his domestic animals,* But even the mercy of the wicked is cruel. 11 The one who cultivates his land will be satisfied with food, But the one pursuing worthless things is lacking good sense.* 12 The wicked man envies what other evil men have caught, But the root of the righteous bears fruit. 13 The evil man is ensnared by his own sinful speech, But the righteous one escapes from distress. 14 From the fruitage of his speech* a man is satisfied with good, And the work of his hands will reward him. 15 The way of the fool is right in his own eyes, But the wise one accepts advice.* 16 A fool immediately* shows his annoyance, But the shrewd man overlooks* an insult. 17 The one who testifies faithfully will tell the truth,* But a false witness speaks deceit. 18 Thoughtless speech is like the stabs of a sword, But the tongue of the wise is a healing. 19 Truthful lips will endure forever, But a lying tongue will last for only a moment. 20 Deceit is in the heart of those who plot mischief, But those who promote* peace have joy. 21 No harm will befall the righteous one, But the wicked will have their fill of calamity. 22 Lying lips are detestable to Jehovah, But those acting faithfully bring pleasure to him. 23 A shrewd man conceals what he knows, But the heart of the fool blurts out his foolishness. 24 The hand of the diligent ones will rule, But idle hands will be put to forced labor. 25 Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down,* But a good word cheers it up. 26 The righteous one searches out his pastures, But the course of the wicked leads them astray. 27 The lazy do not chase after the prey, But diligence is a man’s precious treasure. 28 The path of righteousness leads to life; Along its pathway there is no death.

13 A wise son accepts his father’s discipline, But the scoffer does not listen to a rebuke.*  2 From the fruitage of his speech* a man will eat what is good, But the very desire* of the treacherous is for violence.  3 The one guarding his mouth* protects his life,* But the one opening his lips wide will come to ruin.  4 The lazy person has his cravings, yet he* has nothing, But the diligent one* will be fully satisfied.*  5 The righteous one hates lies, But the actions of the wicked bring shame and disgrace.  6 Righteousness protects the one whose way is innocent, But wickedness brings down the sinner.  7 There is one who pretends to be rich, yet has nothing; There is another who pretends to be poor, yet has great wealth.  8 Riches are the ransom for a man’s life,* But the poor are not even threatened.*  9 The light of the righteous shines brightly,* But the lamp of the wicked will be extinguished. 10 Presumptuousness leads only to strife, But wisdom belongs to those who seek advice.* 11 Wealth quickly gained* will dwindle, But the wealth of the one who gathers it little by little* will increase. 12 Expectation* postponed makes the heart sick, But a desire realized is a tree of life. 13 Whoever despises instruction* will pay the penalty, But the one who respects the commandment will be rewarded. 14 The teaching* of the wise one is a source of life To turn one away from the snares of death. 15 Keen insight wins favor, But the way of the treacherous is harsh. 16 The shrewd person acts with knowledge, But the fool exposes his own foolishness. 17 A wicked messenger falls into trouble, But a faithful envoy brings healing. 18 Whoever neglects discipline comes to poverty and disgrace, But the one accepting correction* will be glorified. 19 Desire when realized is sweet to a person,* But the stupid hate to turn away from bad. 20 The one walking with the wise will become wise, But the one who has dealings with the stupid will fare badly. 21 Calamity pursues sinners, But prosperity rewards the righteous. 22 The good person leaves an inheritance to his grandchildren, But the sinner’s wealth will be stored up for the righteous one. 23 The plowed field of the poor yields much food, But it* may be swept away by injustice. 24 Whoever holds back his rod* hates his son, But the one who loves him disciplines him diligently.* 25 The righteous one eats and satisfies his appetite,* But the stomach of the wicked is empty.

14 The truly wise woman builds up her house, But the foolish one tears it down with her own hands.  2 The one walking in his uprightness fears Jehovah, But the one whose ways are devious* despises Him.  3 The rod of haughtiness is in the mouth of the fool, But the lips of the wise will protect them.  4 Where there are no cattle the manger is clean, But the power of a bull yields an abundant harvest.  5 A faithful witness will not lie, But a false witness lies with every breath.  6 The scoffer seeks wisdom and finds none, But knowledge comes easily to the person with understanding.  7 Stay away from the foolish man, For you will not find knowledge on his lips.  8 By wisdom the shrewd man understands the way he is going, But the stupid are deceived* by their foolishness.  9 Fools make fun of guilt,* But among the upright, there is a willingness to reconcile.* 10 The heart knows its own bitterness,* And no outsider can share in its joy. 11 The house of the wicked will be destroyed, But the tent of the upright will flourish. 12 There is a way that seems right to a man, But in the end it leads to death. 13 Even in laughter the heart may feel pain, And rejoicing may end in grief. 14 The one wayward at heart will reap the results of his ways, But the good man reaps the reward of his dealings. 15 The naive* person believes every word, But the shrewd one ponders each step. 16 The wise one is cautious and turns away from evil, But the stupid one is reckless* and overconfident. 17 The one who is quick to anger acts foolishly, But the man who thinks things out* is hated. 18 The naive* will inherit foolishness, But the shrewd are crowned with knowledge. 19 Bad people will have to bow down before the good, And the wicked will bow at the gates of the righteous. 20 The poor man is hated even by his neighbors, But many are the friends of the rich person. 21 The one who despises his neighbor sins, But whoever shows compassion to the lowly is happy. 22 Will not those who plot mischief go astray? But those intent on doing good will receive loyal love and faithfulness. 23 There is benefit in every kind of hard work, But mere talk leads to want. 24 The crown of the wise is their wealth; But the foolishness of the stupid is only foolishness. 25 A true witness saves lives,* But a deceitful one lies with every breath. 26 There is strong confidence in the fear of Jehovah, And it will be a refuge for his children. 27 The fear of Jehovah is a fountain of life, To turn one away from the snares of death. 28 A multitude of people are a king’s majesty, But a ruler without subjects is ruined. 29 The one who is slow to anger has great discernment, But the impatient one displays his foolishness. 30 A calm heart gives life* to the body, But jealousy is rottenness to the bones. 31 The one who defrauds the lowly one insults his Maker, But whoever shows compassion to the poor glorifies Him. 32 The wicked one will be brought down by his own evil, But the righteous one will find refuge in his integrity. 33 Wisdom rests quietly in the heart of an understanding person, But among the stupid it must make itself known. 34 Righteousness exalts a nation, But sin is disgraceful to a people. 35 The king finds pleasure in a servant who acts with insight, But his fury is against the one who acts shamefully.

15 A mild* answer turns away rage, But a harsh* word stirs up anger.  2 The tongue of the wise makes good use of knowledge, But the mouth of the stupid blurts out foolishness.  3 The eyes of Jehovah are everywhere, Watching both the bad and the good.  4 A calm tongue* is a tree of life, But twisted speech causes despair.*  5 A fool disrespects his father’s discipline, But a shrewd person accepts correction.*  6 In the house of the righteous one there is abundant treasure, But the produce* of the wicked one brings him trouble.  7 The lips of the wise spread knowledge, But not so the heart of the stupid one.  8 The sacrifice of the wicked is detestable to Jehovah, But the prayer of the upright is a pleasure to Him.  9 Jehovah detests the way of the wicked one, But he loves the one who pursues righteousness. 10 Discipline seems bad* to one forsaking the way, But whoever hates reproof will die. 11 The Grave* and the place of destruction* are in full view of Jehovah. How much more so the hearts of men! 12 The scoffer does not love the one correcting* him. He will not consult the wise. 13 A joyful heart makes for a cheerful countenance, But heartache crushes the spirit. 14 The understanding heart seeks knowledge, But the mouth of the stupid feeds on* foolishness. 15 All the days of the afflicted one are bad, But the one with a cheerful* heart has a continual feast. 16 Better is a little in the fear of Jehovah Than great wealth along with anxiety.* 17 Better is a dish of vegetables where there is love Than a fattened* bull where there is hatred. 18 A hot-tempered man stirs up strife, But one who is slow to anger calms a quarrel. 19 The way of the lazy one is like a hedge of thorns, But the path of the upright is like a level highway. 20 A wise son makes his father rejoice, But a stupid man despises his mother. 21 Foolishness is a joy to one lacking good sense,* But the man of discernment walks straight ahead. 22 Plans fail when there is no consultation,* But there is accomplishment through many advisers.* 23 A man rejoices in giving the right answer,* And a word spoken at the right time—how good it is! 24 The path of life leads upward to one with insight, To turn him away from the Grave* below. 25 Jehovah will tear down the house of the haughty, But he will preserve the boundary of the widow. 26 Jehovah detests the schemes of the wicked one, But pleasant sayings are pure to Him. 27 The one making dishonest profit brings trouble* on his own household, But the one hating bribes will keep living. 28 The heart of the righteous one meditates before answering,* But the mouth of the wicked blurts out bad things. 29 Jehovah is far away from the wicked, But he hears the prayer of the righteous. 30 Bright eyes make* the heart rejoice; A good report invigorates the bones.* 31 The one who listens to life-giving reproof Is at home among the wise. 32 Anyone refusing discipline despises his life,* But whoever listens to reproof acquires understanding.* 33 The fear of Jehovah is a training in wisdom, And before glory there is humility.

16 A man prepares the thoughts of his heart,* But the answer he gives* is from Jehovah.  2 All of a man’s ways seem right* to him, But Jehovah examines the motives.*  3 Commit to Jehovah whatever you do,* And your plans will succeed.  4 Jehovah has made everything work for his purpose, Even the wicked for the day of disaster.  5 Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah. Be assured* that he will not go unpunished.  6 By loyal love and faithfulness, error is atoned for, And by fearing Jehovah one turns away from bad.  7 When Jehovah is pleased with a man’s ways, He causes even his enemies to be at peace with him.  8 Better is a little with righteousness Than a large income without justice.  9 A man may plot out his course in his heart, But it is Jehovah who directs his steps. 10 Inspired* decision should be on the lips of a king; He must never betray justice. 11 Honest balances and scales are from Jehovah; All the weights in the bag are his doing. 12 Wicked practices are detestable to kings, For the throne is firmly established by righteousness. 13 Righteous speech is a pleasure to kings. They love someone who speaks honestly. 14 The king’s rage is like a messenger of death, But the wise man appeases* it. 15 In the light of the king’s face there is life; His favor is like a cloud of rain in spring. 16 How much better to acquire wisdom than gold! To gain understanding is to be chosen over silver. 17 The highway of the upright avoids what is bad. Whoever safeguards his way preserves his life.* 18 Pride is before a crash, And a haughty spirit before stumbling. 19 Better to be humble* among the meek Than to share the spoil of the haughty. 20 The one who shows insight in a matter will find success,* And happy is the one trusting in Jehovah. 21 The wise in heart will be called understanding, And the one kind in speech* adds persuasiveness. 22 Insight is a fountain of life to those possessing it, But fools are disciplined by their own foolishness. 23 The heart of the wise one gives his mouth insight And adds persuasiveness to his speech. 24 Pleasant sayings are a honeycomb, Sweet to the soul* and a healing to the bones. 25 There is a way that seems right to a man, But in the end it leads to death. 26 The appetite* of a laborer makes him work hard For his hunger* urges him on. 27 A worthless man digs up what is bad; His speech is like a scorching fire. 28 A troublemaker* causes dissension, And a slanderer separates close friends. 29 A violent man entices his neighbor And leads him in the wrong way. 30 He winks his eye as he schemes harm. He pinches his lips together as he carries out mischief. 31 Gray hair is a crown of beauty* When it is found in the way of righteousness. 32 The one slow to anger is better than a mighty man, And the one controlling his temper* than one conquering a city. 33 The lot is cast into the lap, But every decision by it is from Jehovah.

Or “has no sense.”

Lit., “lie in wait for blood.”

Lit., “bread.”

Or “the soul of his domestic animal.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “counsel.”

Or “in the same day.”

Lit., “covers over.”

Lit., “what is righteous.”

Lit., “those who are counselors of.”

Or “depresses him.”

Or “correction.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “soul.”

Or “what he says.”

Or “soul.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “will be made fat.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “hear no rebuke.”

Lit., “rejoices.”

Or “those consulting together.”

Or “Wealth from vanity.”

Lit., “gathers by hand.”

Or “Hope.”

Or “the word.”

Or “law.”

Or “reproof.”

Or “soul.”

Or “he.”

Or “discipline; punishment.”

Or possibly, “promptly.”

Or “soul.”

Or “crooked.”

Or possibly, “the stupid deceive others.”

Or “of making amends.”

Or “there is goodwill.”

Or “the bitterness of its soul.”

Or “inexperienced.”

Or “furious.”

Or “the man of thinking abilities.”

Or “inexperienced.”

Or “souls.”

Or “health.”

Or “gentle.”

Or “painful.”

Or “A tongue of healing.”

Lit., “the crushing of the spirit.”

Or “reproof.”

Or “income.”

Or “severe.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “and Abaddon.”

Or “reproving.”

Or “pursues.”

Or “good.”

Or “confusion.”

Lit., “manger-fed.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “confidential talk.”

Or “counselors.”

Lit., “in the answer of his mouth.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “disgrace.”

Or “carefully considers how to answer; thinks before speaking.”

Or “A cheerful glance makes.”

Lit., “makes the bones fat.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “heart.”

Lit., “The arrangings of the heart belong to a man.”

Or “the right answer.” Lit., “the answer of the tongue.”

Lit., “pure.”

Lit., “spirits.”

Lit., “Roll to Jehovah your works.”

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

Or “Divine.”

Or “avoids.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “lowly of spirit.”

Lit., “good.”

Or “And appealing speech.” Lit., “And sweetness of lips.”

Or “taste.” See Glossary.

Or “soul.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “A schemer.”

Or “glory.”

Lit., “ruling over his spirit.”

^ (Prov. 17:1-21:31) Better is a piece of dry bread where there is peace* Than a house full of feasting* along with quarreling.  2 A servant with insight will rule over a son who acts shamefully; He will share in the inheritance as one of the brothers.  3 The refining pot is for silver and the furnace for gold, But Jehovah is the examiner of hearts.  4 A wicked man pays attention to hurtful speech, And a deceptive man listens to a malicious tongue.  5 Whoever mocks the poor insults his Maker, And whoever rejoices over another’s disaster will not go unpunished.  6 Grandsons* are a crown to the aged, And fathers* are the glory of their sons.*  7 Upright* speech does not befit a fool. How much less does false speech befit a ruler!*  8 A gift is like a precious stone* to its owner; Everywhere he turns, it brings him success.  9 Whoever forgives* a transgression seeks love, But the one who keeps harping on a matter separates close friends. 10 A rebuke makes a deeper impression on one having understanding Than striking a stupid person a hundred times. 11 A bad man seeks only rebellion, But a cruel messenger will be sent to punish him. 12 Better to meet a bear bereaved of her cubs Than to encounter someone stupid in his foolishness. 13 If anyone repays bad for good, Bad will not depart from his house. 14 Beginning a fight is like opening a floodgate;* Before the quarrel breaks out, take your leave. 15 Anyone who acquits the wicked one and anyone who condemns the righteous one —Both of them are detestable to Jehovah. 16 What good is it that the stupid one has the means to acquire wisdom When he has no heart for acquiring it?* 17 A true friend shows love at all times, And is a brother who is born for times of distress. 18 A man lacking good sense* shakes hands and agrees To put up security* in the presence of his neighbor. 19 The one who loves conflict loves transgression. Anyone who makes his entryway high invites a crash. 20 The one who is crooked at heart will not find success,* And the one who speaks deceitfully will fall into ruin. 21 The one who fathers a stupid child will experience grief; And the father of a senseless child has no joy. 22 A joyful heart is good medicine,* But a crushed spirit saps one’s strength.* 23 A wicked man will take a bribe in secret* To pervert the course of justice. 24 Wisdom is directly in front of the discerning person, But the eyes of the stupid wander to the ends of the earth. 25 A stupid son brings grief to his father And heartache* to the one who gave birth to him. 26 To punish* the righteous one is not good, And to flog honorable people goes against what is right. 27 A man of knowledge restrains his words, And a discerning man will remain calm.* 28 Even a fool who keeps silent will be considered wise, And the one who seals his lips, discerning.

18 Whoever isolates himself pursues his own selfish desires; He rejects* all practical wisdom.  2 A stupid person takes no pleasure in understanding; He would rather disclose what is in his heart.  3 When a wicked person comes, contempt also comes, And along with dishonor there is disgrace.  4 The words of a man’s mouth are deep waters. The fountain of wisdom is a bubbling brook.  5 It is not good to show partiality to the wicked one Or to deprive the righteous one of justice.  6 The speech of the stupid one leads to quarrels, And his mouth invites a beating.  7 The mouth of the stupid is his ruin, And his lips are a snare for his life.*  8 The words of a slanderer are like tasty morsels;* They are gulped right down into the stomach.  9 Whoever is lazy in his work Is a brother to the one who causes ruin. 10 The name of Jehovah is a strong tower. Into it the righteous one runs and receives protection.* 11 The wealth of the rich is his fortified city; It is like a protective wall in his imagination. 12 Before a crash a man’s heart is lofty, And before glory there is humility. 13 When anyone replies to a matter before he hears the facts, It is foolish and humiliating. 14 A person’s spirit can sustain him through illness, But who can bear a crushed spirit?* 15 The heart of the understanding one acquires knowledge, And the ear of the wise seeks to find knowledge. 16 A man’s gift opens the way for him; It gives him access to great people. 17 The first to state his case seems right, Until the other party comes and cross-examines him.* 18 Casting lots puts an end to disputes And decides between* strong opponents. 19 A brother offended is more unyielding than a fortified city, And there are disputes like the bars of a fortress. 20 From the fruitage of a man’s speech* his stomach will be filled; He will be satisfied with what his lips produce. 21 Death and life are in the power of the tongue; Those who love to use it will eat its fruitage. 22 The one who finds a good wife has found something good, And he receives Jehovah’s favor.* 23 The poor man implores when speaking, But the rich man answers harshly. 24 There are companions ready to crush one another, But there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.

19 It is better to be poor and walk in integrity Than to be stupid and speak lies.  2 A person* without knowledge is not good, And the one who acts rashly* is sinning.  3 It is a man’s own foolishness that distorts his way, And his heart becomes enraged against Jehovah.  4 Wealth attracts many friends, But the poor man will be deserted even by his friend.  5 A false witness will not go unpunished, And the one who lies with every breath will not escape.  6 Many seek the favor of a noble,* And everyone is a friend to the man who gives gifts.  7 All the brothers of a poor man hate him; How much more he is shunned by his friends! He pursues them with requests, but no one responds.  8 Whoever acquires good sense* loves himself.* Whoever treasures discernment will find success.*  9 A false witness will not go unpunished, And the one who lies with every breath will perish. 10 It is not fitting for a fool to live in luxury; How much less for a servant to rule over princes! 11 The insight of a man certainly slows down his anger, And it is beauty on his part to overlook* an offense.* 12 The king’s rage is like the growling of a lion,* But his favor is like dew on the vegetation. 13 A stupid son brings adversity on his father, And a quarrelsome* wife is like a roof that never stops leaking. 14 A house and wealth are inherited from fathers, But a discreet wife is from Jehovah. 15 Laziness brings on a deep sleep, And a sluggish person* will go hungry. 16 The one who keeps the commandment keeps his life;* The one who is reckless about his ways will die. 17 The one showing favor to the lowly is lending to Jehovah, And He will repay* him for what he does. 18 Discipline your son while there is hope, And do not become responsible for* his death. 19 The hot-tempered man will pay the penalty; If you try to spare him, you will have to do it again and again. 20 Listen to counsel and accept discipline, In order to become wise in your future. 21 Many are the plans in a man’s heart, But the counsel* of Jehovah is what will prevail. 22 The desirable thing in a man is his loyal love; And it is better to be poor than to be a liar. 23 The fear of Jehovah leads to life; The one who has it will have a pleasant rest, free from harm. 24 The lazy one buries his hand in the banquet bowl, But he does not even bother to bring it back to his mouth. 25 Strike the ridiculer, so that the inexperienced one may become shrewd, And reprove the understanding one, so that he will increase in knowledge. 26 The one who mistreats his father and drives away his mother Is a son causing shame and disgrace. 27 My son, if you stop listening to discipline, You will stray from the sayings of knowledge. 28 A worthless witness mocks justice, And the mouth of the wicked gulps down evil. 29 Judgment is in store for ridiculers, And beatings for the back of the stupid ones.

20 Wine is a ridiculer, alcohol is unruly; Whoever goes astray by them is not wise.  2 The terror* of a king is like the growling of a lion;* Whoever provokes his anger risks his own life.  3 It is honorable for a man to refrain from a dispute, But every fool will become embroiled in it.  4 The lazy one does not plow in winter, So he will be begging during the harvest when he has nothing.*  5 The thoughts* of a man’s heart are like deep waters, But the discerning man draws them out.  6 Many men proclaim their loyal love, But who can find a faithful man?  7 The righteous one is walking in his integrity. Happy are his children* who come after him.  8 When the king sits on the throne to judge, He sifts out all evil with his eyes.  9 Who can say: “I have cleansed my heart; I am pure from my sin”? 10 Dishonest weights and false measures* —Both are detestable to Jehovah. 11 Even a child* is known by his actions, Whether his behavior is pure and right. 12 The hearing ear and the seeing eye —Jehovah has made both of them. 13 Do not love sleep, or you will come to poverty. Open your eyes, and you will be satisfied with bread. 14 “It is no good, it is no good!” says the buyer; Then he goes away and boasts about himself. 15 There is gold, also much coral,* But the lips of knowledge are something precious. 16 Take a man’s garment if he has given security for a stranger; Seize the pledge from him if he did so for a foreign woman.* 17 Bread gained by deceit tastes good to a man, But afterward his mouth will be full of gravel. 18 By consultation,* plans will succeed,* And by skillful direction* wage your war. 19 A slanderer goes about revealing confidential talk; Do not associate with one who loves to gossip.* 20 Whoever curses his father and his mother, His lamp will be extinguished when darkness comes. 21 An inheritance obtained first by greed Will not be a blessing in the end. 22 Do not say: “I will pay back evil!” Hope in Jehovah, and he will save you. 23 Dishonest weights* are detestable to Jehovah, And deceptive scales are not good. 24 A man’s footsteps are directed by Jehovah; How can a man understand his own way?* 25 It is a snare for a man to cry out rashly, “Holy!” And only later to give consideration to what he vowed. 26 A wise king sifts out the wicked And drives the threshing wheel over them. 27 The breath of a man is the lamp of Jehovah, Searching through his innermost being. 28 Loyal love and faithfulness safeguard the king; By loyal love he sustains his throne. 29 The glory of young men is their strength, And the splendor of old men is their gray hair. 30 Bruises and wounds purge* away evil, And beatings cleanse one’s innermost being.

21 A king’s heart is like streams of water in Jehovah’s hand. He directs it wherever He pleases.  2 All of a man’s ways seem right to him, But Jehovah examines the hearts.*  3 To do what is right and just Is more pleasing to Jehovah than a sacrifice.  4 Haughty eyes and an arrogant heart —The lamp that guides the wicked is sin.  5 The plans of the diligent surely lead to success,* But all who are hasty surely head for poverty.  6 Gaining treasures by a lying tongue Is like a vanishing mist, a deadly snare.*  7 The violence of the wicked will sweep them away, For they refuse to act with justice.  8 The way of a guilty man is crooked, But the activity of the pure man is upright.  9 Better to dwell on a corner of the roof Than in the same house with a quarrelsome* wife. 10 The wicked man* craves what is bad; He shows no favor toward his neighbor. 11 When a ridiculer is punished, the inexperienced become wiser, And when a wise person receives insight, he gains knowledge.* 12 The Righteous One observes the house of the wicked one; He overthrows the wicked to their ruin. 13 Whoever stops up his ear to the cry of the lowly one Will himself call and not be answered. 14 A secret gift subdues anger, And a hidden bribe,* fierce rage. 15 It is a joy for the righteous one to act with justice, But it is something terrible to those who practice evil. 16 The man who strays from the way of insight Will rest in the company of those powerless in death. 17 The one who loves having a good time* will come to poverty; The one who loves wine and oil will not grow rich. 18 The wicked one is a ransom for the righteous one, And the treacherous one will be taken in place of the upright. 19 Better to dwell in the wilderness Than with a quarrelsome* and irritable wife. 20 Precious treasure and oil are found in the house of the wise, But the stupid man will squander* what he has. 21 Whoever pursues righteousness and loyal love Will find life, righteousness, and glory. 22 A wise man can scale* the city of the mighty And undermine the strength in which they trust. 23 The one guarding his mouth and his tongue Keeps himself* out of trouble. 24 A presumptuous, arrogant braggart is what you call The man who acts with reckless presumptuousness. 25 What the lazy man craves will put him to death, For his hands refuse to work. 26 All day long he greedily craves, But the righteous one gives, holding nothing back. 27 The sacrifice of the wicked is detestable. How much more when he offers it with evil intent!* 28 A lying witness will perish, But the man who listens will testify with success.* 29 The wicked man puts on a bold face, But it is the upright one whose course is sure.* 30 There is no wisdom, nor discernment, nor counsel in opposition to Jehovah. 31 The horse is prepared for the day of battle, But salvation belongs to Jehovah.

Or “quietness.”

Lit., “sacrifices.”

Or “Grandchildren.”

Or “parents.”

Or “children.”

Or “Fine.”

Or “noble.”

Or “is a stone that brings favor.”

Lit., “covers over.”

Or “like opening a dam.” Lit., “letting out waters.”

Or “When he is lacking good sense?”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “go surety.”

Lit., “good.”

Or “good for healing.”

Or “dries up the bones.”

Lit., “a bribe from the bosom.”

Lit., “bitterness.”

Or “impose a fine on.”

Lit., “cool of spirit.”

Or “shows contempt for.”

Or “soul.”

Or “like things to be swallowed greedily.”

Lit., “is raised high,” that is, out of reach, safe.

Or “complete despair?”

Or “searches him through.”

Lit., “separates.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “goodwill.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “hastens with his feet.”

Or “generous man.”

Lit., “acquires heart.”

Or “his soul.”

Lit., “good.”

Lit., “pass over.”

Or “a transgression.”

Or “a maned young lion.”

Or “nagging.”

Or “soul.”

Or “soul.”

Or “reward.”

Or “desire.” Lit., “raise your soul to.”

Or “purpose.”

Or “fearsomeness.”

Or “a maned young lion.”

Or possibly, “They will look during the harvest but find nothing.”

Or “intentions.” Lit., “counsel.”

Lit., “sons.”

Or “Two different stone weights and two different measuring containers.”

Or “boy.”

See Glossary.

Or “a foreigner.”

Or “counsel.”

Or “be made firm.”

Or “wise guidance.”

Or “who entices with his lips.”

Or “Two different stone weights.”

Or “the way to go?”

Or “scour.”

Or “motives.”

Or “advantage.”

Or possibly, “for those seeking death.”

Or “nagging.”

Or “The soul of the wicked one.”

Or “he knows what to do.”

Lit., “a bribe in the bosom.”

Or “loves pleasure.”

Or “nagging.”

Lit., “swallow.”

Or “prevail over.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “along with shameful conduct!”

Lit., “speak forever.”

Or “who makes his way sure.”

^ (Prov. 18:14-19:10) A person’s spirit can sustain him through illness, But who can bear a crushed spirit?* 15 The heart of the understanding one acquires knowledge, And the ear of the wise seeks to find knowledge. 16 A man’s gift opens the way for him; It gives him access to great people. 17 The first to state his case seems right, Until the other party comes and cross-examines him.* 18 Casting lots puts an end to disputes And decides between* strong opponents. 19 A brother offended is more unyielding than a fortified city, And there are disputes like the bars of a fortress. 20 From the fruitage of a man’s speech* his stomach will be filled; He will be satisfied with what his lips produce. 21 Death and life are in the power of the tongue; Those who love to use it will eat its fruitage. 22 The one who finds a good wife has found something good, And he receives Jehovah’s favor.* 23 The poor man implores when speaking, But the rich man answers harshly. 24 There are companions ready to crush one another, But there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.

19 It is better to be poor and walk in integrity Than to be stupid and speak lies.  2 A person* without knowledge is not good, And the one who acts rashly* is sinning.  3 It is a man’s own foolishness that distorts his way, And his heart becomes enraged against Jehovah.  4 Wealth attracts many friends, But the poor man will be deserted even by his friend.  5 A false witness will not go unpunished, And the one who lies with every breath will not escape.  6 Many seek the favor of a noble,* And everyone is a friend to the man who gives gifts.  7 All the brothers of a poor man hate him; How much more he is shunned by his friends! He pursues them with requests, but no one responds.  8 Whoever acquires good sense* loves himself.* Whoever treasures discernment will find success.*  9 A false witness will not go unpunished, And the one who lies with every breath will perish. 10 It is not fitting for a fool to live in luxury; How much less for a servant to rule over princes!

Or “complete despair?”

Or “searches him through.”

Lit., “separates.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “goodwill.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “hastens with his feet.”

Or “generous man.”

Lit., “acquires heart.”

Or “his soul.”

Lit., “good.”

^ ***sn song 76 Jehovah, God of Peace***

Song 76

Jehovah, God of Peace

(Philippians 4:9)

1. Jehovah, God of peace,

God of love that will not cease.

Grant us peaceful, calm conditions,

That good fruitage may increase.

Your counsel we have sought;

With your Son our lives were bought.

May you grant us now your own peace

That excels all human thought.

2. This world seeks peace in vain.

They have sown and reaped much pain.

But upon your favored people,

Peace descends like gentle rain.

As we discern your will

And our vows to you fulfill,

May you please now bless our efforts

And more peace in us instill.

3. Your spirit aids our sight

As your Word gives needed light.

We are guided and protected

In a world as dark as night.

May peace just like the dew

Calm our thoughts, refresh us too,

That our hearts and mental powers

Might be safe by means of you.

(See also [Ps. 4:8;] Phil. 4:6, 7; 1 Thess. 5:23.)

^ (Phil. 4:9) The things that you learned as well as accepted and heard and saw in connection with me, practice these, and the God of peace will be with you.

^ (Ps. 4:8) I will lie down and sleep in peace, For you alone, O Jehovah, make me dwell in security.

^ (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

^ (1 Thess. 5:23) May the God of peace himself sanctify you completely. And may the spirit and soul* and body of you brothers, sound in every respect, be preserved blameless at the presence of our Lord Jesus Christ.

Or “life.” See Glossary.

^ ***w14 12/1 pp. 12-13 “The Insight of a Man Certainly Slows Down His Anger”***

“The Insight of a Man Certainly Slows Down His Anger”

A college basketball coach is fired because of his uncontrolled anger.

A child throws a temper tantrum for not getting his way.

A mother gets into a shouting match with her son because of his messy room.

ALL of us have seen people get angry, and no doubt we ourselves have become irate at one time or another. While we may view anger as a negative emotion that should be suppressed, we often feel that we have a valid reason to be upset, especially when someone appears to overstep our sense of justice. An article by the American Psychological Association even suggests that “anger is a completely normal, usually healthy, human emotion.”

Such a view may seem plausible when we consider what the Christian apostle Paul wrote under divine inspiration. Acknowledging that there may be times when people become angry, he said: “Be wrathful, but do not sin; do not let the sun set while you are still angry.” (Ephesians 4:26) In view of this, should we vent our anger, or should we do what we can to control it?

SHOULD YOU GET ANGRY?

When Paul gave that counsel about anger, he apparently had in mind the words of the psalmist who wrote: “Be agitated, but do not sin.” ([Psalm 4:4]) What, though, was the intent of Paul’s inspired admonition? He went on to explain: “Put away from yourselves every kind of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath, screaming, and abusive speech, as well as everything injurious.” (Ephesians 4:31) Paul was in fact encouraging Christians to avoid giving vent to anger. Interestingly, the American Psychological Association article goes on to say: “Research has found that ‘letting it rip’ with anger actually escalates anger and aggression and does nothing to help you . . . resolve the situation.”

How, then, can we “put away” anger and all its bad effects? Wise King Solomon of ancient Israel wrote: “The insight of a man certainly slows down his anger, and it is beauty on his part to overlook an offense.” (Proverbs 19:11) How does “the insight of a man” help when rage wells up within him?

HOW INSIGHT SLOWS DOWN ANGER

Insight is the ability to see into a situation. To have insight means to see beyond the surface of a matter. How does that help when we are offended or provoked?

When we see an injustice, we may well become indignant. However, if we follow our emotions and react violently, we may end up hurting ourselves or someone else. Just as an uncontrolled fire can burn down a house, the flare of anger may destroy our reputation and our relationships with others, even with God. So when we feel anger welling up inside us, it is time to take a deeper look into the situation. Seeing a more complete picture of what is happening will surely help us to control our emotions.

Solomon’s father, King David, narrowly escaped incurring bloodguilt in connection with a man named Nabal, thanks to David’s being helped to see into the situation. David and his men protected Nabal’s sheep in the Judean wilderness. When the time came for shearing the flock, David asked Nabal for some provisions. At that, Nabal answered: “Do I have to take my bread and my water and the meat that I butchered for my shearers and give it to men who come from who knows where?” What an insult! When David heard those words, he, with some 400 men, set out to annihilate Nabal and his household.—1 Samuel 25:4-13.

Nabal’s wife, Abigail, learned about the incident and went out to see David. Upon meeting David and his men, she fell at his feet and said: “Let your servant girl speak to you, and listen to the words of your servant girl.” Then, she explained to David how senseless Nabal was and pointed out that David would regret taking revenge and shedding blood.—1 Samuel 25:24-31.

What insight did David gain from Abigail’s words that helped to defuse the tense situation? First, he saw that Nabal was a senseless man by nature, and second, David saw that he could incur bloodguilt if he avenged himself. Like David, you may be infuriated by something. What should you do? “Take a few moments to breathe deeply and count to 10,” suggests a Mayo Clinic article on anger management. Yes, stop and think what the cause of the problem is and what the consequences of your intended action might be. Let insight slow down your anger—even dispel it.—1 Samuel 25:32-35.

In a similar way, many today have been helped to control their anger. Sebastian explained how, as a 23-year-old inmate in a Polish prison, he learned to control his temper and strong emotions through a study of the Bible. “First, I think about the problem,” he said. “Then, I try to apply the Bible’s counsel. I found that the Bible is the best guidebook.”

Setsuo followed basically the same tactic. He said: “I used to shout at others when I was irritated by them at work. Now that I’ve studied the Bible, instead of shouting I ask myself: ‘Who is at fault anyway? Am I not the one causing the problem?’” Thinking about such questions slowed down his anger, and he was able to contain the strong feelings that welled up in his heart.

The emotion of anger may be very strong, but counsel from God’s Word is stronger still. By applying the Bible’s wise counsel and praying for God’s help, you too can let your insight slow down or control your anger.

^ (Eph. 4:26) Be wrathful, but do not sin; do not let the sun set while you are still angry;

^ (Ps. 4:4) Be agitated, but do not sin. Have your say in your heart, upon your bed, and keep silent. (Selah)

^ (Eph. 4:31) Put away from yourselves every kind of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath, screaming, and abusive speech, as well as everything injurious.

^ (Prov. 19:11) The insight of a man certainly slows down his anger, And it is beauty on his part to overlook* an offense.*

Lit., “pass over.”

Or “a transgression.”

^ (1 Sam. 25:4-13) David heard in the wilderness that Naʹbal was shearing his sheep. 5 So David sent ten young men to him, and David told the young men: “Go up to Carʹmel, and when you come to Naʹbal, ask him in my name about his welfare. 6 Then say, ‘May you live long and may you be well* and may your household be well and may all that you have be well. 7 Now I hear that you are doing your shearing. When your shepherds were with us, we did not harm them, and they found nothing missing the whole time they were in Carʹmel. 8 Ask your young men, and they will tell you. May my young men find favor in your eyes, because we have come at a joyous time.* Please give to your servants and to your son David whatever you can spare.’” 9 So David’s young men went and told all of this to Naʹbal in David’s name. When they finished, 10 Naʹbal answered David’s servants: “Who is David, and who is the son of Jesʹse? Nowadays many servants are breaking away from their masters. 11 Do I have to take my bread and my water and the meat that I butchered for my shearers and give it to men who come from who knows where?” 12 At that David’s young men returned and reported all these words to him. 13 David immediately said to his men: “Everyone strap on your sword!” So they all strapped on their swords, and David also strapped on his own sword, and about 400 men went up with David, while 200 men stayed with the baggage.

Or “may you have peace.”

Lit., “a good day.”

^ (1 Sam. 25:24-31) She then fell at his feet and said: “My lord, let the blame be on me; let your servant girl speak to you, and listen to the words of your servant girl. 25 Please, do not let my lord pay attention to this worthless Naʹbal, for he is just like his name. Naʹbal* is his name, and senselessness is with him. But I, your servant girl, did not see my lord’s young men whom you sent. 26 And now, my lord, as surely as Jehovah is living and as you are* living, it is Jehovah who has held you back from incurring bloodguilt and from taking revenge* with your own hand. May your enemies and those seeking injury to my lord become like Naʹbal. 27 Now let this gift* that your servant girl has brought to my lord be given to the young men who are following my lord. 28 Pardon, please, the transgression of your servant girl, for Jehovah will without fail make for my lord a lasting house, because my lord is fighting the wars of Jehovah, and no evil has been found in you all your days. 29 When someone rises up to pursue you and seeks your life,* the life* of my lord will be wrapped securely in the bag of life with Jehovah your God, but the lives* of your enemies he will hurl away like stones from a sling.* 30 And when Jehovah has done for my lord all the good things he has promised and he appoints you as leader over Israel, 31 you will have no remorse or regret* in your heart for shedding blood without cause and for letting the hand of my lord take revenge.* When Jehovah confers good upon my lord, remember your servant girl.”

Meaning “Senseless; Stupid.”

Or “your soul is.”

Or “bringing salvation.”

Lit., “blessing.”

Or “soul.”

Or “soul.”

Or “souls.”

Or “as from the hollow of a sling.”

Lit., “staggering or stumbling.”

Or “bring salvation.”

^ (1 Sam. 25:32-35) At this David said to Abʹi·gail: “Praise Jehovah the God of Israel, who sent you this day to meet me! 33 And blessed be your good sense! May you be blessed for restraining me this day from incurring bloodguilt and from taking revenge* with my own hands. 34 Otherwise, as surely as Jehovah the God of Israel who held me back from harming you is living, if you had not come quickly to meet me, by morning there would not have remained a single male* belonging to Naʹbal.” 35 With that David accepted from her what she had brought him and said to her: “Go up in peace to your house. See, I have listened to you, and I will grant your request.”

Or “bringing salvation.”

Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ ***w11 8/15 p. 30 Pursue Peace***

When Called Upon to Help

11. What care should an elder exercise if a Christian wants to talk to him about a dispute with a fellow believer?

11 What if a Christian wants to talk to an elder about a problem he or she is having with a relative or with a fellow believer? Proverbs 21:13 states: “Anyone stopping up his ear from the complaining cry of the lowly one, he himself also will call and not be answered.” An elder would certainly not ‘stop up his ear.’ However, another proverb warns: “The first to state his case seems right, until his opponent begins to cross-examine him.” ([Prov. 18:17], New English Translation) An elder should listen kindly, but he needs to be careful not to take sides with the one reporting the offense. After listening to the matter, he would likely ask whether the offended party has spoken to the one who caused the upset. The elder may also review Scriptural steps that the offended one can take to pursue peace.

12. Cite examples showing the danger of acting hastily after hearing a complaint.

12 Three Biblical examples underscore the danger of acting hastily after hearing only one side of a controversy. Potiphar believed his wife’s story that Joseph had tried to rape her. With unjustified anger, Potiphar had Joseph thrown into prison. (Gen. 39:19, 20) King David believed Ziba, who said that his master, Mephibosheth, had sided with David’s enemies. “Look! Yours is everything that belongs to Mephibosheth” was David’s hasty response. ([2 Sam. 16:4;][19:25-27]) King Artaxerxes was told that the Jews were rebuilding Jerusalem’s walls and were about to rebel against the Persian Empire. The king believed the false report and ordered that all rebuilding in Jerusalem cease. As a result, the Jews stopped work on God’s temple. (Ezra 4:11-13,[23, 24]) Christian elders wisely follow Paul’s counsel to Timothy to avoid making premature judgments.—Read 1 Timothy 5:21.

13, 14. (a) All of us have what limitations respecting the disputes of others? (b) What help do elders have in making correct judgments respecting fellow believers?

13 Even when it seems that both sides of a dispute have come to light, it is important to realize that “if anyone thinks he has acquired knowledge of something, he does not yet know it just as he ought to know it.” ([1 Cor. 8:2]) Do we really know all the details that led up to the dispute? Can we fully understand the backgrounds of the individuals involved? When called upon to judge, how vital it is that elders not let themselves be deceived by falsehood, clever tactics, or rumors! God’s appointed Judge, Jesus Christ, judges righteously. He does not “judge by any mere appearance to his eyes, nor reprove simply according to the thing heard by his ears.” ([Isa. 11:3, 4]) Rather, Jesus is guided by Jehovah’s spirit. Christian elders likewise have the benefit of being guided by God’s holy spirit.

14 Before they make judgments respecting fellow believers, elders need to pray for the help of Jehovah’s spirit and depend on its guidance by consulting God’s Word and the publications of the faithful and discreet slave class.—[Matt. 24:45].

^ par. 11 (Prov. 21:13) Whoever stops up his ear to the cry of the lowly one Will himself call and not be answered.

^ par. 11 (Prov. 18:17) The first to state his case seems right, Until the other party comes and cross-examines him.*

Or “searches him through.”

^ par. 12 (Gen. 39:19, 20) As soon as his master heard the words his wife spoke to him, saying: “These are the things your servant did to me,” his anger blazed. 20 So Joseph’s master took him and gave him over to the prison, the place where the prisoners of the king were kept under arrest, and he remained there in the prison.

^ par. 12 (2 Sam. 16:4) The king then said to Ziʹba: “Look! Everything that belongs to Me·phibʹo·sheth is yours.” Ziʹba replied: “I bow down before you. May I find favor in your eyes, my lord the king.”

^ par. 12 (2 Sam. 19:25-27) When he came to* Jerusalem to meet the king, the king said to him: “Why did you not go with me, Me·phibʹo·sheth?” 26 To this he said: “My lord the king, my servant tricked me. For your servant had said, ‘Let me get my donkey saddled so that I may ride on it and go with the king,’ for your servant is crippled. 27 But he slandered your servant to my lord the king. However, my lord the king is like an angel of the true God, so do whatever seems good to you.

Or possibly, “from.”

^ par. 12 (Ezra 4:11-13) this is a copy of the letter that they sent him.) “To King Ar·ta·xerxʹes from your servants, the men of the region Beyond the River: And now 12 let it be known to the king that the Jews who came up here from you to us have arrived at Jerusalem. They are rebuilding the rebellious and wicked city, and they are finishing the walls and repairing the foundations. 13 Now let it be known to the king that if this city should be rebuilt and its walls finished, they will not give tax, tribute, or toll, and it will result in a loss to the treasuries of the kings.

^ par. 12 (Ezra 4:23, 24) Now after the copy of the official document of King Ar·ta·xerxʹes had been read before Reʹhum and Shimʹshai the scribe and their colleagues, they quickly went to Jerusalem to the Jews and used force to stop them. 24 It was then that the work on the house of God, which was in Jerusalem, came to a halt; and it remained at a standstill until the second year of the reign of King Da·riʹus of Persia.

^ par. 12 (1 Tim. 5:21) I solemnly charge you before God and Christ Jesus and the chosen angels to observe these instructions without any prejudice or partiality.

^ par. 13 (1 Cor. 8:2) If anyone thinks he knows something, he does not yet know it as he should know it.

^ par. 13 (Isa. 11:3, 4) And he will find delight in the fear of Jehovah. He will not judge by what appears to his eyes, Nor reprove simply according to what his ears hear.  4 He will judge the lowly with fairness,* And with uprightness he will give reproof in behalf of the meek ones of the earth. He will strike the earth with the rod of his mouth And put the wicked to death with the breath* of his lips.

Or “righteousness.”

Or “spirit.”

^ par. 14 (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

Or “wise.”

^ ***w11 8/15 p. 31 Pursue Peace***

17. All Christians play what part in pursuing peace?

17 Most disputes between brothers do not involve serious wrongdoing that requires judicial action. How good it is, therefore, lovingly to cover over the mistakes of others. “The one covering over transgression is seeking love,” says God’s Word, “and he that keeps talking about a matter is separating those familiar with one another.” ([Prov. 17:9]) Complying with those words will help all of us to preserve peace in the congregation and maintain a good relationship with Jehovah.—Matt. 6:14, 15.

^ par. 17 (Prov. 17:9) Whoever forgives* a transgression seeks love, But the one who keeps harping on a matter separates close friends.

Lit., “covers over.”

^ par. 17 (Matt. 6:14, 15) “For if you forgive men their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you; 15 whereas if you do not forgive men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses.

^ ***w10 11/15 p. 6 Young Ones—Be Guided by God’s Word***

17. What questions could you ask yourself when choosing entertainment?

17 To remain loyal to God when you are by yourself, you must develop your “perceptive powers . . . to distinguish both right and wrong” and then train those powers “through use” by acting on what you know is right. ([Heb. 5:14]) For example, when choosing the music you listen to, the movies you watch, or the Internet sites that you visit, here is what will help you choose what is right and avoid what is wrong. Ask yourself the following questions: ‘Will this material encourage me to be tenderly compassionate or will it influence me to rejoice “at another’s disaster”?’ ([Prov. 17:5]) ‘Will it help me to “love what is good” or will it make it difficult for me to “hate what is bad”?’ ([Amos 5:15]) What you do when you are alone reveals the values you really treasure.—[Luke 6:45].

^ par. 17 (Heb. 5:14) But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their powers of discernment* trained to distinguish both right and wrong.

Or “their perceptive powers.”

^ par. 17 (Prov. 17:5) Whoever mocks the poor insults his Maker, And whoever rejoices over another’s disaster will not go unpunished.

^ par. 17 (Amos 5:15) Hate what is bad, and love what is good, Let justice prevail in the city gate. It may be that Jehovah the God of armies Will show favor to the remaining ones of Joseph.’

^ par. 17 (Luke 6:45) A good man brings good out of the good treasure of his heart, but a wicked man brings what is wicked out of his wicked treasure; for out of the heart’s abundance his mouth speaks.

^ ***w10 11/15 p. 31 We Shall Walk in Our Integrity!***

15. Why is it wrong to rejoice when calamity befalls someone hating us?

15 Upright Job never rejoiced if calamity befell someone hating him. A later proverb warns: “When your enemy falls, do not rejoice; and when he is caused to stumble, may your heart not be joyful, that Jehovah may not see and it be bad in his eyes and he certainly turn back his anger from against him.” (Prov. 24:17, 18) Since Jehovah can read the heart, he knows if we are secretly rejoicing over another person’s calamity and surely does not approve of such an attitude. ([Prov. 17:5]) God may deal with us accordingly, for he says: “Vengeance is mine, and retribution.”—[Deut. 32:35].

^ par. 15 (Prov. 24:17, 18) When your enemy falls, do not rejoice, And when he stumbles, do not let your heart be joyful; 18 Otherwise, Jehovah will see and be displeased, And He will turn away his anger from him.*

That is, the enemy.

^ par. 15 (Prov. 17:5) Whoever mocks the poor insults his Maker, And whoever rejoices over another’s disaster will not go unpunished.

^ par. 15 (Deut. 32:35) Vengeance is mine, and retribution, At the appointed time when their foot slips, For the day of their disaster is near, And what awaits them will come quickly.’

^ ***w09 5/15 pp. 15-16 Youths—Make Your Advancement Manifest***

Preparing for a Successful Marriage

12. Why should a Christian considering marriage apply the principle found at Proverbs 20:25?

12 Some young adults have rushed into marriage, believing that it is the solution to unhappiness, loneliness, boredom, and problems at home. However, the exchanging of marriage vows is a serious matter. Some in Bible times rashly made a sacred, or holy, vow without carefully analyzing what was involved. (Read Proverbs 20:25.) At times, young adults do not seriously consider the demands of marriage. Later, they find that much more is involved than they had realized.

13. What questions should those contemplating courtship consider, and what helpful advice is available to them?

13 So before pursuing a courtship, ask yourself: ‘Why do I want to get married? What expectations do I have? Is this the right person for me? What can I bring to a marriage?’ To help you make an insightful examination, “the faithful and discreet slave” has published very specific articles.* (Matt. 24:45-47) View such material as advice that Jehovah is giving you. Carefully evaluate what is stated there and apply it. Never allow yourself to become “like a horse or mule without understanding.” ([Ps. 32:8, 9]) Become full-grown in your understanding of the demands of marriage. If you feel that you are ready to pursue a courtship, always remember to be “an example . . . in chasteness.”—[1 Tim. 4:12].

^ (Prov. 20:25) It is a snare for a man to cry out rashly, “Holy!” And only later to give consideration to what he vowed.

^ par. 12 (Prov. 20:25) It is a snare for a man to cry out rashly, “Holy!” And only later to give consideration to what he vowed.

^ par. 13 (Matt. 24:45-47) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings.

Or “wise.”

^ par. 13 (Ps. 32:8, 9) “I will give you insight and instruct you in the way you should go. I will give you advice with my eye upon you.  9 Do not become like a horse or a mule, without understanding, Whose spiritedness must be controlled with a bridle or a halter Before it will come near to you.”

^ par. 13 (1 Tim. 4:12) Never let anyone look down on your youth. Instead, become an example to the faithful ones in speaking, in conduct, in love, in faith, in chasteness.*

Or “purity.”

^ par. 13 “Is This Person Right for Me?” in the book Questions Young People Ask—Answers That Work, Volume 2; “Divine Guidance for Selecting a Marriage Mate,” in The Watchtower of May 15, 2001; and “How Wise Is a Teenage Marriage?” in Awake! of September 22, 1983.

^ ***lv pp. 57-58 How to Keep Separate From the World***

14. In regard to our appearance and hygiene, what questions should we ask ourselves?

14 Our dress, grooming, and cleanliness are even more important when we are engaging in the field ministry or attending a Christian meeting. Ask yourself: ‘Do my appearance and personal hygiene draw undue attention to me? Do they embarrass others? Do I consider my rights in these areas to be more important than qualifying for service privileges in the congregation?’—[Psalm 68:6;] Philippians 4:5;[1 Peter 5:6].

15. Why does God’s Word not set out a list of rules on dress, grooming, and hygiene?

15 The Bible does not set out for Christians a list of rules on dress, grooming, and hygiene. Jehovah has no desire to deny us our freedom of choice or the use of our thinking faculties. Rather, he wants us to become mature people who reason on Bible principles and who “through use have their powers of discernment trained to distinguish both right and wrong.” ([Hebrews 5:14]) Above all, he wants us to be governed by love—love for God and neighbor. (Read Mark 12:30, 31.) Within those boundaries, there is the potential for great variety in dress and grooming. Evidence of this can be seen in the colorfully dressed, joyful throngs of Jehovah’s people no matter where on earth they are gathered.

^ par. 14 (Ps. 68:6) God gives those who are alone a home to dwell in; He leads prisoners out into prosperity. But the stubborn* must live in a parched land.

Or “rebellious.”

^ par. 14 (Phil. 4:5) Let your reasonableness become known to all men. The Lord is near.

^ par. 14 (1 Pet. 5:6) Humble yourselves, therefore, under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you in due time,

^ par. 15 (Heb. 5:14) But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their powers of discernment* trained to distinguish both right and wrong.

Or “their perceptive powers.”

^ par. 15 (Mark 12:30, 31) and you must love Jehovah* your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul* and with your whole mind and with your whole strength.’ 31 The second is this, ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’ There is no other commandment greater than these.”

See App. A5.

See Glossary.

^ ***sn song 77 Be Forgiving***

Song 77

Be Forgiving

([Psalm 86:5])

1. Lovingly Jehovah

Made provision through his Son

For our sins to be forgiven

And for death to be undone.

If we truly are repentant,

His forgiveness we can claim

On the basis of Christ’s ransom,

Asking pardon in his name.

2. We receive such mercy

When we act like God above

And forgive each other freely,

Showing empathy and love.

Putting up with one another,

Putting hurtfulness away;

Showing honor to our brother,

Showing love’s surpassing way.

3. Mercy is a virtue

That we all should cultivate.

It will keep us from resentment,

From the bitterness of hate.

When we imitate Jehovah,

Who is unsurpassed in love,

We will truly be forgiving;

We will be like God above.

(See also [Matt. 6:12;][Eph. 4:32;][Col. 3:13].)

^ (Ps. 86:5) For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive; You abound in loyal love for all those who call on you.

^ (Matt. 6:12) and forgive us our debts, as we also have forgiven our debtors.

^ (Eph. 4:32) But become kind to one another, tenderly compassionate, freely forgiving one another just as God also by Christ freely forgave you.

^ (Col. 3:13) Continue putting up with one another and forgiving one another freely even if anyone has a cause for complaint against another. Just as Jehovah* freely forgave you, you must also do the same.

See App. A5.

^ ***kr pp. 23-25 The Kingdom Is Born in Heaven***

A Time of Revival!

35. Why did Jesus allow hardships to afflict his followers, and what action did he take to help them?

35 Little did the enemies of the truth know that Jesus allowed these hardships to afflict his people only because Jehovah was then sitting “as a refiner and cleanser of silver.” ([Mal. 3:3]) Jehovah and his Son were sure that the faithful ones would emerge from those fiery tests refined, purified, and better suited than ever for service to the King. From early in 1919, it became clear that God’s spirit had done what the enemies of his people thought impossible. The faithful ones were revived! ([Rev. 11:11]) At that time, Christ evidently fulfilled a key feature of the sign of the last days. He appointed “the faithful and discreet slave,” a small group of anointed men who would take the lead among his people by dispensing spiritual food at the proper time.—Matt. 24:45-47.

36. What showed that God’s people were reviving spiritually?

36 Brother Rutherford and his associates were released from prison on March 26, 1919. A convention was soon scheduled for that September. Plans got under way to start up a second journal, to be called The Golden Age. A companion to The Watch Tower, it was designed for use in the field ministry.* The same year saw the publication of the first issue of the Bulletin, which is now the meeting workbook for Our Christian Life and Ministry. From the start, it has always been a stimulus to the field ministry. Without a doubt, from 1919 onward the personal, house-to-house ministry came increasingly to the fore.

37. In the years after 1919, how did some prove disloyal?

37 The preaching work continued to refine Christ’s servants, for the proud and arrogant among them had no stomach for such humble work. Those who would not get in step with the work parted company with the faithful ones. In the years following 1919, some disloyal ones were embittered and resorted to slander and libel, even siding with the persecutors of Jehovah’s faithful servants.

38. What do the successes and victories of Christ’s followers on earth furnish for us?

38 Despite such attacks, though, Christ’s followers on earth continued to thrive and to prosper spiritually. Their every success, their every victory since then, furnishes us with convincing proof that God’s Kingdom rules! Only by God’s active support and blessing—which he provides through his Son and the Messianic Kingdom—could a group of mere imperfect humans win victory after victory over Satan and this wicked system of things!—Read Isaiah 54:17.

39, 40. (a) What are some of the features of this publication? (b) What can studying this book do for you?

39 In the chapters that follow, we will examine what God’s Kingdom has accomplished on earth in the century since it was born in heaven. Each section of this book will cover a distinct aspect of the Kingdom work here on earth. In each chapter, a review box will help us individually to determine just how real the Kingdom is to us. In the concluding chapters, we will discuss what to expect when the Kingdom comes in the near future to destroy the wicked and usher in a paradise earth. What will studying this publication do for you?

40 Satan wants to erode your faith in God’s Kingdom. But Jehovah wants to strengthen your faith so that it will protect you and keep you strong. ([Eph. 6:16]) Therefore, we urge you to study this publication prayerfully. Keep asking yourself, ‘Is God’s Kingdom real to me?’ The more real it is to you now, the more likely it is that you will be on hand, faithfully and actively supporting that Kingdom, on the day when everyone alive will see that God’s Kingdom is real and that it is ruling!

^ par. 35 (Mal. 3:3) And he will sit as a refiner and cleanser of silver and will cleanse the sons of Leʹvi; and he will clarify* them like gold and like silver, and they will certainly become to Jehovah people presenting a gift offering in righteousness.

Or “refine.”

^ par. 35 (Rev. 11:11) After the three and a half days, spirit of life from God entered into them, and they stood on their feet, and great fear fell upon those who saw them.

^ par. 35 (Matt. 24:45-47) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings.

Or “wise.”

^ par. 38 (Isa. 54:17) No weapon formed against you will have any success, And you will condemn any tongue that rises up against you in the judgment. This is the heritage* of the servants of Jehovah, And their righteousness is from me,” declares Jehovah.

Or “inheritance.”

^ par. 40 (Eph. 6:16) Besides all of this, take up the large shield of faith, with which you will be able to extinguish all the wicked one’s burning arrows.*

Or “missiles; darts.”

^ par. 36 For many years The Watch Tower was intended mainly for members of the little flock for their personal edification.

^ ***kr chap. 2 The Kingdom Is Born in Heaven***

How Real Is the Kingdom to You?

Who helped to prepare Jesus’ true followers for the birth of the Kingdom?

In what ways were true Christians prepared for the rule of God’s Kingdom?

What features mark the Kingdom as a real government? (See the box “God’s Kingdom—A Real Government.”)

How can you imitate Christ’s faithful followers of a century ago as you support the Kingdom today?

^ ***kr pp. 26-27 The Kingdom Is Born in Heaven***

GOD’S KINGDOM—A REAL GOVERNMENT

Is God’s Kingdom a real government? Consider just a few of the features of God’s Kingdom. Ask yourself, ‘Does not each feature show that the Kingdom is just as real as—and far superior to—any human government on earth today?’

A RULER

Enthroned in 1914, Jesus Christ is a powerful, just, wise, and merciful King who is humble before Jehovah God. ([Isa. 9:6, 7;][11:1-3]) Unlike imperfect human rulers, he cannot be corrupted, nor is he hampered by fractious congresses and parliaments or self-seeking lobbyists and special-interest groups.

LEGISLATIVE AND JUDICIAL POWERS

Jesus’ life and example while on earth form the basis for a perfect law, “the law of the Christ.”—[Gal. 6:2;][1 Pet. 2:21].

Jehovah has entrusted all judging to his Son, and Jesus carries out that assignment perfectly, as no human judge ever could.—[John 5:22].

A BODY OF ADMINISTRATORS

Jesus has 144,000 corulers who will share in administering his just reign over the earth. A key objective of his rule is to reconcile humans to God, so his corulers will also serve as priests for that purpose.—[Rev. 14:1;][20:6].

AN ARMY

As Leader of Jehovah’s vast army of mighty angels, Jesus commands the most powerful military force ever to exist. It will soon wage war on all wickedness.—[Ps. 45:1,][3-5;][Rev. 19:11,][14-16].

A SEAT OF GOVERNMENT

Jesus’ throne is in heaven, at the side of his Father. Heaven is Jehovah’s “lofty abode of holiness and glory.” ([Isa. 63:15]) Is it a real place? Yes, more so than any capital city or government building you can see, for heavenly things do not decay.—[Matt. 6:20].

A TERRITORY ON EARTH

Today, Jesus’ subjects are like foreigners who live as law-abiding citizens in every land and nation. But Jehovah has provided a spiritual land for them, a realm of activity in which they carry out the King’s will. ([Isa. 60:2;][66:8]) Soon, Jesus’ Kingdom will claim the entire earth as its physical territory.—[Ps. 72:8].

GOVERNMENT PROGRAMS

God’s Kingdom will soon fulfill God’s promises to provide all these blessings and more.—[Ps. 72:16;][Isa. 2:3;][33:24;][35:6;][65:21].

HEALTH

HOUSING

EMPLOYMENT

NOURISHMENT

EDUCATION

A POPULATION OF LOYAL SUBJECTS

“A ruler without subjects is ruined,” explains the Bible, whereas “a multitude of people are a king’s majesty.” ([Prov. 14:28]) The Kingdom’s population of loyal subjects has surged in number to well over seven and a half million.—[Ps. 72:8;][Isa. 60:22].

^ (Isa. 9:6, 7) For a child has been born to us, A son has been given to us; And the rulership* will rest on his shoulder. His name will be called Wonderful Counselor, Mighty God, Eternal Father, Prince of Peace.  7 To the increase of his rulership* And to peace, there will be no end, On the throne of David and on his kingdom In order to establish it firmly and to sustain it Through justice and righteousness, From now on and forever. The zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.

Or “government; princely rule.”

Or “government; princely rule.”

^ (Isa. 11:1-3) A twig will grow out of the stump of Jesʹse, And a sprout from his roots will bear fruit.  2 And the spirit of Jehovah will settle upon him, The spirit of wisdom and of understanding, The spirit of counsel and of mightiness, The spirit of knowledge and of the fear of Jehovah.  3 And he will find delight in the fear of Jehovah. He will not judge by what appears to his eyes, Nor reprove simply according to what his ears hear.

^ (Gal. 6:2) Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and in this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.

^ (1 Pet. 2:21) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

^ (John 5:22) For the Father judges no one at all, but he has entrusted all the judging to the Son,

^ (Rev. 14:1) Then I saw, and look! the Lamb standing on Mount Zion, and with him 144,000 who have his name and the name of his Father written on their foreheads.

^ (Rev. 20:6) Happy and holy is anyone having part in the first resurrection; over these the second death has no authority, but they will be priests of God and of the Christ, and they will rule as kings with him for the 1,000 years.

^ (Ps. 45:1) My heart is stirred by something good. I say: “My song is* about a king.” May my tongue be the stylus* of a skilled copyist.*

Lit., “My works are.”

Or “pen.”

Or “scribe.”

^ (Ps. 45:3-5) Strap your sword on your side, O mighty one, In your dignity and your splendor.  4 And in your splendor go on to victory;* Ride in the cause of truth and humility and righteousness, And your right hand will accomplish* awe-inspiring things.  5 Your arrows are sharp, making peoples fall before you; They pierce the hearts of the king’s enemies.

Or “success.”

Lit., “teach you.”

^ (Rev. 19:11) I saw heaven opened, and look! a white horse. And the one seated on it is called Faithful and True, and he judges and carries on war in righteousness.

^ (Rev. 19:14-16) Also, the armies in heaven were following him on white horses, and they were clothed in white, clean, fine linen. 15 And out of his mouth protrudes a sharp, long sword with which to strike the nations, and he will shepherd them with a rod of iron. Moreover, he treads the winepress of the fury of the wrath of God the Almighty. 16 On his outer garment, yes, on his thigh, he has a name written, King of kings and Lord of lords.

^ (Isa. 63:15) Look down from heaven and see From your lofty abode of holiness and glory.* Where are your zeal and your mightiness, The stirring of your compassions* and your mercy? They are withheld from me.

Or “beauty.”

Lit., “The agitation of your inward parts.”

^ (Matt. 6:20) Rather, store up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust consumes, and where thieves do not break in and steal.

^ (Isa. 60:2) For look! darkness will cover the earth And thick gloom the nations; But on you Jehovah will shine, And on you his glory will be seen.

^ (Isa. 66:8) Who has ever heard of such a thing? Who has seen such things? Will a land be brought to birth in one day? Or will a nation be born all at once? Yet, as soon as Zion went into labor, she gave birth to her sons.

^ (Ps. 72:8) He will have subjects* from sea to sea And from the River* to the ends of the earth.

Or “will rule.”

That is, the Euphrates.

^ (Ps. 72:16) There will be an abundance of grain on the earth; On the top of the mountains it will overflow. His fruit will flourish as in Lebʹa·non, And in the cities people will blossom like the vegetation of the earth.

^ (Isa. 2:3) And many peoples will go and say: “Come, let us go up to the mountain of Jehovah, To the house of the God of Jacob. He will instruct us about his ways, And we will walk in his paths.” For law* will go out of Zion, And the word of Jehovah out of Jerusalem.

Or “instruction.”

^ (Isa. 33:24) And no resident* will say: “I am sick.” The people dwelling in the land will be pardoned for their error.

Or “inhabitant.”

^ (Isa. 35:6) At that time the lame will leap like the deer, And the tongue of the speechless will shout for joy. For waters will burst forth in the wilderness, And streams in the desert plain.

^ (Isa. 65:21) They will build houses and live in them, And they will plant vineyards and eat their fruitage.

^ (Prov. 14:28) A multitude of people are a king’s majesty, But a ruler without subjects is ruined.

^ (Ps. 72:8) He will have subjects* from sea to sea And from the River* to the ends of the earth.

Or “will rule.”

That is, the Euphrates.

^ (Isa. 60:22) The little one will become a thousand And the small one a mighty nation. I myself, Jehovah, will speed it up in its own time.”

^ ***kr pp. 28-29 The Kingdom Is Born in Heaven***

PREPARED FOR THE BIRTH OF THE KINGDOM

Consider some historical events from the decades leading up to 1914. Can you see how these developments helped God’s people to be prepared for the birth of the Messianic Kingdom?

Mid-1800’s

Henry Grew, George Stetson, and George Storrs scrutinize and expose the falseness of the doctrine of the immortality of the human soul

1868 or 1869

Charles T. Russell begins a careful examination of the doctrines of Christendom’s churches and finds misinterpretations of the Scriptures; Russell’s “wavering faith” is reestablished after he hears a sermon by Adventist preacher Jonas Wendell

1870

Brother Russell forms a Bible study group; they begin a systematic study of the Bible

1870-1875

Truths regarding the soul, the ransom, and the manner of Christ’s return become clearer

1876

An article by C. T. Russell, published in the Bible Examiner, points to 1914 as the end of the Gentile Times

1877

The Object and Manner of Our Lord’s Return is published to clarify truths regarding Christ’s presence

1879

The first issue of Zion’s Watch Tower and Herald of Christ’s Presence is published

Babylon the Great is recognized as being associated with the nominal churches of Christendom

1880

Brother Russell tours the northeastern United States to visit and strengthen study groups

1881

Multipage tracts (some over 100 pages long) are published and provided to Watch Tower readers for free public distribution

The Watch Tower invites all readers to commemorate the Memorial in Allegheny, Pennsylvania

Colporteur work begins

Articles such as “Wanted 1,000 Preachers” and “Anointed to Preach” promote the ministry

Christians who are not yet doing so are encouraged to begin holding meetings regularly

1882

An article refuting the Trinity doctrine is published

1885

Watch Tower publications reach readers on five continents

1886

The Divine Plan of the Ages is released, the first volume of the series of books later known as Studies in the Scriptures

The Watch Tower invites readers to a three-day “general meeting” to follow the Memorial of Christ’s death, thus beginning the practice of holding annual conventions

1889

The Bible House is built in Allegheny, Pennsylvania

1890

The Watch Tower Society publishes Rotherham’s New Testament, using a secular printing company

1891

C. T. Russell begins extensive tours outside the United States, seeking ways of “forwarding the spread of the Truth”

1894

Tower Tract Society representatives, acting as traveling overseers, are sent out to visit and encourage congregations

1895

The Watch Tower notes that some faithful ones are holding “Dawn Circles” for Bible study and recommends “the holding of these Circles everywhere”

1896

C. T. Russell publishes the booklet What Say the Scriptures About Hell?

1900

First branch office established in London, England

Preaching work reaches 28 countries

1903

Distribution of free tracts on Sundays, which had taken place on streets near churches, shifts to intense house-to-house campaigns

Russell’s sermons begin to appear regularly in newspapers

1909

The headquarters of the Watch Tower Society moves to Brooklyn, New York

1910

The Bible Students begin to use the name International Bible Students Association

1911-1912

C. T. Russell and six companions travel some 35,000 miles (56,000 km) on a round-the-world tour to investigate the “status and prospects of Christianity” in various lands, including China, India, Japan, and the Philippines

1914

The “Photo-Drama of Creation” is first shown in New York on January 11, then in five other cities within the next month. By the end of the year, it is seen in various forms by close to 9,000,000 people in North America, Europe, Australia, and New Zealand

In October, C. T. Russell announces to the Bethel family: “The Gentile times have ended; their kings have had their day.” According to a sister in attendance, he added: “So we know not what awaits us”

^ ***snnw song 144 It Means Their Life***

Song 144

It Means Their Life

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

(Ezekiel 3:17-19)

In this year of goodwill

by our God, all need to hear

That the day of his anger

will come, and it is near.

(CHORUS)

It means their life, but not just theirs;

It means our own life as well.

It means their life if they obey,

So all the nations we must tell;

We must tell.

There’s a message to preach,

so we spread it all abroad.

We invite all to come and

be reconciled to God.

(CHORUS)

It means their life, but not just theirs;

It means our own life as well.

It means their life if they obey,

So all the nations we must tell;

We must tell.

(BRIDGE)

It’s urgent, it’s important,

That people listen, learn, and live.

We tell them, and we teach them;

Life-giving truth we freely give.

(CHORUS)

It means their life, but not just theirs;

It means our own life as well.

It means their life if they obey,

So all the nations we must tell;

We must tell.

(See also 2 Chron. 36:15;[Isa. 61:2;][Ezek. 33:6;] 2 Thess. 1:8.)

^ (Ezek. 3:17-19) “Son of man, I have appointed you as a watchman to the house of Israel; and when you hear a word from my mouth, you must warn them from me. 18 When I say to someone wicked, ‘You will surely die,’ but you do not warn him, and you fail to speak in order to warn the wicked one to turn from his wicked course so that he may stay alive, he will die for his error because he is wicked, but I will ask his blood back from you.* 19 But if you warn someone wicked and he does not turn back from his wickedness and from his wicked course, he will die for his error, but you will certainly save your own life.*

Or “I will hold you accountable for his blood.”

Or “soul.”

^ (2 Chron. 36:15) Jehovah the God of their forefathers kept warning them by means of his messengers, warning them again and again, because he felt compassion for his people and for his dwelling place.

^ (Isa. 61:2) To proclaim the year of Jehovah’s goodwill* And the day of vengeance of our God, To comfort all who mourn,

Or “favor.”

^ (Ezek. 33:6) “‘But if the watchman sees the sword coming and he does not blow the horn and the people receive no warning and a sword comes and takes the life* of one of them, that person will die for his own error, but I will ask his blood back from the watchman.’*

Or “soul.”

Or “I will hold the watchman accountable for his blood.”

^ (2 Thess. 1:8) in a flaming fire, as he brings vengeance on those who do not know God and those who do not obey the good news about our Lord Jesus.

^ (Prov. 17:1-21:31) Better is a piece of dry bread where there is peace* Than a house full of feasting* along with quarreling.  2 A servant with insight will rule over a son who acts shamefully; He will share in the inheritance as one of the brothers.  3 The refining pot is for silver and the furnace for gold, But Jehovah is the examiner of hearts.  4 A wicked man pays attention to hurtful speech, And a deceptive man listens to a malicious tongue.  5 Whoever mocks the poor insults his Maker, And whoever rejoices over another’s disaster will not go unpunished.  6 Grandsons* are a crown to the aged, And fathers* are the glory of their sons.*  7 Upright* speech does not befit a fool. How much less does false speech befit a ruler!*  8 A gift is like a precious stone* to its owner; Everywhere he turns, it brings him success.  9 Whoever forgives* a transgression seeks love, But the one who keeps harping on a matter separates close friends. 10 A rebuke makes a deeper impression on one having understanding Than striking a stupid person a hundred times. 11 A bad man seeks only rebellion, But a cruel messenger will be sent to punish him. 12 Better to meet a bear bereaved of her cubs Than to encounter someone stupid in his foolishness. 13 If anyone repays bad for good, Bad will not depart from his house. 14 Beginning a fight is like opening a floodgate;* Before the quarrel breaks out, take your leave. 15 Anyone who acquits the wicked one and anyone who condemns the righteous one —Both of them are detestable to Jehovah. 16 What good is it that the stupid one has the means to acquire wisdom When he has no heart for acquiring it?* 17 A true friend shows love at all times, And is a brother who is born for times of distress. 18 A man lacking good sense* shakes hands and agrees To put up security* in the presence of his neighbor. 19 The one who loves conflict loves transgression. Anyone who makes his entryway high invites a crash. 20 The one who is crooked at heart will not find success,* And the one who speaks deceitfully will fall into ruin. 21 The one who fathers a stupid child will experience grief; And the father of a senseless child has no joy. 22 A joyful heart is good medicine,* But a crushed spirit saps one’s strength.* 23 A wicked man will take a bribe in secret* To pervert the course of justice. 24 Wisdom is directly in front of the discerning person, But the eyes of the stupid wander to the ends of the earth. 25 A stupid son brings grief to his father And heartache* to the one who gave birth to him. 26 To punish* the righteous one is not good, And to flog honorable people goes against what is right. 27 A man of knowledge restrains his words, And a discerning man will remain calm.* 28 Even a fool who keeps silent will be considered wise, And the one who seals his lips, discerning.

18 Whoever isolates himself pursues his own selfish desires; He rejects* all practical wisdom.  2 A stupid person takes no pleasure in understanding; He would rather disclose what is in his heart.  3 When a wicked person comes, contempt also comes, And along with dishonor there is disgrace.  4 The words of a man’s mouth are deep waters. The fountain of wisdom is a bubbling brook.  5 It is not good to show partiality to the wicked one Or to deprive the righteous one of justice.  6 The speech of the stupid one leads to quarrels, And his mouth invites a beating.  7 The mouth of the stupid is his ruin, And his lips are a snare for his life.*  8 The words of a slanderer are like tasty morsels;* They are gulped right down into the stomach.  9 Whoever is lazy in his work Is a brother to the one who causes ruin. 10 The name of Jehovah is a strong tower. Into it the righteous one runs and receives protection.* 11 The wealth of the rich is his fortified city; It is like a protective wall in his imagination. 12 Before a crash a man’s heart is lofty, And before glory there is humility. 13 When anyone replies to a matter before he hears the facts, It is foolish and humiliating. 14 A person’s spirit can sustain him through illness, But who can bear a crushed spirit?* 15 The heart of the understanding one acquires knowledge, And the ear of the wise seeks to find knowledge. 16 A man’s gift opens the way for him; It gives him access to great people. 17 The first to state his case seems right, Until the other party comes and cross-examines him.* 18 Casting lots puts an end to disputes And decides between* strong opponents. 19 A brother offended is more unyielding than a fortified city, And there are disputes like the bars of a fortress. 20 From the fruitage of a man’s speech* his stomach will be filled; He will be satisfied with what his lips produce. 21 Death and life are in the power of the tongue; Those who love to use it will eat its fruitage. 22 The one who finds a good wife has found something good, And he receives Jehovah’s favor.* 23 The poor man implores when speaking, But the rich man answers harshly. 24 There are companions ready to crush one another, But there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.

19 It is better to be poor and walk in integrity Than to be stupid and speak lies.  2 A person* without knowledge is not good, And the one who acts rashly* is sinning.  3 It is a man’s own foolishness that distorts his way, And his heart becomes enraged against Jehovah.  4 Wealth attracts many friends, But the poor man will be deserted even by his friend.  5 A false witness will not go unpunished, And the one who lies with every breath will not escape.  6 Many seek the favor of a noble,* And everyone is a friend to the man who gives gifts.  7 All the brothers of a poor man hate him; How much more he is shunned by his friends! He pursues them with requests, but no one responds.  8 Whoever acquires good sense* loves himself.* Whoever treasures discernment will find success.*  9 A false witness will not go unpunished, And the one who lies with every breath will perish. 10 It is not fitting for a fool to live in luxury; How much less for a servant to rule over princes! 11 The insight of a man certainly slows down his anger, And it is beauty on his part to overlook* an offense.* 12 The king’s rage is like the growling of a lion,* But his favor is like dew on the vegetation. 13 A stupid son brings adversity on his father, And a quarrelsome* wife is like a roof that never stops leaking. 14 A house and wealth are inherited from fathers, But a discreet wife is from Jehovah. 15 Laziness brings on a deep sleep, And a sluggish person* will go hungry. 16 The one who keeps the commandment keeps his life;* The one who is reckless about his ways will die. 17 The one showing favor to the lowly is lending to Jehovah, And He will repay* him for what he does. 18 Discipline your son while there is hope, And do not become responsible for* his death. 19 The hot-tempered man will pay the penalty; If you try to spare him, you will have to do it again and again. 20 Listen to counsel and accept discipline, In order to become wise in your future. 21 Many are the plans in a man’s heart, But the counsel* of Jehovah is what will prevail. 22 The desirable thing in a man is his loyal love; And it is better to be poor than to be a liar. 23 The fear of Jehovah leads to life; The one who has it will have a pleasant rest, free from harm. 24 The lazy one buries his hand in the banquet bowl, But he does not even bother to bring it back to his mouth. 25 Strike the ridiculer, so that the inexperienced one may become shrewd, And reprove the understanding one, so that he will increase in knowledge. 26 The one who mistreats his father and drives away his mother Is a son causing shame and disgrace. 27 My son, if you stop listening to discipline, You will stray from the sayings of knowledge. 28 A worthless witness mocks justice, And the mouth of the wicked gulps down evil. 29 Judgment is in store for ridiculers, And beatings for the back of the stupid ones.

20 Wine is a ridiculer, alcohol is unruly; Whoever goes astray by them is not wise.  2 The terror* of a king is like the growling of a lion;* Whoever provokes his anger risks his own life.  3 It is honorable for a man to refrain from a dispute, But every fool will become embroiled in it.  4 The lazy one does not plow in winter, So he will be begging during the harvest when he has nothing.*  5 The thoughts* of a man’s heart are like deep waters, But the discerning man draws them out.  6 Many men proclaim their loyal love, But who can find a faithful man?  7 The righteous one is walking in his integrity. Happy are his children* who come after him.  8 When the king sits on the throne to judge, He sifts out all evil with his eyes.  9 Who can say: “I have cleansed my heart; I am pure from my sin”? 10 Dishonest weights and false measures* —Both are detestable to Jehovah. 11 Even a child* is known by his actions, Whether his behavior is pure and right. 12 The hearing ear and the seeing eye —Jehovah has made both of them. 13 Do not love sleep, or you will come to poverty. Open your eyes, and you will be satisfied with bread. 14 “It is no good, it is no good!” says the buyer; Then he goes away and boasts about himself. 15 There is gold, also much coral,* But the lips of knowledge are something precious. 16 Take a man’s garment if he has given security for a stranger; Seize the pledge from him if he did so for a foreign woman.* 17 Bread gained by deceit tastes good to a man, But afterward his mouth will be full of gravel. 18 By consultation,* plans will succeed,* And by skillful direction* wage your war. 19 A slanderer goes about revealing confidential talk; Do not associate with one who loves to gossip.* 20 Whoever curses his father and his mother, His lamp will be extinguished when darkness comes. 21 An inheritance obtained first by greed Will not be a blessing in the end. 22 Do not say: “I will pay back evil!” Hope in Jehovah, and he will save you. 23 Dishonest weights* are detestable to Jehovah, And deceptive scales are not good. 24 A man’s footsteps are directed by Jehovah; How can a man understand his own way?* 25 It is a snare for a man to cry out rashly, “Holy!” And only later to give consideration to what he vowed. 26 A wise king sifts out the wicked And drives the threshing wheel over them. 27 The breath of a man is the lamp of Jehovah, Searching through his innermost being. 28 Loyal love and faithfulness safeguard the king; By loyal love he sustains his throne. 29 The glory of young men is their strength, And the splendor of old men is their gray hair. 30 Bruises and wounds purge* away evil, And beatings cleanse one’s innermost being.

21 A king’s heart is like streams of water in Jehovah’s hand. He directs it wherever He pleases.  2 All of a man’s ways seem right to him, But Jehovah examines the hearts.*  3 To do what is right and just Is more pleasing to Jehovah than a sacrifice.  4 Haughty eyes and an arrogant heart —The lamp that guides the wicked is sin.  5 The plans of the diligent surely lead to success,* But all who are hasty surely head for poverty.  6 Gaining treasures by a lying tongue Is like a vanishing mist, a deadly snare.*  7 The violence of the wicked will sweep them away, For they refuse to act with justice.  8 The way of a guilty man is crooked, But the activity of the pure man is upright.  9 Better to dwell on a corner of the roof Than in the same house with a quarrelsome* wife. 10 The wicked man* craves what is bad; He shows no favor toward his neighbor. 11 When a ridiculer is punished, the inexperienced become wiser, And when a wise person receives insight, he gains knowledge.* 12 The Righteous One observes the house of the wicked one; He overthrows the wicked to their ruin. 13 Whoever stops up his ear to the cry of the lowly one Will himself call and not be answered. 14 A secret gift subdues anger, And a hidden bribe,* fierce rage. 15 It is a joy for the righteous one to act with justice, But it is something terrible to those who practice evil. 16 The man who strays from the way of insight Will rest in the company of those powerless in death. 17 The one who loves having a good time* will come to poverty; The one who loves wine and oil will not grow rich. 18 The wicked one is a ransom for the righteous one, And the treacherous one will be taken in place of the upright. 19 Better to dwell in the wilderness Than with a quarrelsome* and irritable wife. 20 Precious treasure and oil are found in the house of the wise, But the stupid man will squander* what he has. 21 Whoever pursues righteousness and loyal love Will find life, righteousness, and glory. 22 A wise man can scale* the city of the mighty And undermine the strength in which they trust. 23 The one guarding his mouth and his tongue Keeps himself* out of trouble. 24 A presumptuous, arrogant braggart is what you call The man who acts with reckless presumptuousness. 25 What the lazy man craves will put him to death, For his hands refuse to work. 26 All day long he greedily craves, But the righteous one gives, holding nothing back. 27 The sacrifice of the wicked is detestable. How much more when he offers it with evil intent!* 28 A lying witness will perish, But the man who listens will testify with success.* 29 The wicked man puts on a bold face, But it is the upright one whose course is sure.* 30 There is no wisdom, nor discernment, nor counsel in opposition to Jehovah. 31 The horse is prepared for the day of battle, But salvation belongs to Jehovah.

Or “quietness.”

Lit., “sacrifices.”

Or “Grandchildren.”

Or “parents.”

Or “children.”

Or “Fine.”

Or “noble.”

Or “is a stone that brings favor.”

Lit., “covers over.”

Or “like opening a dam.” Lit., “letting out waters.”

Or “When he is lacking good sense?”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “go surety.”

Lit., “good.”

Or “good for healing.”

Or “dries up the bones.”

Lit., “a bribe from the bosom.”

Lit., “bitterness.”

Or “impose a fine on.”

Lit., “cool of spirit.”

Or “shows contempt for.”

Or “soul.”

Or “like things to be swallowed greedily.”

Lit., “is raised high,” that is, out of reach, safe.

Or “complete despair?”

Or “searches him through.”

Lit., “separates.”

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “goodwill.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “hastens with his feet.”

Or “generous man.”

Lit., “acquires heart.”

Or “his soul.”

Lit., “good.”

Lit., “pass over.”

Or “a transgression.”

Or “a maned young lion.”

Or “nagging.”

Or “soul.”

Or “soul.”

Or “reward.”

Or “desire.” Lit., “raise your soul to.”

Or “purpose.”

Or “fearsomeness.”

Or “a maned young lion.”

Or possibly, “They will look during the harvest but find nothing.”

Or “intentions.” Lit., “counsel.”

Lit., “sons.”

Or “Two different stone weights and two different measuring containers.”

Or “boy.”

See Glossary.

Or “a foreigner.”

Or “counsel.”

Or “be made firm.”

Or “wise guidance.”

Or “who entices with his lips.”

Or “Two different stone weights.”

Or “the way to go?”

Or “scour.”

Or “motives.”

Or “advantage.”

Or possibly, “for those seeking death.”

Or “nagging.”

Or “The soul of the wicked one.”

Or “he knows what to do.”

Lit., “a bribe in the bosom.”

Or “loves pleasure.”

Or “nagging.”

Lit., “swallow.”

Or “prevail over.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “along with shameful conduct!”

Lit., “speak forever.”

Or “who makes his way sure.”

^ (Prov. 22:1-26:28) A good name* is to be chosen rather than great wealth; To be respected* is better than silver and gold.  2 The rich and the poor have this in common:* Jehovah made them both.  3 The shrewd one sees the danger and conceals himself, But the inexperienced keep right on going and suffer the consequences.*  4 The result of humility and the fear of Jehovah Is riches and glory and life.  5 Thorns and traps are in the crooked man’s path, But whoever values his life* keeps far away from them.  6 Train a boy* in the way he should go; Even when he grows old he will not depart from it.  7 The rich one rules the poor, And the borrower is a slave to the lender.  8 Whoever sows unrighteousness will reap disaster, And the rod of his fury will come to its end.  9 The generous person* will be blessed, For he shares his food with the poor. 10 Drive away the scornful man, And contention will disappear; Disputes* and insults will cease. 11 The one who loves a pure heart and whose speech is gracious Will have the king as his friend. 12 The eyes of Jehovah safeguard knowledge, But He overturns the words of the treacherous. 13 The lazy one says: “There is a lion outside! I will be killed in the middle of the public square!” 14 The mouth of wayward* women is a deep pit. The one condemned by Jehovah will fall into it. 15 Foolishness is bound up in the heart of a boy,* But the rod of discipline will remove it far from him. 16 The one defrauding the poor to increase his wealth And the one giving gifts to the rich Will end up in poverty. 17 Incline your ear and listen to the words of the wise, In order to apply your heart to my knowledge, 18 For it is pleasant to keep them deep within you, So that all of them may constantly be on your lips. 19 For your confidence to be in Jehovah, I am giving you knowledge today. 20 Have I not already written you, Imparting advice and knowledge, 21 To teach you true and reliable words, So that you can return with an accurate report to the one who sent you? 22 Do not rob the poor man because he is poor, And do not crush the lowly man in the city gate, 23 For Jehovah himself will plead their cause And he will take the life* of those who defraud them. 24 Do not keep company with a hot-tempered man Or get involved with one disposed to rage, 25 So that you never learn his ways And ensnare yourself.* 26 Do not be among those who shake hands in a pledge, Who put up security for loans. 27 If you have nothing to pay, Your bed will be taken right out from under you! 28 Do not move an ancient boundary marker That your forefathers put in place. 29 Have you seen a man skillful at his work? He will stand before kings; He will not stand before common men.

23 When you sit down to eat with a king, Carefully consider what is before you;  2 Put a knife to your throat* If you have a large appetite.*  3 Do not crave his delicacies, For it is deceptive food.  4 Do not wear yourself out to gain wealth. Stop and show understanding.*  5 When you cast your eyes on it, it is not there, For it will surely sprout wings like an eagle and fly off into the sky.  6 Do not eat the food of a stingy person;* Do not crave his delicacies,  7 For he is like one keeping accounts.* “Eat and drink,” he says to you, but he does not mean it.*  8 You will vomit up the morsels you have eaten And will have wasted your compliments.  9 Do not speak in the ears of the stupid one, For he will despise the wisdom of your words. 10 Do not move an ancient boundary marker Or encroach on the field of the fatherless. 11 For their Defender* is strong; He will take up their cause against you. 12 Apply your heart to discipline And your ear to the sayings of knowledge. 13 Do not hold back discipline from a boy.* If you strike him with the rod, he will not die. 14 With the rod you should strike him, In order to save him* from the Grave.* 15 My son, if your heart becomes wise, Then my own heart will rejoice. 16 My innermost being* will find joy When your lips speak what is right. 17 Let your heart not envy sinners, But be in the fear of Jehovah all day long, 18 For then you will have a future And your hope will not be cut off. 19 Listen, my son, and become wise, And direct your heart in the right way. 20 Do not be among those who drink too much wine, Among those who gorge themselves on meat, 21 For a drunkard and a glutton will come to poverty, And drowsiness will clothe one with rags. 22 Listen to your father who caused your birth, And do not despise your mother just because she has grown old. 23 Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding. 24 The father of a righteous one will surely be joyful; Whoever fathers a wise son will rejoice in him. 25 Your father and your mother will rejoice, And she who gave birth to you will be joyful. 26 My son, do give your heart to me, And may your eyes take pleasure in my ways. 27 For a prostitute is a deep pit, And an immoral* woman is a narrow well. 28 She lies in wait like a robber; She increases the number of unfaithful men. 29 Who has woe? Who has uneasiness? Who has quarrels? Who has complaints? Who has wounds for no reason? Who has bleary* eyes? 30 Those lingering long over wine; Those searching out* mixed wine. 31 Do not look at the wine’s red color As it sparkles in the cup and goes down smoothly, 32 For in the end it bites like a serpent, And it secretes poison like a viper. 33 Your eyes will see strange things, And your heart will speak perverse things. 34 And you will be like one lying down in the middle of the sea, Like one lying at the top of a ship’s mast. 35 You will say: “They have struck me, but I did not feel it.* They beat me, but I did not know it. When will I wake up? I need another drink.”*

24 Do not envy evil men, And do not crave their company,  2 For their heart meditates on violence, And their lips speak of trouble.  3 By wisdom a house* is built up, And by discernment it is made secure.  4 By knowledge its rooms are filled With all sorts of precious and pleasant treasures.  5 A wise man is powerful, And with knowledge a man increases his power.  6 By skillful direction* you will wage your war, And through many advisers* there is victory.*  7 True wisdom is unattainable for a fool; He has nothing to say in the city gate.  8 Anyone who plots evil Will be called a master schemer.  9 Foolish schemes* are sinful, And people detest a ridiculer. 10 If you become discouraged in the day of distress,* Your strength will be meager. 11 Rescue those who are being taken away to death, And hold back those staggering to the slaughter. 12 If you say, “But we did not know about this,” Does not the One who examines hearts* discern it? Yes, the One who watches you* will know And will repay each man according to his activity. 13 My son, eat honey, because it is good; Honey from the comb is sweet to the taste. 14 Likewise, know that wisdom is good for you.* If you find it, you will have a future And your hope will not be cut off. 15 Do not wickedly lie in ambush near the home of the righteous one; Do not destroy his place of rest. 16 For the righteous one may fall seven times, and he will get up again, But the wicked will be made to stumble by calamity. 17 When your enemy falls, do not rejoice, And when he stumbles, do not let your heart be joyful; 18 Otherwise, Jehovah will see and be displeased, And He will turn away his anger from him.* 19 Do not be upset* because of evil men; Do not envy wicked people, 20 For there is no future for anyone evil; The lamp of the wicked will be extinguished. 21 My son, fear Jehovah and the king. And do not associate with dissenters,* 22 For their disaster will arise suddenly. Who knows what ruin both* will bring upon them? 23 These sayings also belong to the wise: Partiality in judgment is not good. 24 Whoever says to the wicked one, “You are righteous,” Will be cursed by the peoples and denounced by the nations. 25 But it will go well for those reproving him; Blessings of good things will come upon them. 26 People will kiss the lips of the one replying honestly.* 27 Prepare your outside work, and get everything ready in the field; Then build your house.* 28 Do not testify against your neighbor without grounds. Do not use your lips to deceive others. 29 Do not say: “I will do to him just as he has done to me; I will repay him for what he did.”* 30 I passed by the field of the lazy one, By the vineyard of the man lacking good sense.* 31 I saw that it was overgrown with weeds; The ground was covered with nettles, And its stone wall was broken down. 32 I observed this and took it to heart; I saw it and learned this lesson:* 33 A little sleep, a little slumbering, A little folding of the hands to rest, 34 And your poverty will come like a bandit, And your want like an armed man.

25 These also are the proverbs of Solʹo·mon, which the men of Hez·e·kiʹah the king of Judah transcribed:*  2 It is the glory of God to keep a matter secret, And the glory of kings is to search through a matter.  3 As the heavens are high and the earth is deep, So the heart of kings is unsearchable.  4 Remove the dross from the silver, And it will emerge completely refined.  5 Remove the wicked one from the king’s presence, And his throne will be firmly established in righteousness.  6 Do not honor yourself before the king, And do not take a place among the prominent,  7 For it is better for him to say to you, “Come up here,” Than to humiliate you in the presence of a noble.  8 Do not rush into a legal dispute, For what will you do later if your neighbor humiliates you?  9 Plead your case with your neighbor, But do not reveal what you were told confidentially,* 10 So that the one listening will not put you to shame And you spread a bad report* that cannot be recalled. 11 Like apples of gold in silver carvings* Is a word spoken at the right time. 12 Like an earring of gold and an ornament of fine gold Is a wise reprover to the receptive ear. 13 Just like the coldness of snow on the day of harvest Is a faithful messenger to those who sent him, For he refreshes his master.* 14 Like clouds and wind that bring no rain Is a man who boasts about a gift never given.* 15 By patience a commander is won over, And a gentle* tongue can break a bone. 16 If you find honey, eat only what you need, For if you take too much, you may vomit it up. 17 Rarely set foot in your neighbor’s house, So that he does not get tired of you and hate you. 18 Like a war club and a sword and a sharp arrow Is a man bearing false witness against his neighbor. 19 Like a broken tooth or an unsteady foot Is confidence in an unreliable* person in times of trouble. 20 Like one who removes a garment on a cold day And like vinegar poured on soda* Is the one who sings songs to a gloomy heart. 21 If your enemy* is hungry, give him bread to eat; If he is thirsty, give him water to drink, 22 For you will be heaping burning coals on his head,* And Jehovah will reward you. 23 The north wind brings a downpour, And a gossiping tongue brings an angry face. 24 Better to dwell on a corner of the roof Than in the same house with a quarrelsome* wife. 25 Like cold water on a tired soul* Is a good report from a distant land. 26 Like a muddied spring and a ruined well Is a righteous person who gives in to* a wicked one. 27 It is not good to eat too much honey, Nor is it glorious to seek one’s own glory. 28 As a city broken through, without a wall, Is the man who cannot control his temper.*

26 Like snow in summer and rain at harvesttime, Honor is not fitting for someone stupid.  2 Just as a bird has reason to flee and a swallow to fly, So a curse does not come without a real reason.*  3 A whip is for the horse, a bridle is for the donkey, And the rod is for the back of stupid people.  4 Do not answer the stupid one according to his foolishness, So that you do not put yourself on his level.*  5 Answer the stupid one according to his foolishness, So that he does not think he is wise.  6 Like someone who cripples his own feet and harms himself* Is the one who entrusts matters to someone stupid.  7 Like the limp* legs of the lame, So is a proverb in the mouth of stupid people.  8 Like tying a stone to a sling, So is giving glory to someone stupid.  9 Like a thorn plant that comes into the hand of a drunkard, So is a proverb in the mouth of stupid people. 10 Like an archer who wounds at random,* So is the one who hires the stupid one or those passing by. 11 Like a dog that returns to its vomit, The stupid one repeats his foolishness. 12 Have you seen a man who thinks he is wise? There is more hope for someone stupid than for him. 13 The lazy one says: “There is a young lion in the road, A lion in the public square!” 14 A door keeps turning on its hinges,* And the lazy one on his bed. 15 The lazy one buries his hand in the banquet bowl, But he is too tired to bring it back to his mouth. 16 The lazy one thinks he is wiser Than seven people who give a sensible reply. 17 Like someone grabbing hold of a dog’s ears Is the one passing by who becomes furious about* a quarrel that is not his. 18 Like a madman who shoots fiery missiles, arrows, and death* 19 Is the man who plays a trick on his neighbor and says, “I was only joking!” 20 Where there is no wood, the fire goes out, And where there is no slanderer, quarreling ceases. 21 As charcoal for the embers and wood for the fire, So a contentious man kindles a quarrel. 22 The words of a slanderer are like tasty morsels;* They are gulped right down into the stomach. 23 Like a silver glazing over a piece of earthenware Are affectionate words from* an evil heart. 24 The one who hates others disguises it with his lips, But inside he harbors deceit. 25 Although he speaks graciously, do not trust him, For there are seven detestable things in his heart.* 26 Though his hatred is concealed by deceit, His evil will be exposed in the congregation. 27 The one who digs a pit will fall into it, And whoever rolls away a stone—it will come back on him. 28 A lying tongue hates those crushed by it, And a flattering mouth causes ruin.

Or “A good reputation.” Lit., “A name.”

Lit., “Favor.”

Lit., “meet together.”

Or “penalty.”

Or “soul.”

Or “child; youth.”

Lit., “He with a good eye.”

Or “Lawsuits.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “child; youth.”

Or “rob the soul.”

Or “your soul.”

Or “Restrain yourself.”

Or “a soul full of desire.”

Or possibly, “Cease from your own understanding.”

Or “of anyone whose eye is evil.”

Or “calculating in his soul.”

Lit., “his heart is not with you.”

Lit., “Redeemer.”

Or “child; youth.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Lit., “My kidneys.”

Or “Acquire.”

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “dullness of.”

Or “who gather to try out.”

Or “I felt no pain.”

Or “I will seek it again.”

Or “household.”

Or “wise guidance.”

Or “counselors.”

Or “success; salvation.”

Or “The schemes of a fool.”

Or “in times of trouble.”

Or “motives.”

Or “your soul.”

Or “is sweet to your soul.”

That is, the enemy.

Or “show yourself heated up.”

Or “those who are for a change.”

That is, Jehovah and the king.

Or possibly, “Replying in a straightforward way is like giving a kiss.”

Or “household.”

Or “I will get even with him.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Lit., “I took the discipline:”

Or “copied and compiled.”

Or “the secrets of others.”

Or “a malicious rumor.”

Or “settings.”

Or “the soul of his master.”

Lit., “a gift of falsehood.”

Or “mild.”

Or possibly, “a treacherous.”

Or “alkali.”

Lit., “the one hating you.”

That is, to soften the person and melt his hardness.

Or “nagging.”

See Glossary.

Or “compromises with.” Lit., “staggers before.”

Or “who has no restraint for his spirit.”

Or possibly, “So an undeserved curse does not come to pass.”

Or “So that you do not make yourself his equal.”

Lit., “drinks violence.”

Or “dangling.”

Or “who wounds everyone.”

Or “pivot.”

Or possibly, “who meddles in.”

Or “deadly arrows.”

Or “like things to be swallowed greedily.”

Lit., “fervent lips with.”

Or “For his heart is completely detestable.”

^ (Prov. 22:1-21) A good name* is to be chosen rather than great wealth; To be respected* is better than silver and gold.  2 The rich and the poor have this in common:* Jehovah made them both.  3 The shrewd one sees the danger and conceals himself, But the inexperienced keep right on going and suffer the consequences.*  4 The result of humility and the fear of Jehovah Is riches and glory and life.  5 Thorns and traps are in the crooked man’s path, But whoever values his life* keeps far away from them.  6 Train a boy* in the way he should go; Even when he grows old he will not depart from it.  7 The rich one rules the poor, And the borrower is a slave to the lender.  8 Whoever sows unrighteousness will reap disaster, And the rod of his fury will come to its end.  9 The generous person* will be blessed, For he shares his food with the poor. 10 Drive away the scornful man, And contention will disappear; Disputes* and insults will cease. 11 The one who loves a pure heart and whose speech is gracious Will have the king as his friend. 12 The eyes of Jehovah safeguard knowledge, But He overturns the words of the treacherous. 13 The lazy one says: “There is a lion outside! I will be killed in the middle of the public square!” 14 The mouth of wayward* women is a deep pit. The one condemned by Jehovah will fall into it. 15 Foolishness is bound up in the heart of a boy,* But the rod of discipline will remove it far from him. 16 The one defrauding the poor to increase his wealth And the one giving gifts to the rich Will end up in poverty. 17 Incline your ear and listen to the words of the wise, In order to apply your heart to my knowledge, 18 For it is pleasant to keep them deep within you, So that all of them may constantly be on your lips. 19 For your confidence to be in Jehovah, I am giving you knowledge today. 20 Have I not already written you, Imparting advice and knowledge, 21 To teach you true and reliable words, So that you can return with an accurate report to the one who sent you?

Or “A good reputation.” Lit., “A name.”

Lit., “Favor.”

Lit., “meet together.”

Or “penalty.”

Or “soul.”

Or “child; youth.”

Lit., “He with a good eye.”

Or “Lawsuits.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “child; youth.”

^ ***sn song 88 Children Are a Trust From God***

Song 88

Children Are a Trust From God

(Psalm 127:3-5)

1. When a man becomes a father

And a woman has a child of her own,

They share a trust, they must remember,

That is not theirs, not theirs alone.

The gift they share is from Jehovah;

Of life and love he is the one true Source.

To parents he gives sure direction

That they may follow the wisest course.

(CHORUS)

A sacred trust you have been given;

A precious life is in your hands.

You can bestow the greatest favor;

Instruct your child in God’s commands.

2. All the words God has commanded—

They must always prove to be on your heart.

These words you’ll speak to sons and daughters;

This is your trust, this is your part.

To them you’ll speak along your roadway,

When you rise up and when you are at rest.

In years to come, may they remember,

May they be faithful, may they be blessed.

(CHORUS)

A sacred trust you have been given;

A precious life is in your hands.

You can bestow the greatest favor;

Instruct your child in God’s commands.

(See also Deut. 6:6, 7;[Eph. 6:4;][1 Tim. 4:16].)

^ (Ps. 127:3-5) Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.  4 Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, So are the sons of one’s youth.  5 Happy is the man who fills his quiver with them. They will not be put to shame, For they will speak with enemies in the city gate.

Or “Children.”

^ (Deut. 6:6, 7) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

^ (Eph. 6:4) And fathers, do not be irritating your children, but go on bringing them up in the discipline and admonition* of Jehovah.*

Or “instruction; guidance.” Lit., “putting mind in.”

See App. A5.

^ (1 Tim. 4:16) Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. Persevere in these things, for by doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

^ ***w08 4/1 p. 16 Raising Children in a Permissive World***

their innocence, or their clean standing before God is an essential way to show that you love them. In time, they will likely come to understand your motives, and they will appreciate your loving protection.

Directing the Arrow

Note that Psalm 127:4, 5 likens the parent to “a mighty man.” Does this mean that only a father can be effective in the parental role? Not at all. In fact, the principle of this illustration applies to both fathers and mothers—and to single parents as well. ([Proverbs 1:8]) The phrase “mighty man” suggests that a considerable amount of strength was required to shoot an arrow from a bow. In Bible times, bows were sometimes mounted with copper, and a soldier was said to ‘tread the bow,’ perhaps bracing the bow with his foot so that he could string it. (Jeremiah 50:14,[29]) Clearly, much energy and effort went into pulling that taut string back in order to shoot those arrows toward their mark!

Similarly, raising children requires considerable effort. They do not simply rear themselves, any more than an arrow launches itself toward its target. Sadly, many parents today seem unwilling to expend the kind of effort that is needed. They take the easy way out. They let television, school, and peers teach their children about right and wrong, about morals, about sex. They let their children have whatever they want. And when saying no seems like too much work, they simply say yes—often excusing their decision by saying that they do not want to hurt their children’s feelings. In reality, it is their permissiveness that will do their children real, lasting harm.

Raising children is hard work. Doing that work wholeheartedly with the guidance of God’s Word is certainly demanding, but the rewards are priceless. Parents magazine noted: “Studies . . . have found that children brought up by loving but authoritative parents—those who are supportive of their children yet maintain firm limits—excel academically, develop better social skills, feel good about themselves, and are happier overall than kids whose parents are either too lenient or excessively harsh.”

There is an even better reward. Earlier we considered the first part of Proverbs 22:6: “Train up a boy according to the way for him.” The verse continues with these heartwarming words: “Even when he grows old he will not turn aside from it.” Does this inspired proverb offer a guarantee of success? Not necessarily. Your child has free will and will grow up to exercise it. But this verse offers parents a loving assurance. What is that?

If you train your children according to the Bible’s counsel, you are creating the most favorable circumstances to bring about a marvelous result—seeing your children grow up to be happy, fulfilled, and responsible adults. (Proverbs 23:24) By all means, then, prepare those precious “arrows,” protect them, and expend yourself in directing them. You will never regret it.

^ (Ps. 127:4, 5) Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, So are the sons of one’s youth.  5 Happy is the man who fills his quiver with them. They will not be put to shame, For they will speak with enemies in the city gate.

^ (Prov. 1:8) Listen, my son, to the discipline of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother.

Or “law.”

^ (Jer. 50:14) Come against Babylon in battle formation on every side, All you who are bending* the bow. Shoot at her, spare no arrow, For it is against Jehovah that she has sinned.

Lit., “treading.”

^ (Jer. 50:29) Summon archers against Babylon, All who are bending* the bow. Camp all around her; let no one escape. Repay her according to her activity. Do to her just as she has done. For she has acted arrogantly against Jehovah, Against the Holy One of Israel.

Lit., “treading.”

^ (Prov. 22:6) Train a boy* in the way he should go; Even when he grows old he will not depart from it.

Or “child; youth.”

^ (Prov. 23:24) The father of a righteous one will surely be joyful; Whoever fathers a wise son will rejoice in him.

^ ***w07 6/1 p. 31 Questions From Readers***

Questions From Readers

Does Proverbs 22:6 guarantee that if Christian children are properly trained, they will not depart from the way of Jehovah?

This verse reads: “Train up a boy according to the way for him; even when he grows old he will not turn aside from it.” Just as the bending of a twig influences its growth into a tree, children who are properly trained are more inclined to continue to serve Jehovah when they grow up. As every parent knows, such training takes considerable time and effort. To make Christian disciples of their children, parents must carefully instruct, admonish, encourage, and discipline them as well as set a good example. They must do this consistently and lovingly for many years.

Does this mean, though, that if a child does turn away from serving Jehovah, parental training is at fault? In some cases, parents may have been deficient in their efforts to bring their children up in the discipline and mental-regulating of Jehovah. (Ephesians 6:4) On the other hand, the proverb is not a guarantee that good training will produce children who are faithful to God. Parents cannot mold their children into whatever they wish. Children, like adults, have free will and must ultimately choose their own course in life. (Deuteronomy 30:15, 16,[19]) Despite the most earnest efforts of parents, some children become unfaithful, as did Solomon, who wrote the verse we are considering. Even Jehovah had sons who proved unfaithful.

Thus, this scripture does not mean that in every case a child “will not turn aside from it” but that generally speaking this would be the result. What an encouragement this is to parents! Parents should take heart from knowing that their earnest efforts to train their children in the way of Jehovah will produce good results. Since their role is important and their influence is great, parents are encouraged to take their role seriously.—Deuteronomy 6:6, 7.

Even when children turn aside from serving Jehovah, parents who have been conscientious in training their children can entertain the hope that their children will come to their senses. Bible truth is powerful, and parental training is not quickly forgotten.—[Psalm 19:7].

^ (Prov. 22:6) Train a boy* in the way he should go; Even when he grows old he will not depart from it.

Or “child; youth.”

^ (Eph. 6:4) And fathers, do not be irritating your children, but go on bringing them up in the discipline and admonition* of Jehovah.*

Or “instruction; guidance.” Lit., “putting mind in.”

See App. A5.

^ (Deut. 30:15, 16) “See, I do put before you today life and good, and death and bad. 16 If you listen to the commandments of Jehovah your God that I am commanding you today, by loving Jehovah your God, by walking in his ways, and by keeping his commandments and his statutes and his judicial decisions, then you will live and multiply, and Jehovah your God will bless you in the land you are going to possess.

^ (Deut. 30:19) I take the heavens and the earth as witnesses against you today that I have put life and death before you, the blessing and the curse; and you must choose life so that you may live, you and your descendants,

^ (Deut. 6:6, 7) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

^ (Ps. 19:7) The law of Jehovah is perfect, restoring strength.* The reminder of Jehovah is trustworthy, making the inexperienced one wise.

Or “restoring (bringing back) the soul.”

^ ***w97 10/15 p. 32 Raising Moral Children—Is It Still Possible?***

Raising Moral Children—Is It Still Possible?

“WE NOW live in a very complex society, a very heterogeneous culture, where there is no uniform code of morality,” observes Robert Glossop of the Vanier Institute for the Family in Ottawa, Canada. With what result? A report in The Toronto Star newspaper says: “Teen pregnancies, youth violence and teen suicide are all on the increase.”

The problem extends beyond North America. Bill Damon, director of the Center for Human Development at Brown University in Rhode Island, U.S.A., has studied these issues in Britain and other European nations, as well as in Australia, Israel, and Japan. He points to the decline of churches, schools, and other institutions in providing guidance for the young. Our culture, he believes, “has lost touch with what children need to forge character and competence.” Citing parenting experts who teach that “discipline is hazardous to children’s health and well-being,” Damon maintains that this is “a recipe for raising wilful, disobedient children.”

What is it that youths of today need? They constantly need loving training that corrects the mind and heart. Different youths require different kinds of discipline. When motivated by love, discipline often can be conveyed by reasoning. That is why we are told at Proverbs 8:33 to “listen to discipline.” Some, though, are not “corrected by mere words.” For them, the appropriate punishment for disobedience, administered to the proper degree, may be needed. (Proverbs 17:10;[23:13, 14;][29:19]) In making this recommendation, the Bible is not endorsing angry whippings or severe beatings, which may bruise and injure a child. (Proverbs 16:32) Rather, a child should understand why he is being corrected and sense that it is because the parent is with him, on his side.—Compare Hebrews 12:6,[11].

Such practical and sound Biblical advice is highlighted in the book The Secret of Family Happiness.

^ (Prov. 8:33) Listen to discipline and become wise, And never neglect it.

^ (Prov. 17:10) A rebuke makes a deeper impression on one having understanding Than striking a stupid person a hundred times.

^ (Prov. 23:13, 14) Do not hold back discipline from a boy.* If you strike him with the rod, he will not die. 14 With the rod you should strike him, In order to save him* from the Grave.*

Or “child; youth.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 29:19) A servant will not let himself be corrected by words, For though he understands, he does not obey.

^ (Prov. 16:32) The one slow to anger is better than a mighty man, And the one controlling his temper* than one conquering a city.

Lit., “ruling over his spirit.”

^ (Heb. 12:6) for those whom Jehovah* loves he disciplines, in fact, he scourges* everyone whom he receives as a son.”

See App. A5.

Or “punishes.”

^ (Heb. 12:11) True, no discipline seems for the present to be joyous, but it is painful;* yet afterward, it yields the peaceable fruit of righteousness to those who have been trained by it.

Or “grievous.”

^ ***it-2 p. 818 Rod, Staff***

Parental authority. “Rod” is used also to symbolize the authority of parents over their children. The book of Proverbs makes many references to this authority, the term symbolizing all forms of discipline used, including the literal rod used for chastisement. The parent is actually responsible before God to exercise this rod, controlling the child. If the parent fails in this, he will bring ruination and death to his child and disgrace and God’s disapproval to himself also. ([Pr 10:1;][15:20;][17:25;][19:13]) “Foolishness is tied up with the heart of a boy; the rod of discipline is what will remove it far from him.” “Do not hold back discipline from the mere boy. In case you beat him with the rod, he will not die. With the rod you yourself should beat him, that you may deliver his very soul from Sheol itself.” ([Pr 22:15;][23:13, 14]) In fact, “the one holding back his rod is hating his son, but the one loving him is he that does look for him with discipline.”—[Pr 13:24;][19:18;][29:15;][1Sa 2:27-36].

^ (Prov. 10:1) Proverbs of Solʹo·mon. A wise son makes his father rejoice, But a foolish son is the grief of his mother.

^ (Prov. 15:20) A wise son makes his father rejoice, But a stupid man despises his mother.

^ (Prov. 17:25) A stupid son brings grief to his father And heartache* to the one who gave birth to him.

Lit., “bitterness.”

^ (Prov. 19:13) A stupid son brings adversity on his father, And a quarrelsome* wife is like a roof that never stops leaking.

Or “nagging.”

^ (Prov. 22:15) Foolishness is bound up in the heart of a boy,* But the rod of discipline will remove it far from him.

Or “child; youth.”

^ (Prov. 23:13, 14) Do not hold back discipline from a boy.* If you strike him with the rod, he will not die. 14 With the rod you should strike him, In order to save him* from the Grave.*

Or “child; youth.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 13:24) Whoever holds back his rod* hates his son, But the one who loves him disciplines him diligently.*

Or “discipline; punishment.”

Or possibly, “promptly.”

^ (Prov. 19:18) Discipline your son while there is hope, And do not become responsible for* his death.

Or “desire.” Lit., “raise your soul to.”

^ (Prov. 29:15) The rod* and reproof impart wisdom, But a child left unrestrained brings shame on his mother.

Or “discipline; punishment.”

^ (1 Sam. 2:27-36) A man of God came to Eʹli and said to him: “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Did I not plainly reveal myself to your father’s house while they were in Egypt as slaves to the house of Pharʹaoh? 28 And he was chosen out of all the tribes of Israel to serve as my priest and to go up on my altar to make sacrifices, to offer incense,* and to bear an ephʹod before me; and I gave to the house of your forefather all the offerings made by fire of the Israelites.* 29 Why do you men scorn* my sacrifice and my offering that I have commanded in my place of dwelling? Why do you keep honoring your sons more than me by fattening yourselves from the best portions of every offering of my people Israel? 30 “‘That is why the word of Jehovah the God of Israel is: “I did indeed say that your house and the house of your forefather would always walk before me.” But now Jehovah declares: “It is unthinkable, on my part, because those honoring me I will honor, but those despising me will be treated with contempt.” 31 Look! Days are coming when I will cut off your strength* and that of your father’s house, so that no man in your house will live to old age. 32 And you will look upon a rival in my dwelling amid all the good that is done to Israel, and never again will there be an old man in your house. 33 The man of yours whom I do not cut off from serving at my altar will cause your eyes to fail and will bring you grief,* but the greater number of your house will die by the sword of men. 34 And what happens to your two sons, Hophʹni and Phinʹe·has, will be the sign for you: On one day both of them will die. 35 Then I will raise up for myself a faithful priest. He will act in harmony with what is my heart’s desire;* and I will build for him a lasting house, and he will walk before my anointed one always. 36 Anyone who remains in your house will come and bow down to him for the payment of money and a loaf of bread, and will say: “Assign me, please, to one of the priestly offices to eat a piece of bread.”’”

Or possibly, “to make sacrificial smoke billow up.”

Lit., “sons of Israel.”

Lit., “kick at.”

Lit., “arm.”

Or “will cause your soul to pine away.”

Or “is in my heart and in my soul.”

^ ***w04 6/15 p. 14 Rightly Value Your Gift of Life***

1. What evidence is there that we put a high value on life?

IF YOU were asked to put a value on your life, what would it be? We highly value life—our own and that of others. As evidence of that, we may go to a physician for care when we are sick or for regular checkups. We want to stay alive and healthy. Even most who are old or disabled do not want to die; they want to stay alive.

2, 3. (a) Proverbs 23:22 highlights what obligation? (b) How is God involved in the obligation mentioned at Proverbs 23:22?

2 Your evaluation of life affects your relationships with others. For example, God’s Word directs: “Listen to your father who caused your birth, and do not despise your mother just because she has grown old.” (Proverbs 23:22) To “listen” means more than just to hear words; this proverb means to hear and then to obey. (Exodus 15:26; Deuteronomy 7:12;[13:18;][15:5;] Joshua 22:2;[Psalm 81:13]) What reason does God’s Word give for listening? It is not just that your father and mother are older than you or have more experience. The reason given is that they “caused your birth.” Some versions render this verse: “Listen to your father who gave you life.” Understandably, if you value your life, you feel an obligation to the source of that life.

3 Of course, if you are a true Christian, you recognize Jehovah as the ultimate Source of your life. By him you “have life” itself; you can “move,” act as a sentient creature; and you now “exist” and can think about or plan for the future, including permanent life. ([Acts 17:28;][Psalm 36:9;] Ecclesiastes 3:11) In line with Proverbs 23:22, it is right to “listen” to God obediently, desirous of grasping and acting on his view of life rather than preferring any other assessment of life.

^ (Prov. 23:22) Listen to your father who caused your birth, And do not despise your mother just because she has grown old.

^ (Prov. 23:22) Listen to your father who caused your birth, And do not despise your mother just because she has grown old.

^ par. 2 (Prov. 23:22) Listen to your father who caused your birth, And do not despise your mother just because she has grown old.

^ par. 2 (Ex. 15:26) He said: “If you will strictly listen to the voice of Jehovah your God and will do what is right in his eyes and will pay attention to his commandments and keep all his regulations, I will not bring upon you any of the diseases that I brought upon the Egyptians, for I, Jehovah, am healing you.”

^ par. 2 (Deut. 7:12) “If you continue listening to these judicial decisions and you observe them and carry them out, Jehovah your God will keep the covenant and the loyal love about which he swore to your forefathers.

^ par. 2 (Deut. 13:18) For you should obey* Jehovah your God by keeping all his commandments that I am commanding you today, thus doing what is right in the eyes of Jehovah your God.

Or “listen to the voice of.”

^ par. 2 (Deut. 15:5) but only if you strictly obey the voice of Jehovah your God and carefully observe all this commandment that I am giving you today.

^ par. 2 (Josh. 22:2) and said to them: “You have done all that Moses the servant of Jehovah commanded you, and you have obeyed my voice in all that I commanded you.

^ par. 2 (Ps. 81:13) If only my people would listen to me, If only Israel would walk in my ways!

^ par. 3 (Acts 17:28) For by him we have life and move and exist, even as some of your own poets have said, ‘For we are also his children.’*

Or “progeny.”

^ par. 3 (Ps. 36:9) With you is the source of life; By your light we can see light.

^ par. 3 (Eccl. 3:11) He has made everything beautiful* in its time. He has even put eternity in their heart; yet mankind will never find out the work that the true God has made from start to finish.

Or “well-arranged; proper; appropriate.”

^ par. 3 (Prov. 23:22) Listen to your father who caused your birth, And do not despise your mother just because she has grown old.

^ ***w00 6/15 p. 21 “All You Are Brothers”***

13. What is the Bible’s view of the elderly in a family?

13 Showing honor to family members goes beyond dignifying one’s wife and children. “When old, obey your children,” says a Japanese proverb. The point of that proverb is that elderly parents should refrain from exceeding their parental authority and should take notice of what their grown children say. While it is Scriptural for parents to honor their children by giving them a hearing ear, the children should not display a disrespectful attitude toward older members of the family. “Do not despise your mother just because she has grown old,” says Proverbs 23:22. King Solomon lived up to this proverb and honored his mother when she approached him to make a petition. Solomon had a throne set to the right of his own and listened to what his elderly mother, Bath-sheba, had to tell him.—1 Kings 2:19, 20.

^ par. 13 (Prov. 23:22) Listen to your father who caused your birth, And do not despise your mother just because she has grown old.

^ par. 13 (1 Ki. 2:19, 20) So Bath-sheʹba went in to King Solʹo·mon to speak to him for Ad·o·niʹjah. At once the king rose to meet her and bowed down to her. Then he sat down on his throne and had a throne set for the king’s mother, so that she could sit at his right. 20 She then said: “There is one small request that I am making of you. Do not turn me away.” So the king said to her: “Make it, my mother; for I will not turn you away.”

^ ***w13 3/15 pp. 4-5 For Those Loving Jehovah, “There Is No Stumbling Block”***

IF YOU STUMBLE, STAY IN THE RACE

5, 6. (a) How is there “no stumbling block” for a Christian, and what will help him to “get up”? (b) Why do some not recover after stumbling?

5 Perhaps you have used the words “stumble” and “fall” interchangeably to describe a spiritual condition. These Bible expressions can, but do not always, have the same sense. For instance, notice the wording of Proverbs 24:16: “The righteous one may fall even seven times, and he will certainly get up; but the wicked ones will be made to stumble by calamity.”

6 Jehovah will not allow those trusting in him to stumble or to experience a fall—an adversity or a setback in their worship—from which they cannot recover. We are assured that Jehovah will help us “get up” so that we can continue giving him our utmost devotion. How comforting that is for all who love Jehovah deeply from the heart! The wicked do not have the same desire to get up. They do not seek the help of God’s holy spirit and his people, or they refuse such help when offered to them. In contrast, for those ‘loving Jehovah’s law,’ no stumbling block exists that can permanently knock them out of the race for life.—Read Psalm 119:165.

7, 8. How can one “fall” and yet have God’s favor?

7 Some lapse into minor sin—even repeatedly—because of some weakness. But they are still righteous in Jehovah’s eyes if they continue to “get up,” that is, sincerely repent and strive to resume a course of loyal service. We can see that from the way God dealt with ancient Israel. (Isa. 41:9, 10) Proverbs 24:16, quoted earlier, rather than emphasizing the negative—our ‘falling’—focuses on the positive, our ‘getting up’ with the help of our merciful God. (Read Isaiah 55:7.) Expressing their confidence in us, Jehovah God and Jesus Christ kindly encourage us to “get up.”—[Ps. 86:5;][John 5:19].

8 Even if a runner stumbles or falls in a marathon, he may have time to recover and finish the course if he acts with urgency. In our race for everlasting life, we do not know the “day and hour” when the end of the race will come. ([Matt. 24:36]) Still, the less we stumble, the more likely we are to keep a steady pace, stay in the race, and finish it successfully. So how can we avoid stumbling?

^ par. 5 (Prov. 24:16) For the righteous one may fall seven times, and he will get up again, But the wicked will be made to stumble by calamity.

^ par. 6 (Ps. 119:165) Abundant peace belongs to those who love your law; Nothing can make them stumble.*

Or “For them there is no stumbling block.”

^ par. 7 (Isa. 41:9, 10) You, whom I took from the ends of the earth, And you, whom I called from its most distant parts. I said to you, ‘You are my servant; I have chosen you; I have not rejected you. 10 Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.’

^ par. 7 (Prov. 24:16) For the righteous one may fall seven times, and he will get up again, But the wicked will be made to stumble by calamity.

^ par. 7 (Isa. 55:7) Let the wicked man leave his way And the evil man his thoughts; Let him return to Jehovah, who will have mercy on him, To our God, for he will forgive in a large way.*

Or “will freely forgive.”

^ par. 7 (Ps. 86:5) For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive; You abound in loyal love for all those who call on you.

^ par. 7 (John 5:19) Therefore, in response Jesus said to them: “Most truly I say to you, the Son cannot do a single thing of his own initiative, but only what he sees the Father doing. For whatever things that One does, these things the Son does also in like manner.

^ par. 8 (Matt. 24:36) “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father.

^ ***w09 10/15 p. 12 Questions From Readers***

In giving advice to a young man, the writer of Proverbs states: “Prepare your work out of doors, and make it ready for yourself in the field. Afterward you must also build up your household.” What point is being made in this inspired proverb? That a man should prepare properly before he gets married and starts his own family, recognizing the responsibilities that come with such a commitment.

^ ***lv pp. 179-181 Find Enjoyment for Your Hard Work***

18. Why is it not easy to maintain spiritual balance?

18 Maintaining spiritual balance is not easy in these “last days” with their “critical times hard to deal with.” (2 Timothy 3:1) Finding a job and holding on to it can be a real challenge. As true Christians, we recognize the importance of working hard to provide for our family. But if we are not careful, pressure in the workplace or the world’s infectious materialistic thinking could interfere with our spiritual pursuits. (1 Timothy 6:9, 10) Let us consider how we can keep our balance, making sure of “the more important things.”—Philippians 1:10.

19. Why is Jehovah worthy of our full trust, and what does such trust help us to avoid?

19 Place your full trust in Jehovah. (Read Proverbs 3:5, 6.) Is he not worthy of such trust? After all, he cares for us. ([1 Peter 5:7]) He knows our needs better than we do, and his hand is never short. ([Psalm 37:25]) We therefore do well to listen when his Word reminds us: “Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things. For [God] has said: ‘I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.’” ([Hebrews 13:5]) Many full-time servants can testify to God’s ability to provide life’s necessities. If we fully trust that Jehovah will care for us, we will avoid becoming unduly anxious about providing for our family. (Matthew 6:25-32) We will not allow secular work to cause us to neglect spiritual activities, such as preaching the good news and attending meetings.—Matthew 24:14; Hebrews 10:24, 25.

^ par. 18 (2 Tim. 3:1) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.

^ par. 18 (1 Tim. 6:9, 10) But those who are determined to be rich fall into temptation and a snare and many senseless and harmful desires that plunge men into destruction and ruin. 10 For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

^ par. 18 (Phil. 1:10) that you may make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others up to the day of Christ;

^ par. 19 (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

^ par. 19 (1 Pet. 5:7) while you throw all your anxiety* on him, because he cares for you.

Or “cares; worries.”

^ par. 19 (Ps. 37:25) I was once young and now I am old, But I have not seen anyone righteous abandoned, Nor his children looking for bread.*

Or “food.”

^ par. 19 (Heb. 13:5) Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things. For he has said: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.”

^ par. 19 (Matt. 6:25-32) “On this account I say to you: Stop being anxious about your lives* as to what you will eat or what you will drink, or about your bodies as to what you will wear. Does not life* mean more than food and the body than clothing? 26 Observe intently the birds of heaven; they do not sow seed or reap or gather into storehouses, yet your heavenly Father feeds them. Are you not worth more than they are? 27 Who of you by being anxious can add one cubit* to his life span? 28 Also, why are you anxious about clothing? Take a lesson from the lilies of the field, how they grow; they do not toil, nor do they spin; 29 but I tell you that not even Solʹo·mon in all his glory was arrayed as one of these. 30 Now if this is how God clothes the vegetation of the field that is here today and tomorrow is thrown into the oven, will he not much rather clothe you, you with little faith? 31 So never be anxious and say, ‘What are we to eat?’ or, ‘What are we to drink?’ or, ‘What are we to wear?’ 32 For all these are the things the nations are eagerly pursuing. Your heavenly Father knows that you need all these things.

Or “souls.”

Or “the soul.”

See App. B14.

^ par. 19 (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ par. 19 (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ ***sn song 101 Making Known the Kingdom Truth***

Song 101

Making Known the Kingdom Truth

(Acts 20:20, 21)

1. There was a time we did not know

The way a Christian ought to go.

Then Jehovah sent the light,

His Kingdom truth so clear and bright.

Our Father’s will we then could see

To serve the grand Theocracy,

To declare Jehovah’s fame,

And help to glorify his holy name.

We witness now to all we meet,

From door to door and on the street.

We take the time to help them see;

We teach the truth that sets men free.

And as we strive in ev’ry land

Jehovah’s worship to expand,

May we serve our God as one

Until Jehovah says the work is done.

(See also [Josh. 9:9;][Isa. 24:15;][John 8:12,][32].)

^ (Acts 20:20, 21) while I did not hold back from telling you any of the things that were profitable* nor from teaching you publicly and from house to house. 21 But I thoroughly bore witness both to Jews and to Greeks about repentance toward God and faith in our Lord Jesus.

Or “for your good.”

^ (Josh. 9:9) At this they said to him: “Your servants have come from a very distant land out of regard for the name of Jehovah your God, because we have heard about his fame and about all he did in Egypt

^ (Isa. 24:15) That is why they will glorify Jehovah in the region of light;* In the islands of the sea they will glorify the name of Jehovah the God of Israel.

Or “in the east.”

^ (John 8:12) Then Jesus spoke again to them, saying: “I am the light of the world. Whoever follows me will by no means walk in darkness, but will possess the light of life.”

^ (John 8:32) and you will know the truth, and the truth will set you free.”

^ ***kr pp. 32-35 Jehovah Reveals His Purpose***

1, 2. How has Jehovah revealed his purpose for mankind?

CARING parents include their children in discussions about family matters. They are discreet, however, about the amount of information that they share. They reveal only details that they feel their children are mature enough to absorb.

2 Similarly, Jehovah has progressively revealed his purpose for the human family. But he has done so only when he knew that the time was right. Consider a brief overview of how Jehovah has revealed truths about the Kingdom throughout history.

Why the Need for the Kingdom?

3, 4. Did Jehovah predestinate the path of human history? Explain.

3 Originally, the Messianic Kingdom was not part of Jehovah’s purpose. Why not? Because Jehovah did not predestinate the path of human history; after all, he created humans with free will. Thus, he told Adam and Eve his purpose for mankind, stating: “Be fruitful and become many, fill the earth and subdue it.” ([Gen. 1:28]) Jehovah also required that they respect his standards of good and bad. (Gen. 2:16, 17) Adam and Eve could have chosen to remain loyal. If they and their descendants had done so, we would not need the Kingdom ruled by Christ to fulfill God’s purpose. Right now, the globe would be teeming with perfect people, all worshipping Jehovah.

4 The rebellion of Satan, Adam, and Eve did not cause Jehovah to abandon his purpose to fill the earth with a perfect human family. Instead, Jehovah adapted his method of fulfilling it. His purpose is not like a train that must run on a certain track to reach its destination and can be derailed by the actions of others. Once Jehovah states his purpose, no force in the universe can prevent its fulfillment. (Read Isaiah 55:11.) If a challenge threatens to block one track, Jehovah uses another.* ([Ex. 3:14, 15]) When he sees fit, he informs his loyal servants of the new method he will use to accomplish his purpose.

5. How did Jehovah respond to the rebellion in Eden?

5 In response to the rebellion in Eden, Jehovah purposed to set up the Kingdom. ([Matt. 25:34]) At that dark point in human history, Jehovah began to shed light on the instrument that he would use to restore mankind and undo the hurt caused by Satan’s futile grab for power. ([Gen. 3:14-19]) Even so, Jehovah did not disclose details about the Kingdom all at once.

Jehovah Begins to Reveal Truths About the Kingdom

6. What did Jehovah promise, but what did he not reveal?

6 With the very first prophecy, Jehovah promised that a certain “offspring” would crush the serpent. (Read Genesis 3:15.) However, the identities of that offspring and the offspring of the serpent were not revealed at that time. In fact, Jehovah did not shed more light on such details for some 2,000 years.*

7. Why was Abraham chosen, and what key lesson do we learn from this?

7 Eventually, Jehovah chose Abraham as the one through whom the promised offspring would come. Abraham was chosen because he “listened to [Jehovah’s] voice.” ([Gen. 22:18]) We learn a key lesson from that fact—Jehovah reveals his purpose only to those who have a reverential fear of him.—Read Psalm 25:14.

8, 9. What facts about the promised offspring did Jehovah reveal to Abraham and Jacob?

8 When speaking to his friend Abraham through an angel, Jehovah for the first time revealed this vital fact about the promised offspring: He would be human. (Gen. 22:15-17;[Jas. 2:23]) But how would this human crush the serpent? Who was the serpent? Later revelations would shed light on those questions.

9 Jehovah determined that the promised offspring would come through Abraham’s grandson Jacob, a man who displayed great faith in God. (Gen. 28:13-22) By means of Jacob, Jehovah disclosed that the Promised One would be a descendant of Jacob’s son Judah. Jacob prophesied that this descendant of Judah would receive a “scepter,” a rod symbolizing royal authority, and that to this one ‘the obedience of the peoples would belong.’ ([Gen. 49:1,][10]) With that pronouncement, Jehovah indicated that the Promised One would become a ruler, a king.

10, 11. Why did Jehovah reveal his purpose to David and Daniel?

10 Some 650 years after Judah’s day, Jehovah revealed more about his purpose to King David, a descendant of Judah. Jehovah described David as “a man agreeable to his heart.” (1 Sam. 13:14;[17:12;][Acts 13:22]) Because David had a reverential fear of God, Jehovah chose to make a covenant with him, promising him that one of his descendants would rule forever.—[2 Sam. 7:8,][12-16].

11 About 500 years later, Jehovah used the prophet Daniel to disclose the exact year when this Anointed One, or Messiah, would appear on earth. ([Dan. 9:25]) Jehovah considered Daniel to be “someone very precious.” Why? Because Daniel deeply respected Jehovah and served him continually.—[Dan. 6:16;][9:22, 23].

12. What was Daniel told to do, and why?

12 Even though Jehovah used such faithful prophets as Daniel to record dozens of details about the promised offspring, the Messiah, it was not yet Jehovah’s time for his servants to understand the full significance of what he inspired them to write. For example, after being given a vision involving the establishment of God’s Kingdom, Daniel was told to seal up the prophecy until the time appointed by Jehovah. At that future time, true knowledge would “become abundant.”—[Dan. 12:4].

^ par. 3 (Gen. 1:28) Further, God blessed them, and God said to them: “Be fruitful and become many, fill the earth and subdue it, and have in subjection the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and every living creature that is moving on the earth.”

^ par. 3 (Gen. 2:16, 17) Jehovah God also gave this command to the man: “From every tree of the garden you may eat to satisfaction. 17 But as for the tree of the knowledge of good and bad, you must not eat from it, for in the day you eat from it you will certainly die.”

^ par. 4 (Isa. 55:11) So my word that goes out of my mouth will be.* It will not return to me without results, But it will certainly accomplish whatever is my delight,* And it will have sure success in what I send it to do.

Or “will prove to be.”

Or “my will.”

^ par. 4 (Ex. 3:14, 15) So God said to Moses: “I Will Become What I Choose* to Become.”* And he added: “This is what you are to say to the Israelites, ‘I Will Become has sent me to you.’” 15 Then God said once more to Moses: “This is what you are to say to the Israelites, ‘Jehovah the God of your forefathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has sent me to you.’ This is my name forever, and this is how I am to be remembered from generation to generation.

Or “Want.”

Or “I Will Prove to Be What I Will Prove to Be.” See App. A4.

^ par. 5 (Matt. 25:34) “Then the King will say to those on his right: ‘Come, you who have been blessed by my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the founding of the world.

^ par. 5 (Gen. 3:14-19) Then Jehovah God said to the serpent: “Because you have done this, you are the cursed one out of all the domestic animals and out of all the wild animals of the field. On your belly you will go, and you will eat dust all the days of your life. 15 And I will put enmity* between you and the woman and between your offspring* and her offspring.* He will crush* your head, and you will strike* him in the heel.” 16 To the woman he said: “I will greatly increase the pain of your pregnancy; in pain you will give birth to children, and your longing will be for your husband, and he will dominate you.” 17 And to Adam* he said: “Because you listened to your wife’s voice and ate from the tree concerning which I gave you this command, ‘You must not eat from it,’ cursed is the ground on your account. In pain you will eat its produce all the days of your life. 18 It will grow thorns and thistles for you, and you must eat the vegetation of the field. 19 In the sweat of your face you will eat bread* until you return to the ground, for out of it you were taken. For dust you are and to dust you will return.”

Or “hostility.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “bruise; strike.”

Or “bruise; crush.”

Meaning “Earthling Man; Mankind; Humankind.”

Or “food.”

^ par. 6 (Gen. 3:15) And I will put enmity* between you and the woman and between your offspring* and her offspring.* He will crush* your head, and you will strike* him in the heel.”

Or “hostility.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “bruise; strike.”

Or “bruise; crush.”

^ par. 7 (Gen. 22:18) And by means of your offspring* all nations of the earth will obtain a blessing for themselves because you have listened to my voice.’”

Lit., “seed.”

^ par. 7 (Ps. 25:14) Close friendship with Jehovah belongs to those who fear him, And he makes his covenant known to them.

^ par. 8 (Gen. 22:15-17) And Jehovah’s angel called to Abraham a second time from the heavens, 16 saying: “‘By myself I swear,’ declares Jehovah, ‘that because you have done this and you have not withheld your son, your only one, 17 I will surely bless you and I will surely multiply your offspring* like the stars of the heavens and like the grains of sand on the seashore, and your offspring* will take possession of the gate* of his enemies.

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “the cities.”

^ par. 8 (Jas. 2:23) and the scripture was fulfilled that says: “Abraham put faith in Jehovah,* and it was counted to him as righteousness,” and he came to be called Jehovah’s* friend.

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ par. 9 (Gen. 28:13-22) And look! there was Jehovah stationed above it, and he said: “I am Jehovah the God of Abraham your father and the God of Isaac. The land on which you are lying, to you I am going to give it and to your offspring.* 14 And your offspring* will certainly become like the dust particles of the earth, and you will spread abroad to the west and to the east and to the north and to the south, and by means of you and by means of your offspring* all the families of the ground will certainly be blessed.* 15 I am with you, and I will safeguard you wherever you go, and I will return you to this land. I will not leave you until I have done what I have promised you.” 16 Then Jacob awoke from his sleep and said: “Truly Jehovah is in this place, and I did not know it.” 17 And he grew fearful and added: “How awe-inspiring this place is! This can only be the house of God, and this is the gate of the heavens.” 18 So Jacob got up early in the morning and took the stone on which he had rested his head and set it up as a pillar and poured oil on top of it. 19 So he named that place Bethʹel,* but previously the city’s name was Luz. 20 Jacob then made a vow, saying: “If God will continue with me and will protect me on my journey and will give me bread to eat and garments to wear 21 and I return in peace to the house of my father, then Jehovah will certainly have proved to be my God. 22 And this stone that I have set up as a pillar will become a house of God, and without fail I will give you a tenth of everything you give to me.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “will obtain a blessing for themselves.”

Meaning “House of God.”

^ par. 9 (Gen. 49:1) And Jacob called his sons and said: “Gather yourselves together that I may tell you what will happen to you in the final part of the days.

^ par. 9 (Gen. 49:10) The scepter will not depart from Judah, neither the commander’s staff from between his feet, until Shiʹloh* comes, and to him the obedience of the peoples will belong.

Meaning “He Whose It Is; He to Whom It Belongs.”

^ par. 10 (1 Sam. 13:14) But now your kingdom will not last. Jehovah will find a man agreeable to his heart, and Jehovah will commission him as a leader over his people, because you did not obey what Jehovah commanded you.”

^ par. 10 (1 Sam. 17:12) Now David was the son of the Ephʹrath·ite from Bethʹle·hem of Judah named Jesʹse, who had eight sons and who in the days of Saul was already an old man.

^ par. 10 (Acts 13:22) After removing him, he raised up for them David as king, about whom he bore witness and said: ‘I have found David the son of Jesʹse a man agreeable to my heart; he will do all the things I desire.’

^ par. 10 (2 Sam. 7:8) Now say this to my servant David, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “I took you from the pastures, from following the flock, to become a leader over my people Israel.

^ par. 10 (2 Sam. 7:12-16) When your days come to an end and you are laid to rest with your forefathers, then I will raise up your offspring* after you, your own son,* and I will firmly establish his kingdom. 13 He is the one who will build a house for my name, and I will firmly establish the throne of his kingdom forever. 14 I will become his father, and he will become my son. When he does wrong, I will reprove him with the rod of men and with the strokes of the sons of men.* 15 My loyal love will not be taken away from him the way I took it away from Saul, whom I removed from before you. 16 Your house and your kingdom will be secure forever before you; your throne will be firmly established forever.”’”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “one who will come out of your inward parts.”

Or possibly, “Adam.”

^ par. 11 (Dan. 9:25) You should know and understand that from the issuing of the word to restore and to rebuild Jerusalem until Mes·siʹah* the Leader, there will be 7 weeks, also 62 weeks. She will be restored and rebuilt, with a public square and moat, but in times of distress.

Or “the Anointed One.”

^ par. 11 (Dan. 6:16) So the king gave the order, and they brought Daniel and threw him into the pit of lions. The king said to Daniel: “Your God whom you are continually serving will rescue you.”

^ par. 11 (Dan. 9:22, 23) And he gave me understanding, saying: “O Daniel, now I have come to give you insight and understanding. 23 When you began your entreaty the word went out, and I have come to report it to you, because you are someone very precious.* So consider the matter and understand the vision.

Or “very desirable; highly esteemed.”

^ par. 12 (Dan. 12:4) “As for you, Daniel, keep the words secret, and seal up the book until the time of the end. Many will rove about,* and the true knowledge will become abundant.”

Or “examine it [that is, the book] thoroughly.”

^ par. 4 God’s name is a form of the Hebrew verb meaning “to become.” Jehovah’s name implies that he is the Fulfiller of his promises. See the box “The Meaning of God’s Name,” in Chapter 4.

^ par. 6 Although this amount of time may seem extensive today, we must remember that human life spans used to be much longer; there were only four lifespans that overlapped from Adam to Abraham. Adam’s life overlapped the life of Lamech, Noah’s father. Lamech’s life overlapped that of Shem, Noah’s son. Shem’s life overlapped that of Abraham.—[Gen. 5:5,][31;][9:29;][11:10, 11;][25:7].

^ (Gen. 5:5) So all the days of Adam’s life amounted to 930 years, and then he died.

^ (Gen. 5:31) So all the days of Laʹmech amounted to 777 years, and then he died.

^ (Gen. 9:29) So all the days of Noah amounted to 950 years, and he died.

^ (Gen. 11:10, 11) This is the history of Shem. Shem was 100 years old when he became father to Ar·pachʹshad two years after the Flood. 11 After becoming father to Ar·pachʹshad, Shem continued to live 500 years. And he became father to sons and daughters.

^ (Gen. 25:7) The years of Abraham’s life were 175 years.

^ ***kr pp. 30-31 Kingdom Truth—Dispensing Spiritual Food***

SECTION 1

Kingdom Truth—Dispensing Spiritual Food

YOU see your Bible student’s eyes light up as he grasps the meaning of the scripture you have just read together. Slowly, he says, “Do you mean that the Bible teaches that we can live in Paradise forever—right here on this earth?” Your companion in the ministry smiles and says, “Well, what did you see in the Bible?” Overwhelmed, the student shakes his head in wonderment, saying, “I just can’t believe that I was never taught this before!” You recall that he said something similar just a few weeks ago when he learned for the first time that God’s name is Jehovah.

Have you ever had such an experience? Many of God’s people have. Few things can so vividly remind us of the precious gift we have been given—the knowledge of the truth! Stop and think: How did that gift come to you? In this section we will examine that question. The way that God’s people have progressively received spiritual enlightenment is a vivid proof that God’s Kingdom is real. For a century, its King, Jesus Christ, has been actively ensuring that God’s people are taught the truth.

^ ***snnw song 146 You Did It for Me***

Song 146

You Did It for Me

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

(Matthew 25:34-40)

Other sheep Jesus has, and they serve alongside

those anointed to be Christ’s heavenly bride.

All the things that are done

for their comfort and aid

are things he considers that must be repaid.

(CHORUS)

“If you comforted them, you comforted me.

If you did it for them, you did it for me.

Your labors for them were your labors for me.

You did it for them; you did it for me.

If you did it for them, you did it for me.”

“Yes, you comforted me in my hunger and thirst,

and whatever my need, you came to me first.”

“Tell us, when did we do this?”

these ones will reply.

The King will then answer them, telling them why:

(CHORUS)

“If you comforted them, you comforted me.

If you did it for them, you did it for me.

Your labors for them were your labors for me.

You did it for them; you did it for me.

If you did it for them, you did it for me.”

“You’ve been loyal to me, doing works that are fine,

as you preach alongside these brothers of mine.”

So the King will then say

to the sheep on his right:

“Inherit the earth and perfection of life.”

(CHORUS)

“If you comforted them, you comforted me.

If you did it for them, you did it for me.

Your labors for them were your labors for me.

You did it for them; you did it for me.

If you did it for them, you did it for me.”

(See also [Prov. 19:17;] Matt. 10:40-42; 2 Tim. 1:16, 17.)

^ (Matt. 25:34-40) “Then the King will say to those on his right: ‘Come, you who have been blessed by my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the founding of the world. 35 For I became hungry and you gave me something to eat; I was thirsty and you gave me something to drink. I was a stranger and you received me hospitably; 36 naked* and you clothed me. I fell sick and you looked after me. I was in prison and you visited me.’ 37 Then the righteous ones will answer him with the words: ‘Lord, when did we see you hungry and feed you, or thirsty and give you something to drink? 38 When did we see you a stranger and receive you hospitably, or naked and clothe you? 39 When did we see you sick or in prison and visit you?’ 40 In reply the King will say to them, ‘Truly I say to you, to the extent that you did it to one of the least of these my brothers, you did it to me.’

Or “not sufficiently dressed.”

^ (Prov. 19:17) The one showing favor to the lowly is lending to Jehovah, And He will repay* him for what he does.

Or “reward.”

^ (Matt. 10:40-42) “Whoever receives you receives me also, and whoever receives me receives also the One who sent me. 41 Whoever receives a prophet because he is a prophet will get a prophet’s reward, and whoever receives a righteous man because he is a righteous man will get a righteous man’s reward. 42 And whoever gives one of these little ones only a cup of cold water to drink because he is a disciple, I tell you truly, he will by no means lose his reward.”

^ (2 Tim. 1:16, 17) May the Lord grant mercy to the household of On·e·siphʹo·rus, for he often refreshed me, and he did not become ashamed of my prison chains. 17 On the contrary, when he was in Rome, he diligently looked for me and found me.

^ (Prov. 22:1-26:28) A good name* is to be chosen rather than great wealth; To be respected* is better than silver and gold.  2 The rich and the poor have this in common:* Jehovah made them both.  3 The shrewd one sees the danger and conceals himself, But the inexperienced keep right on going and suffer the consequences.*  4 The result of humility and the fear of Jehovah Is riches and glory and life.  5 Thorns and traps are in the crooked man’s path, But whoever values his life* keeps far away from them.  6 Train a boy* in the way he should go; Even when he grows old he will not depart from it.  7 The rich one rules the poor, And the borrower is a slave to the lender.  8 Whoever sows unrighteousness will reap disaster, And the rod of his fury will come to its end.  9 The generous person* will be blessed, For he shares his food with the poor. 10 Drive away the scornful man, And contention will disappear; Disputes* and insults will cease. 11 The one who loves a pure heart and whose speech is gracious Will have the king as his friend. 12 The eyes of Jehovah safeguard knowledge, But He overturns the words of the treacherous. 13 The lazy one says: “There is a lion outside! I will be killed in the middle of the public square!” 14 The mouth of wayward* women is a deep pit. The one condemned by Jehovah will fall into it. 15 Foolishness is bound up in the heart of a boy,* But the rod of discipline will remove it far from him. 16 The one defrauding the poor to increase his wealth And the one giving gifts to the rich Will end up in poverty. 17 Incline your ear and listen to the words of the wise, In order to apply your heart to my knowledge, 18 For it is pleasant to keep them deep within you, So that all of them may constantly be on your lips. 19 For your confidence to be in Jehovah, I am giving you knowledge today. 20 Have I not already written you, Imparting advice and knowledge, 21 To teach you true and reliable words, So that you can return with an accurate report to the one who sent you? 22 Do not rob the poor man because he is poor, And do not crush the lowly man in the city gate, 23 For Jehovah himself will plead their cause And he will take the life* of those who defraud them. 24 Do not keep company with a hot-tempered man Or get involved with one disposed to rage, 25 So that you never learn his ways And ensnare yourself.* 26 Do not be among those who shake hands in a pledge, Who put up security for loans. 27 If you have nothing to pay, Your bed will be taken right out from under you! 28 Do not move an ancient boundary marker That your forefathers put in place. 29 Have you seen a man skillful at his work? He will stand before kings; He will not stand before common men.

23 When you sit down to eat with a king, Carefully consider what is before you;  2 Put a knife to your throat* If you have a large appetite.*  3 Do not crave his delicacies, For it is deceptive food.  4 Do not wear yourself out to gain wealth. Stop and show understanding.*  5 When you cast your eyes on it, it is not there, For it will surely sprout wings like an eagle and fly off into the sky.  6 Do not eat the food of a stingy person;* Do not crave his delicacies,  7 For he is like one keeping accounts.* “Eat and drink,” he says to you, but he does not mean it.*  8 You will vomit up the morsels you have eaten And will have wasted your compliments.  9 Do not speak in the ears of the stupid one, For he will despise the wisdom of your words. 10 Do not move an ancient boundary marker Or encroach on the field of the fatherless. 11 For their Defender* is strong; He will take up their cause against you. 12 Apply your heart to discipline And your ear to the sayings of knowledge. 13 Do not hold back discipline from a boy.* If you strike him with the rod, he will not die. 14 With the rod you should strike him, In order to save him* from the Grave.* 15 My son, if your heart becomes wise, Then my own heart will rejoice. 16 My innermost being* will find joy When your lips speak what is right. 17 Let your heart not envy sinners, But be in the fear of Jehovah all day long, 18 For then you will have a future And your hope will not be cut off. 19 Listen, my son, and become wise, And direct your heart in the right way. 20 Do not be among those who drink too much wine, Among those who gorge themselves on meat, 21 For a drunkard and a glutton will come to poverty, And drowsiness will clothe one with rags. 22 Listen to your father who caused your birth, And do not despise your mother just because she has grown old. 23 Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding. 24 The father of a righteous one will surely be joyful; Whoever fathers a wise son will rejoice in him. 25 Your father and your mother will rejoice, And she who gave birth to you will be joyful. 26 My son, do give your heart to me, And may your eyes take pleasure in my ways. 27 For a prostitute is a deep pit, And an immoral* woman is a narrow well. 28 She lies in wait like a robber; She increases the number of unfaithful men. 29 Who has woe? Who has uneasiness? Who has quarrels? Who has complaints? Who has wounds for no reason? Who has bleary* eyes? 30 Those lingering long over wine; Those searching out* mixed wine. 31 Do not look at the wine’s red color As it sparkles in the cup and goes down smoothly, 32 For in the end it bites like a serpent, And it secretes poison like a viper. 33 Your eyes will see strange things, And your heart will speak perverse things. 34 And you will be like one lying down in the middle of the sea, Like one lying at the top of a ship’s mast. 35 You will say: “They have struck me, but I did not feel it.* They beat me, but I did not know it. When will I wake up? I need another drink.”*

24 Do not envy evil men, And do not crave their company,  2 For their heart meditates on violence, And their lips speak of trouble.  3 By wisdom a house* is built up, And by discernment it is made secure.  4 By knowledge its rooms are filled With all sorts of precious and pleasant treasures.  5 A wise man is powerful, And with knowledge a man increases his power.  6 By skillful direction* you will wage your war, And through many advisers* there is victory.*  7 True wisdom is unattainable for a fool; He has nothing to say in the city gate.  8 Anyone who plots evil Will be called a master schemer.  9 Foolish schemes* are sinful, And people detest a ridiculer. 10 If you become discouraged in the day of distress,* Your strength will be meager. 11 Rescue those who are being taken away to death, And hold back those staggering to the slaughter. 12 If you say, “But we did not know about this,” Does not the One who examines hearts* discern it? Yes, the One who watches you* will know And will repay each man according to his activity. 13 My son, eat honey, because it is good; Honey from the comb is sweet to the taste. 14 Likewise, know that wisdom is good for you.* If you find it, you will have a future And your hope will not be cut off. 15 Do not wickedly lie in ambush near the home of the righteous one; Do not destroy his place of rest. 16 For the righteous one may fall seven times, and he will get up again, But the wicked will be made to stumble by calamity. 17 When your enemy falls, do not rejoice, And when he stumbles, do not let your heart be joyful; 18 Otherwise, Jehovah will see and be displeased, And He will turn away his anger from him.* 19 Do not be upset* because of evil men; Do not envy wicked people, 20 For there is no future for anyone evil; The lamp of the wicked will be extinguished. 21 My son, fear Jehovah and the king. And do not associate with dissenters,* 22 For their disaster will arise suddenly. Who knows what ruin both* will bring upon them? 23 These sayings also belong to the wise: Partiality in judgment is not good. 24 Whoever says to the wicked one, “You are righteous,” Will be cursed by the peoples and denounced by the nations. 25 But it will go well for those reproving him; Blessings of good things will come upon them. 26 People will kiss the lips of the one replying honestly.* 27 Prepare your outside work, and get everything ready in the field; Then build your house.* 28 Do not testify against your neighbor without grounds. Do not use your lips to deceive others. 29 Do not say: “I will do to him just as he has done to me; I will repay him for what he did.”* 30 I passed by the field of the lazy one, By the vineyard of the man lacking good sense.* 31 I saw that it was overgrown with weeds; The ground was covered with nettles, And its stone wall was broken down. 32 I observed this and took it to heart; I saw it and learned this lesson:* 33 A little sleep, a little slumbering, A little folding of the hands to rest, 34 And your poverty will come like a bandit, And your want like an armed man.

25 These also are the proverbs of Solʹo·mon, which the men of Hez·e·kiʹah the king of Judah transcribed:*  2 It is the glory of God to keep a matter secret, And the glory of kings is to search through a matter.  3 As the heavens are high and the earth is deep, So the heart of kings is unsearchable.  4 Remove the dross from the silver, And it will emerge completely refined.  5 Remove the wicked one from the king’s presence, And his throne will be firmly established in righteousness.  6 Do not honor yourself before the king, And do not take a place among the prominent,  7 For it is better for him to say to you, “Come up here,” Than to humiliate you in the presence of a noble.  8 Do not rush into a legal dispute, For what will you do later if your neighbor humiliates you?  9 Plead your case with your neighbor, But do not reveal what you were told confidentially,* 10 So that the one listening will not put you to shame And you spread a bad report* that cannot be recalled. 11 Like apples of gold in silver carvings* Is a word spoken at the right time. 12 Like an earring of gold and an ornament of fine gold Is a wise reprover to the receptive ear. 13 Just like the coldness of snow on the day of harvest Is a faithful messenger to those who sent him, For he refreshes his master.* 14 Like clouds and wind that bring no rain Is a man who boasts about a gift never given.* 15 By patience a commander is won over, And a gentle* tongue can break a bone. 16 If you find honey, eat only what you need, For if you take too much, you may vomit it up. 17 Rarely set foot in your neighbor’s house, So that he does not get tired of you and hate you. 18 Like a war club and a sword and a sharp arrow Is a man bearing false witness against his neighbor. 19 Like a broken tooth or an unsteady foot Is confidence in an unreliable* person in times of trouble. 20 Like one who removes a garment on a cold day And like vinegar poured on soda* Is the one who sings songs to a gloomy heart. 21 If your enemy* is hungry, give him bread to eat; If he is thirsty, give him water to drink, 22 For you will be heaping burning coals on his head,* And Jehovah will reward you. 23 The north wind brings a downpour, And a gossiping tongue brings an angry face. 24 Better to dwell on a corner of the roof Than in the same house with a quarrelsome* wife. 25 Like cold water on a tired soul* Is a good report from a distant land. 26 Like a muddied spring and a ruined well Is a righteous person who gives in to* a wicked one. 27 It is not good to eat too much honey, Nor is it glorious to seek one’s own glory. 28 As a city broken through, without a wall, Is the man who cannot control his temper.*

26 Like snow in summer and rain at harvesttime, Honor is not fitting for someone stupid.  2 Just as a bird has reason to flee and a swallow to fly, So a curse does not come without a real reason.*  3 A whip is for the horse, a bridle is for the donkey, And the rod is for the back of stupid people.  4 Do not answer the stupid one according to his foolishness, So that you do not put yourself on his level.*  5 Answer the stupid one according to his foolishness, So that he does not think he is wise.  6 Like someone who cripples his own feet and harms himself* Is the one who entrusts matters to someone stupid.  7 Like the limp* legs of the lame, So is a proverb in the mouth of stupid people.  8 Like tying a stone to a sling, So is giving glory to someone stupid.  9 Like a thorn plant that comes into the hand of a drunkard, So is a proverb in the mouth of stupid people. 10 Like an archer who wounds at random,* So is the one who hires the stupid one or those passing by. 11 Like a dog that returns to its vomit, The stupid one repeats his foolishness. 12 Have you seen a man who thinks he is wise? There is more hope for someone stupid than for him. 13 The lazy one says: “There is a young lion in the road, A lion in the public square!” 14 A door keeps turning on its hinges,* And the lazy one on his bed. 15 The lazy one buries his hand in the banquet bowl, But he is too tired to bring it back to his mouth. 16 The lazy one thinks he is wiser Than seven people who give a sensible reply. 17 Like someone grabbing hold of a dog’s ears Is the one passing by who becomes furious about* a quarrel that is not his. 18 Like a madman who shoots fiery missiles, arrows, and death* 19 Is the man who plays a trick on his neighbor and says, “I was only joking!” 20 Where there is no wood, the fire goes out, And where there is no slanderer, quarreling ceases. 21 As charcoal for the embers and wood for the fire, So a contentious man kindles a quarrel. 22 The words of a slanderer are like tasty morsels;* They are gulped right down into the stomach. 23 Like a silver glazing over a piece of earthenware Are affectionate words from* an evil heart. 24 The one who hates others disguises it with his lips, But inside he harbors deceit. 25 Although he speaks graciously, do not trust him, For there are seven detestable things in his heart.* 26 Though his hatred is concealed by deceit, His evil will be exposed in the congregation. 27 The one who digs a pit will fall into it, And whoever rolls away a stone—it will come back on him. 28 A lying tongue hates those crushed by it, And a flattering mouth causes ruin.

Or “A good reputation.” Lit., “A name.”

Lit., “Favor.”

Lit., “meet together.”

Or “penalty.”

Or “soul.”

Or “child; youth.”

Lit., “He with a good eye.”

Or “Lawsuits.”

Lit., “strange.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “child; youth.”

Or “rob the soul.”

Or “your soul.”

Or “Restrain yourself.”

Or “a soul full of desire.”

Or possibly, “Cease from your own understanding.”

Or “of anyone whose eye is evil.”

Or “calculating in his soul.”

Lit., “his heart is not with you.”

Lit., “Redeemer.”

Or “child; youth.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Lit., “My kidneys.”

Or “Acquire.”

Lit., “foreign.” See Pr 2:16.

Or “dullness of.”

Or “who gather to try out.”

Or “I felt no pain.”

Or “I will seek it again.”

Or “household.”

Or “wise guidance.”

Or “counselors.”

Or “success; salvation.”

Or “The schemes of a fool.”

Or “in times of trouble.”

Or “motives.”

Or “your soul.”

Or “is sweet to your soul.”

That is, the enemy.

Or “show yourself heated up.”

Or “those who are for a change.”

That is, Jehovah and the king.

Or possibly, “Replying in a straightforward way is like giving a kiss.”

Or “household.”

Or “I will get even with him.”

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Lit., “I took the discipline:”

Or “copied and compiled.”

Or “the secrets of others.”

Or “a malicious rumor.”

Or “settings.”

Or “the soul of his master.”

Lit., “a gift of falsehood.”

Or “mild.”

Or possibly, “a treacherous.”

Or “alkali.”

Lit., “the one hating you.”

That is, to soften the person and melt his hardness.

Or “nagging.”

See Glossary.

Or “compromises with.” Lit., “staggers before.”

Or “who has no restraint for his spirit.”

Or possibly, “So an undeserved curse does not come to pass.”

Or “So that you do not make yourself his equal.”

Lit., “drinks violence.”

Or “dangling.”

Or “who wounds everyone.”

Or “pivot.”

Or possibly, “who meddles in.”

Or “deadly arrows.”

Or “like things to be swallowed greedily.”

Lit., “fervent lips with.”

Or “For his heart is completely detestable.”